<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book id="treeview-tutorial">
  <bookinfo>
    <date>September 1st, 2003</date>

    <title>GTK+ 2.0 Tree View Tutorial</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Tim-Philipp</firstname>

        <surname>Müller</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <abstract>
      <para>This is a tutorial on how to use the GTK (the GIMP Toolkit)
      GtkTreeView widget through its C interface.</para>

      <para>Please mail all comments and suggestions to <email>tim at
      centricular dot net</email></para>

      <para>A tarball of the tutorial for off-line reading including the
      example source codes is available here: <ulink
      url="treeview-tutorial.tar.gz">treeview-tutorial.tar.gz</ulink>.</para>

      <para>There is also a <ulink url="treeview-tutorial.pdf">version in PDF
      format</ulink> (for easier printing) and the raw <ulink
      url="treeview-tutorial-xml.tar.gz">docbook XML source
      document</ulink>.</para>

      <para>This tutorial is work-in-progress. The latest version can be found
      at <ulink url="http://scentric.net/tutorial/">
      http://scentric.net/tutorial/</ulink>.</para>

      <para>Some sections are a bit outdated (e.g. GtkTreeModelFilter has been
      in Gtk since 2.4), just haven't gotten around to rewrite them or update
      them. Sorry!</para>

      <para>Last updated: September 29th, 2006</para>
    </abstract>
  </bookinfo>

  <toc/>

  <chapter id="ch-TreeView">
    <title>Lists and Trees: the GtkTreeView Widget</title>

    <para><literal>GtkTreeView</literal> is a widget that displays single- or
    multi-columned lists and trees. It replaces the old Gtk+-1.2 GtkCList and
    GtkCTree widgets. Even though <literal>GtkTreeView</literal> is slightly
    harder to master than its predecessors, it is so much more powerful and
    flexible that most application developers will not want to miss it once
    they have come to know it.</para>

    <para>The purpose of this chapter is not to provide an exhaustive
    documentation of <literal>GtkTreeView</literal> - that is what the <ulink
    url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/TreeWidgetObjects.html">API
    documentation</ulink> is for, which should be read alongside with this
    tutorial. The goal is rather to present an introduction to the most
    commonly-used aspects of <literal>GtkTreeView</literal>, and to
    demonstrate how the various <literal>GtkTreeView</literal> components and
    concepts work together. Furthermore, an attempt has been made to shed some
    light on custom tree models and custom cell renderers, which seem to be
    often-mentioned, but rarely explained.</para>

    <para>Developers looking for a quick and dirty introduction that teaches
    them everything they need to know in less than five paragraphs will not
    find it here. In the author's experience, developers who do not understand
    how the tree view and the models work together will run into problems once
    they try to modify the given examples, whereas developers who have worked
    with other toolkits that employ the Model/View/Controller-design will find
    that the API reference provides all the information they need to know in
    more condensed form anyway. Those who disagree may jump straight to the
    <link linkend="sec-treeview-col-example">working example code</link> of
    course.</para>

    <para>Please note that the code examples in the following sections do not
    necessarily demonstrate how <literal>GtkTreeView</literal> is used best in
    a particular situation. There are different ways to achieve the same
    result, and the examples merely show those different ways, so that
    developers are able to decide which one is most suitable for the task at
    hand.</para>

    <sect1 id="sec-TreeView-HelloWorld">
      <title>Hello World</title>

      <para>For the impatient, here is a small treeview 'Hello World' program
      (which can also be found in the examples section of the <ulink
      url="treeview-tutorial.tar.gz"> treeview-tutorial.tar.gz</ulink>
      tarball).</para>

      <programlisting role="C">

/* 
 * Compile with:
 *  gcc -o helloworld helloworld.c `pkg-config --cflags --libs gtk+-2.0`
 *
 */

#include &lt;gtk/gtk.h&gt;

enum
{
  COL_NAME = 0,
  COL_AGE,
  NUM_COLS
} ;


static GtkTreeModel *
create_and_fill_model (void)
{
  GtkListStore  *store;
  GtkTreeIter    iter;
  
  store = gtk_list_store_new (NUM_COLS, G_TYPE_STRING, G_TYPE_UINT);

  /* Append a row and fill in some data */
  gtk_list_store_append (store, &amp;iter);
  gtk_list_store_set (store, &amp;iter,
                      COL_NAME, "Heinz El-Mann",
                      COL_AGE, 51,
                      -1);
  
  /* append another row and fill in some data */
  gtk_list_store_append (store, &amp;iter);
  gtk_list_store_set (store, &amp;iter,
                      COL_NAME, "Jane Doe",
                      COL_AGE, 23,
                      -1);
  
  /* ... and a third row */
  gtk_list_store_append (store, &amp;iter);
  gtk_list_store_set (store, &amp;iter,
                      COL_NAME, "Joe Bungop",
                      COL_AGE, 91,
                      -1);
  
  return GTK_TREE_MODEL (store);
}

static GtkWidget *
create_view_and_model (void)
{
  GtkCellRenderer     *renderer;
  GtkTreeModel        *model;
  GtkWidget           *view;

  view = gtk_tree_view_new ();

  /* --- Column #1 --- */

  renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new ();
  gtk_tree_view_insert_column_with_attributes (GTK_TREE_VIEW (view),
                                               -1,      
                                               "Name",  
                                               renderer,
                                               "text", COL_NAME,
                                               NULL);

  /* --- Column #2 --- */

  renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new ();
  gtk_tree_view_insert_column_with_attributes (GTK_TREE_VIEW (view),
                                               -1,      
                                               "Age",  
                                               renderer,
                                               "text", COL_AGE,
                                               NULL);

  model = create_and_fill_model ();

  gtk_tree_view_set_model (GTK_TREE_VIEW (view), model);

  /* The tree view has acquired its own reference to the
   *  model, so we can drop ours. That way the model will
   *  be freed automatically when the tree view is destroyed */

  g_object_unref (model);

  return view;
}


int
main (int argc, char **argv)
{
  GtkWidget *window;
  GtkWidget *view;

  gtk_init (&amp;argc, &amp;argv);

  window = gtk_window_new (GTK_WINDOW_TOPLEVEL);
  g_signal_connect (window, "delete_event", gtk_main_quit, NULL); /* dirty */

  view = create_view_and_model ();

  gtk_container_add (GTK_CONTAINER (window), view);

  gtk_widget_show_all (window);

  gtk_main ();

  return 0;
}
</programlisting>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-treeview-components">
    <title>Components: Model, Renderer, Column, View</title>

    <para>The most important concept underlying <literal>GtkTreeView</literal>
    is that of complete separation between data and how that data is displayed
    on the screen. This is commonly known as Model/View/Controller-design
    (MVC). Data of various type (strings, numbers, images, etc.) is stored in
    a 'model'. The 'view' is then told which data to display, where to display
    it, and how to display it. One of the advantages of this approach is that
    you can have multiple views that display the same data (a directory tree
    for example) in different ways, or in the same way multiple times, with
    only one copy of the underlying data. This avoids duplication of data and
    programming effort if the same data is re-used in different contexts.
    Also, when the data in the model is updated, all views automatically get
    updated as well.</para>

    <para>So, while <literal>GtkTreeModel</literal> is used to store data,
    there are other components that determine which data is displayed in the
    <literal>GtkTreeView</literal> and how it is displayed. These components
    are <literal>GtkTreeViewColumn</literal> and
    <literal>GtkCellRenderer</literal>. A <literal>GtkTreeView</literal> is
    made up of tree view columns. These are the columns that users perceive as
    columns. They have a clickable column header with a column title that can
    be hidden, and can be resized and sorted. Tree view columns do not display
    any data, they are only used as a device to represent the user-side of the
    tree view (sorting etc.) and serve as packing widgets for the components
    that do the actual rendering of data onto the screen, namely the
    <literal>GtkCellRenderer</literal> family of objects (I call them
    'objects' because they are not GtkWidgets). There are a number of
    different cell renderers that specialise in rendering certain data like
    strings, pixbufs, or toggle buttons. More on this <link
    linkend="sec-renderer">later</link>.</para>

    <para>Cell renderers are packed into tree view columns to display data. A
    tree view column needs to contain at least one cell renderer, but can
    contain multiple cell renderers. For example, if one wanted to display a
    'Filename' column where each filename has a little icon on the left
    indicating the file type, one would pack a
    <literal>GtkCellRendererPixbuf</literal> and a
    <literal>GtkCellRendererText</literal> into one tree view column. Packing
    renderers into a tree view column is similar to packing widgets into a
    <literal>GtkHBox</literal>.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-treemodels">
    <title>GtkTreeModels for Data Storage: GtkListStore and
    GtkTreeStore</title>

    <para>It is important to realise what <ulink
    url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html"><literal>GtkTreeModel</literal></ulink>
    is and what it is not. <literal>GtkTreeModel</literal> is basically just
    an 'interface' to the data store, meaning that it is a standardised set of
    functions that allows a <literal>GtkTreeView</literal> widget (and the
    application programmer) to query certain characteristics of a data store,
    for example how many rows there are, which rows have children, and how
    many children a particular row has. It also provides functions to retrieve
    data from the data store, and tell the tree view what type of data is
    stored in the model. Every data store must implement the
    <literal>GtkTreeModel</literal> interface and provide these functions,
    which you can use by casting a store to a tree model with
    <literal>GTK_TREE_MODEL(store)</literal>. <literal>GtkTreeModel</literal>
    itself only provides a way to query a data store's characteristics and to
    retrieve existing data, it does not provide a way to remove or add rows to
    the store or put data into the store. This is done using the specific
    store's functions.</para>

    <para>Gtk+ comes with two built-in data stores (models): <ulink
    url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkListStore.html"><literal>GtkListStore</literal></ulink>
    and <ulink
    url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeStore.html"><literal>GtkTreeStore</literal></ulink>.
    As the names imply, <literal>GtkListStore</literal> is used for simple
    lists of data items where items have no hierarchical parent-child
    relationships, and <literal>GtkTreeStore</literal> is used for tree-like
    data structures, where items can have parent-child relationships. A list
    of files in a directory would be an example of a simple list structure,
    whereas a directory tree is an example for a tree structure. A list is
    basically just a special case of a tree with none of the items having any
    children, so one could use a tree store to maintain a simple list of items
    as well. The only reason <literal>GtkListStore</literal> exists is in
    order to provide an easier interface that does not need to cater for
    child-parent relationships, and because a simple list model can be
    optimised for the special case where no children exist, which makes it
    faster and more efficient.</para>

    <para><literal>GtkListStore</literal> and <literal>GtkTreeStore</literal>
    should cater for most types of data an application developer might want to
    display in a <literal>GtkTreeView</literal>. However, it should be noted
    that <literal>GtkListStore</literal> and <literal>GtkTreeStore</literal>
    have been designed with flexibility in mind. If you plan to store a lot of
    data, or have a large number of rows, you should consider implementing
    your own custom model that stores and manipulates data your own way and
    implements the <literal>GtkTreeModel</literal> interface. This will not
    only be more efficient, but probably also lead to saner code in the long
    run, and give you more control over your data. See <link
    linkend="sec-custom-models">below</link> for more details on how to
    implement custom models.</para>

    <para>Tree model implementations like <literal>GtkListStore</literal> and
    <literal>GtkTreeStore</literal> will take care of the view side for you
    once you have configured the <literal>GtkTreeView</literal> to display
    what you want. If you change data in the store, the model will notify the
    tree view and your data display will be updated. If you add or remove
    rows, the model will also notify the store, and your row will appear in or
    disappear from the view as well.</para>

    <sect1 id="sec-treemodel-data">
      <title>How Data is Organised in a Store</title>

      <para>A model (data store) has model columns and rows. While a tree view
      will display each row in the model as a row in the view, the model's
      columns are not to be confused with a view's columns. A model column
      represents a certain data field of an item that has a fixed data type.
      You need to know what kind of data you want to store when you create a
      list store or a tree store, as you can not add new fields later
      on.</para>

      <para>For example, we might want to display a list of files. We would
      create a list store with two fields: a field that stores the filename
      (ie. a string) and a field that stores the file size (ie. an unsigned
      integer). The filename would be stored in column 0 of the model, and the
      file size would be stored in column 1 of the model. For each file we
      would add a row to the list store, and set the row's fields to the
      filename and the file size.</para>

      <para>The <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gobject/gobject-GType.html">GLib
      type system (GType)</ulink> is used to indicate what type of data is
      stored in a model column. These are the most commonly used types:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara><literal>G_TYPE_BOOLEAN</literal></simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><literal>G_TYPE_INT</literal>,
          <literal>G_TYPE_UINT</literal></simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><literal>G_TYPE_LONG</literal>,
          <literal>G_TYPE_ULONG</literal>, <literal>G_TYPE_INT64</literal>,
          <literal>G_TYPE_UINT64</literal> (these are not supported in early
          gtk+-2.0.x versions)</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><literal>G_TYPE_FLOAT</literal>,
          <literal>G_TYPE_DOUBLE</literal></simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><literal>G_TYPE_STRING</literal> - stores a string in the
          store (makes a copy of the original string)</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><literal>G_TYPE_POINTER</literal> - stores a pointer value
          (does not copy any data into the store, just stores the pointer
          value!)</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><literal>GDK_TYPE_PIXBUF</literal> - stores a GdkPixbuf in
          the store (increases the pixbuf's refcount, <link
          linkend="sec-treemodel-storing-gobjects">see below</link>)</simpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>You do not need to understand the type system, it will usually
      suffice to know the above types, so you can tell a list store or tree
      store what kind of data you want to store. Advanced users can derive
      their own types from the fundamental GLib types. For simple structures
      you could <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gobject/gobject-Boxed-Types.html#g-boxed-type-register-static">register</ulink>
      a new <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gobject/gobject-Boxed-Types.html">boxed
      type</ulink> for example, but that is usually not necessary.
      <literal>G_TYPE_POINTER</literal> will often do as well, you will just
      need to take care of memory allocation and freeing yourself then.</para>

      <para>Storing <literal>GObject</literal>-derived types (most
      <literal>GDK_TYPE_FOO</literal> and <literal>GTK_TYPE_FOO</literal>) is
      a special case that is dealt with <link
      linkend="sec-treemodel-storing-gobjects">further below</link>.</para>

      <para>Here is an example of how to create a list store:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  GtkListStore *list_store;

  list_store = gtk_list_store_new (2, G_TYPE_STRING, G_TYPE_UINT);
</programlisting>

      <para>This creates a new list store with two columns. Column 0 stores a
      string and column 1 stores an unsigned integer for each row. At this
      point the model has no rows yet of course. Before we start to add rows,
      let's have a look at the different ways used to refer to a particular
      row.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treemodel-rowref">
      <title>Refering to Rows: GtkTreeIter, GtkTreePath,
      GtkTreeRowReference</title>

      <para>There are different ways to refer to a specific row. The two you
      will have to deal with are <literal>GtkTreeIter</literal> and
      <literal>GtkTreePath</literal>.</para>

      <sect2 id="sec-treemodel-rowref-path">
        <title>GtkTreePath</title>

        <subtitle>Describing a row 'geographically'</subtitle>

        <para>A <literal>GtkTreePath</literal> is a comparatively
        straight-forward way to describe the logical position of a row in the
        model. As a <literal>GtkTreeView</literal> always displays
        <emphasis>all</emphasis> rows in a model, a tree path always describes
        the same row in both model and view.</para>

        <figure id="sec-treemodel-treepath-sshot">
          <title>Tree Paths</title>

          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/treepath.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>

              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/treepath.eps" format="EPS"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

        <para>The picture shows the tree path in string form next to the
        label. Basically, it just counts the children from the imaginary root
        of the tree view. An empty tree path string would specify that
        imaginary invisible root. Now 'Songs' is the first child (from the
        root) and thus its tree path is just "0". 'Videos' is the second child
        from the root, and its tree path is "1". 'oggs' is the second child of
        the first item from the root, so its tree path is "0:1". So you just
        count your way down from the root to the row in question, and you get
        your tree path.</para>

        <para>To clarify this, a tree path of "3:9:4:1" would basically mean
        <emphasis>in human language</emphasis> (attention - this is not what
        it really means!) something along the lines of: go to the 3rd
        top-level row. Now go to the 9th child of that row. Proceed to the 4th
        child of the previous row. Then continue to the 1st child of that. Now
        you are at the row this tree path describes. This is not what it means
        for Gtk+ though. While humans start counting at 1, computers usually
        start counting at 0. So the real meaning of the tree path "3:9:4:1"
        is: Go to the 4th top-level row. Then go to the 10th child of that
        row. Pick the 5th child of that row. Then proceed to the 2nd child of
        the previous row. Now you are at the row this tree path describes.
        :)</para>

        <para>The implication of this way of refering to rows is as follows:
        if you insert or delete rows in the middle or if the rows are
        resorted, a tree path might suddenly refer to a completely different
        row than it refered to before the insertion/deletion/resorting. This
        is important to keep in mind. (See the <link
        linkend="sec-treemodel-rowref-rowref">section on
        <literal>GtkTreeRowReference</literal>s below</link> for a tree path
        that keeps updating itself to make sure it always refers to the same
        row when the model changes).</para>

        <para>This effect becomes apparent if you imagine what would happen if
        we were to delete the row entitled 'funny clips' from the tree in the
        above picture. The row 'movie trailers' would suddenly be the first
        and only child of 'clips', and be described by the tree path that
        formerly belonged to 'funny clips', ie. "1:0:0".</para>

        <para>You can get a new <literal>GtkTreePath</literal> from a path in
        string form using <literal>gtk_tree_path_new_from_string</literal>,
        and you can convert a given <literal>GtkTreePath</literal> into its
        string notation with <literal>gtk_tree_path_to_string</literal>.
        Usually you will rarely have to handle the string notation, it is
        described here merely to demonstrate the concept of tree paths.</para>

        <para>Instead of the string notation, <literal>GtkTreePath</literal>
        uses an integer array internally. You can get the depth (ie. the
        nesting level) of a tree path with <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-path-get-depth">
        <literal>gtk_tree_path_get_depth</literal></ulink>. A depth of 0 is
        the imaginary invisible root node of the tree view and model. A depth
        of 1 means that the tree path describes a top-level row. As lists are
        just trees without child nodes, all rows in a list always have tree
        paths of depth 1. <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-path-get-indices">
        <literal>gtk_tree_path_get_indices</literal></ulink> returns the
        internal integer array of a tree path. You will rarely need to operate
        with those either.</para>

        <para>If you operate with tree paths, you are most likely to use a
        given tree path, and use functions like <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk_tree_path_up">
        <literal>gtk_tree_path_up</literal></ulink>, <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-path-down">
        <literal>gtk_tree_path_down</literal></ulink>, <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-path-next">
        <literal>gtk_tree_path_next</literal></ulink>, <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-path-prev">
        <literal>gtk_tree_path_prev</literal></ulink>, <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-path-is-ancestor">
        <literal>gtk_tree_path_is_ancestor</literal></ulink>, or <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-path-is-descendant">
        <literal>gtk_tree_path_is_descendant</literal></ulink>. Note that this
        way you can construct and operate on tree paths that refer to rows
        that do not exist in model or view! The only way to check whether a
        path is valid for a specific model (ie. the row described by the path
        exists) is to convert the path into an iter using <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get-iter">
        <literal>gtk_tree_model_get_iter</literal></ulink>.</para>

        <para><literal>GtkTreePath</literal> is an opaque structure, with its
        details hidden from the compiler. If you need to make a copy of a tree
        path, use <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-path-copy">
        <literal>gtk_tree_path_copy</literal></ulink>.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-treemodel-rowref-iter">
        <title>GtkTreeIter</title>

        <subtitle>Refering to a row in model-speak</subtitle>

        <para>Another way to refer to a row in a list or tree is
        <literal>GtkTreeIter</literal>. A tree iter is just a structure that
        contains a couple of pointers that mean something to the model you are
        using. Tree iters are used internally by models, and they often
        contain a direct pointer to the internal data of the row in question.
        You should never look at the content of a tree iter and you must not
        modify it directly either.</para>

        <para>All tree models (and therefore also
        <literal>GtkListStore</literal> and <literal>GtkTreeStore</literal>)
        must support the <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html">
        <literal>GtkTreeModel</literal></ulink> functions that operate on tree
        iters (e.g. get the tree iter for the first child of the row specified
        by a given tree iter, get the first row in the list/tree, get the n-th
        child of a given iter etc.). Some of these functions are:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <simpara><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get-iter-first">
            <literal>gtk_tree_model_get_iter_first</literal></ulink> - sets
            the given iter to the first top-level item in the list or
            tree</simpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <simpara><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-iter-next">
            <literal>gtk_tree_model_iter_next</literal></ulink> - sets the
            given iter to the next item at the current level in a list or
            tree.</simpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <simpara><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-iter-children">
            <literal>gtk_tree_model_iter_children</literal></ulink> - sets the
            first given iter to the first child of the row referenced by the
            second iter (not very useful for lists, mostly useful for
            trees).</simpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <simpara><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-iter-n-children">
            <literal>gtk_tree_model_iter_n_children</literal></ulink> -
            returns the number of children the row referenced by the provided
            iter has. If you pass <literal>NULL</literal> instead of a pointer
            to an iter structure, this function will return the number of
            top-level rows. You can also use this function to count the number
            of items in a list store.</simpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <simpara><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-iter-nth-child">
            <literal>gtk_tree_model_iter_nth_child</literal></ulink> - sets
            the first iter to the n-th child of the row referenced by the
            second iter. If you pass <literal>NULL</literal> instead of a
            pointer to an iter structure as the second iter, you can get the
            first iter set to the n-th row of a list.</simpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <simpara><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-iter-parent">
            <literal>gtk_tree_model_iter_parent</literal></ulink> - sets the
            first iter to the parent of the row referenced by the second iter
            (does nothing for lists, only useful for trees).</simpara>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Almost all of those functions return <literal>TRUE</literal> if
        the requested operation succeeded, and return <literal>FALSE</literal>
        otherwise. There are more functions that operate on iters. Check out
        the <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html">
        <literal>GtkTreeModel</literal> API reference</ulink> for
        details.</para>

        <para>You might notice that there is no
        <literal>gtk_tree_model_iter_prev</literal>. This is unlikely to be
        implemented for a variety of reasons. It should be fairly simple to
        write a helper function that provides this functionality though once
        you have read this section.</para>

        <para>Tree iters are used to retrieve data from the store, and to put
        data into the store. You also get a tree iter as result if you add a
        new row to the store using <literal>gtk_list_store_append</literal> or
        <literal>gtk_tree_store_append</literal>.</para>

        <para>Tree iters are often only valid for a short time, and might
        become invalid if the store changes with some models. It is therefore
        usually a bad idea to store tree iters, unless you really know what
        you are doing. You can use <literal>gtk_tree_model_get_flags</literal>
        to get a model's flags, and check whether the
        <literal>GTK_TREE_MODEL_ITERS_PERSIST</literal> flag is set (in which
        case a tree iter will be valid as long as a row exists), yet still it
        is not advisable to store iter structures unless you really mean to do
        that. There is a better way to keep track of a row over time:
        <literal>GtkTreeRowReference</literal></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-treemodel-rowref-rowref">
        <title>GtkTreeRowReference</title>

        <subtitle>Keeping track of rows even when the model changes</subtitle>

        <para>A <literal>GtkTreeRowReference</literal> is basically an object
        that takes a tree path, and watches a model for changes. If anything
        changes, like rows getting inserted or removed, or rows getting
        re-ordered, the tree row reference object will keep the given tree
        path up to date, so that it always points to the same row as before.
        In case the given row is removed, the tree row reference will become
        invalid.</para>

        <para>A new tree row reference can be created with <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-row-reference-new">
        <literal>gtk_tree_row_reference_new</literal></ulink>, given a model
        and a tree path. After that, the tree row reference will keep updating
        the path whenever the model changes. The current tree path of the row
        originally refered to when the tree row reference was created can be
        retrieved with <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-row-reference-get-path">
        <literal>gtk_tree_row_reference_get_path</literal></ulink>. If the row
        has been deleted, <literal>NULL</literal> will be returned instead of
        of a tree path. The tree path returned is a <emphasis>copy</emphasis>,
        so it will need to be freed with <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-path-free">
        <literal>gtk_tree_path_free</literal></ulink> when it is no longer
        needed.</para>

        <para>You can check whether the row referenced still exists with
        <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-row-reference-valid">
        <literal>gtk_tree_row_reference_valid</literal></ulink>, and free it
        with <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-row-reference-free">
        <literal/></ulink> when no longer needed.</para>

        <para>For the curious: internally, the tree row reference connects to
        the tree model's <literal>"row-inserted"</literal>,
        <literal>"row-deleted"</literal>, and
        <literal>"rows-reordered"</literal> signals and updates its internal
        tree path whenever something happened to the model that affects the
        position of the referenced row.</para>

        <para>Note that using tree row references entails a small overhead.
        This is hardly significant for 99.9% of all applications out there,
        but when you have multiple thousands of rows and/or row references,
        this might be something to keep in mind (because whenever rows are
        inserted, removed, or reordered, a signal will be sent out and
        processed for each row reference).</para>

        <para>If you have read the tutorial only up to here so far, it is hard
        to explain really what tree row references are good for. An example
        where tree row references come in handy can be found further below in
        the <link linkend="sec-treemodel-remove-many-rows">section on removing
        multiple rows in one go</link>.</para>

        <para>In practice, a programmer can either use tree row references to
        keep track of rows over time, or store tree iters directly (if, and
        only if, the model has persistent iters). Both
        <literal>GtkListStore</literal> and <literal>GtkTreeStore</literal>
        have persistent iters, so storing iters is possible. However, using
        tree row references is definitively the Right Way(tm) to do things,
        even though it comes with some overhead that might impact performance
        in case of trees that have a very large number of rows (in that case
        it might be preferable to write a custom model anyway though).
        Especially beginners might find it easier to handle and store tree row
        references than iters, because tree row references are handled by
        pointer value, which you can easily add to a <literal>GList</literal>
        or pointer array, while it is easy to store tree iters in a wrong
        way.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-treemodel-rowref-usage">
        <title>Usage</title>

        <para>Tree iters can easily be converted into tree paths using <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get-path">
        <literal>gtk_tree_model_get_path</literal></ulink>, and tree paths can
        easily be converted into tree iters using <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get-iter">
        <literal>gtk_tree_model_get_iter</literal></ulink>. Here is an example
        that shows how to get the iter from the tree path that is passed to us
        from the tree view in the <literal>"row-activated"</literal> signal
        callback. We need the iter here to retrieve data from the store</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
/************************************************************
 *                                                          *
 * Converting a GtkTreePath into a GtkTreeIter              *
 *                                                          *
 ************************************************************/

/************************************************************
 *
 * onTreeViewRowActivated: a row has been double-clicked
 *
 ************************************************************/

void
onTreeViewRowActivated (GtkTreeView *view, GtkTreePath *path,
                        GtkTreeViewColumn *col, gpointer userdata)
{
	GtkTreeIter   iter;
  GtkTreeModel *model;

  model = gtk_tree_view_get_model(view);

  if (gtk_tree_model_get_iter(model, &amp;iter, path))
  {
    gchar *name;

    gtk_tree_model_get(model, &amp;iter, COL_NAME, &amp;name, -1);

    g_print ("The row containing the name '%s' has been double-clicked.\n", name);

    g_free(name);
  }
}
</programlisting>

        <para>Tree row references reveal the current path of a row with
        <literal>gtk_tree_row_reference_get_path</literal>. There is no direct
        way to get a tree iter from a tree row reference, you have to retrieve
        the tree row reference's path first and then convert that into a tree
        iter.</para>

        <para>As tree iters are only valid for a short time, they are usually
        allocated on the stack, as in the following example (keep in mind that
        <literal>GtkTreeIter</literal> is just a structure that contains data
        fields you do not need to know anything about):</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
 /************************************************************
  *                                                          *
  *  Going through every row in a list store                 *
  *                                                          *
  ************************************************************/

  void
  traverse_list_store (GtkListStore *liststore)
  {
    GtkTreeIter  iter;
    gboolean     valid;

    g_return_if_fail ( liststore != NULL );

    /* Get first row in list store */
    valid = gtk_tree_model_get_iter_first(GTK_TREE_MODEL(liststore), &amp;iter);

    while (valid)
    {
       /* ... do something with that row using the iter ...          */
       /* (Here column 0 of the list store is of type G_TYPE_STRING) */
       gtk_list_store_set(liststore, &amp;iter, 0, "Joe", -1);

       /* Make iter point to the next row in the list store */
       valid = gtk_tree_model_iter_next(GTK_TREE_MODEL(liststore), &amp;iter);
    }
  }
</programlisting>

        <para>The code above asks the model to fill the iter structure to make
        it point to the first row in the list store. If there is a first row
        and the list store is not empty, the iter will be set, and <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get-iter-first">
        <literal>gtk_tree_model_get_iter_first</literal></ulink> will return
        <literal>TRUE</literal>. If there is no first row, it will just return
        <literal>FALSE</literal>. If a first row exists, the while loop will
        be entered and we change some of the first row's data. Then we ask the
        model to make the given iter point to the next row, until there are no
        more rows, which is when <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-iter-next">
        <literal>gtk_tree_model_iter_next</literal></ulink> returns
        <literal>FALSE</literal>. Instead of traversing the list store we
        could also have used <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-foreach">
        <literal>gtk_tree_model_foreach</literal></ulink></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treemodel-add-rows">
      <title>Adding Rows to a Store</title>

      <sect2 id="sec-liststore-add-rows">
        <title>Adding Rows to a List Store</title>

        <para>Rows are added to a list store with <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkListStore.html#gtk-list-store-append">
        <literal>gtk_list_store_append</literal></ulink>. This will insert a
        new empty row at the end of the list. There are other functions,
        documented in the <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkListStore.html">
        GtkListStore API reference</ulink>, that give you more control about
        where exactly the new row is inserted, but as they work very similar
        to <literal>gtk_list_store_append</literal> and are fairly
        straight-forward to use, we will not deal with them here.</para>

        <para>Here is a simple example of how to create a list store and add
        some (empty) rows to it:</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
  GtkListStore *liststore;
  GtkTreeIter   iter;

  liststore = gtk_list_store_new(1, G_TYPE_STRING);

  /* Append an empty row to the list store. Iter will point to the new row */
  gtk_list_store_append(liststore, &amp;iter);

  /* Append an empty row to the list store. Iter will point to the new row */
  gtk_list_store_append(liststore, &amp;iter);

  /* Append an empty row to the list store. Iter will point to the new row */
  gtk_list_store_append(liststore, &amp;iter);
</programlisting>

        <para>This in itself is not very useful yet of course. We will add
        data to the rows in the next section.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-treestore-add-rows">
        <title>Adding Rows to a Tree Store</title>

        <para>Adding rows to a tree store works similar to adding rows to a
        list store, only that <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeStore.html#gtk-tree-store-append">
        <literal>gtk_tree_store_append</literal></ulink> is the function to
        use and one more argument is required, namely the tree iter to the
        parent of the row to insert. If you supply NULL instead of providing
        the tree iter of another row, a new top-level row will be inserted. If
        you do provide a parent tree iter, the new empty row will be inserted
        after any already existing children of the parent. Again, there are
        other ways to insert a row into the tree store and they are documented
        in the <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeStore.html">
        GtkTreeStore API reference manual</ulink>. Another short
        example:</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
  GtkTreeStore *treestore;
  GtkTreeIter   iter, child;

  treestore = gtk_tree_store_new(1, G_TYPE_STRING);

  /* Append an empty top-level row to the tree store.
   *  Iter will point to the new row */
  gtk_tree_store_append(treestore, &amp;iter, NULL);

  /* Append another empty top-level row to the tree store.
   *  Iter will point to the new row */
  gtk_tree_store_append(treestore, &amp;iter, NULL);

  /* Append a child to the row we just added.
   *  Child will point to the new row */
  gtk_tree_store_append(treestore, &amp;child, &amp;iter);

  /* Get the first row, and add a child to it as well (could have been done
   *  right away earlier of course, this is just for demonstration purposes) */
  if (gtk_tree_model_get_iter_first(GTK_TREE_MODEL(treestore), &amp;iter))
  {
    /* Child will point to new row */
    gtk_tree_store_append(treestore, &amp;child, &amp;iter);
  }
  else
  {
    g_error("Oops, we should have a first row in the tree store!\n");
  }
</programlisting>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-treestore-adding-many-rows">
        <title>Speed Issues when Adding a Lot of Rows</title>

        <para>A common scenario is that a model needs to be filled with a lot
        of rows at some point, either at start-up, or when some file is
        opened. An equally common scenario is that this takes an awfully long
        time even on powerful machines once the model contains more than a
        couple of thousand rows, with an exponentially decreasing rate of
        insertion. As already pointed out above, <link
        linkend="sec-custom-models">writing a custom model</link> might be the
        best thing to do in this case. Nevertheless, there are some things you
        can do to work around this problem and speed things up a bit even with
        the stock Gtk+ models:</para>

        <para>Firstly, you should detach your list store or tree store from
        the tree view before doing your mass insertions, then do your
        insertions, and only connect your store to the tree view again when
        you are done with your insertions. Like this:</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
  ...

  model = gtk_tree_view_get_model(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view));

  g_object_ref(model); /* Make sure the model stays with us after the tree view unrefs it */

  gtk_tree_view_set_model(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view), NULL); /* Detach model from view */

  ... insert a couple of thousand rows ...

  gtk_tree_view_set_model(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view), model); /* Re-attach model to view */

  g_object_unref(model);

  ...
</programlisting>

        <para>Secondly, you should make sure that sorting is disabled while
        you are doing your mass insertions, otherwise your store might be
        resorted after each and every single row insertion, which is going to
        be everything but fast.</para>

        <para>Thirdly, you should not keep around a lot of tree row references
        if you have so many rows, because with each insertion (or removal)
        every single tree row reference will check whether its path needs to
        be updated or not.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treemodel-data-manipulation">
      <title>Manipulating Row Data</title>

      <para>Adding empty rows to a data store is not terribly exciting, so
      let's see how we can add or change data in the store.</para>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkListStore.html#gtk-list-store-set">
      <literal>gtk_list_store_set</literal></ulink> and <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeStore.html#gtk-tree-store-set">
      <literal>gtk_tree_store_set</literal></ulink> are used to manipulate a
      given row's data. There is also
      <literal>gtk_list_store_set_value</literal> and
      <literal>gtk_tree_store_set_value</literal>, but those should only be
      used by people familiar with GLib's GValue system.</para>

      <para>Both <literal>gtk_list_store_set</literal> and
      <literal>gtk_tree_store_set</literal> take a variable number of
      arguments, and must be terminated with a -1 argument. The first two
      arguments are a pointer to the model, and the iter pointing to the row
      whose data we want to change. They are followed by a variable number of
      (column, data) argument pairs, terminated by a -1. The column refers to
      the model column number and is usually an enum value (to make the code
      more readable and to make changes easier). The data should be of the
      same data type as the model column.</para>

      <para>Here is an example where we create a store that stores two strings
      and one integer for each row:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  enum
  {
    COL_FIRST_NAME = 0,
    COL_LAST_NAME,
    COL_YEAR_BORN,
    NUM_COLS
  };

  GtkListStore *liststore;
  GtkTreeIter   iter;

  liststore = gtk_list_store_new(NUM_COLS, G_TYPE_STRING, G_TYPE_STRING, G_TYPE_UINT);

  /* Append an empty row to the list store. Iter will point to the new row */
  gtk_list_store_append(liststore, &amp;iter);

  /* Fill fields with some data */
  gtk_list_store_set (liststore, &amp;iter,
                      COL_FIRST_NAME, "Joe",
                      COL_LAST_NAME, "Average",
                      COL_YEAR_BORN, (guint) 1970,
                      -1);
</programlisting>

      <para>You do not need to worry about allocating and freeing memory for
      the data to store. The model (or more precisely: the GLib/GObject GType
      and GValue system) will take care of that for you. If you store a
      string, for example, the model will make a copy of the string and store
      that. If you then set the field to a new string later on, the model will
      automatically free the old string and again make a copy of the new
      string and store the copy. This applies to almost all types, be it
      <literal>G_TYPE_STRING</literal> or
      <literal>GDK_TYPE_PIXBUF</literal>.</para>

      <para>The exception to note is <literal>G_TYPE_POINTER</literal>. If you
      allocate a chunk of data or a complex structure and store it in a
      <literal>G_TYPE_POINTER</literal> field, only the pointer
      <emphasis>value</emphasis> is stored. The model does not know anything
      about the size or content of the data your pointer refers to, so it
      could not even make a copy if it wanted to, so you need to allocate and
      free the memory yourself in this case. However, if you do not want to do
      that yourself and want the model to take care of your custom data for
      you, then you need to register your own type and derive it from one of
      the GLib fundamental types (usually <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gobject/gobject-Boxed-Types.html">G_TYPE_BOXED</ulink>).
      See the GObject <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gobject/gobject-GType.html">GType
      reference manual</ulink> for details. Making a copy of data involves
      memory allocation and other overhead of course, so one should consider
      the performance implications of using a custom GLib type over a
      G_TYPE_POINTER carefully before taking that approach. Again, a custom
      model might be the better alternative, depending on the overall amount
      of data to be stored (and retrieved).</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treemodel-data-retrieval">
      <title>Retrieving Row Data</title>

      <para>Storing data is not very useful if it cannot be retrieved again.
      This is done using <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get">
      <literal>gtk_tree_model_get</literal></ulink>, which takes similar
      arguments as <literal>gtk_list_store_set</literal> or
      <literal>gtk_tree_store_set</literal> do, only that it takes (column,
      pointer) arguments. The pointer must point to a variable that is of the
      same type as the data stored in that particular model column.</para>

      <para>Here is the previous example extended to traverse the list store
      and print out the data stored. As an extra, we use
      <literal>gtk_tree_model_foreach</literal> to traverse the store and
      retrieve the row number from the <literal>GtkTreePath</literal> passed
      to us in the foreach callback function:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  #include &lt;gtk/gtk.h&gt;

  enum
  {
    COL_FIRST_NAME = 0,
    COL_LAST_NAME,
    COL_YEAR_BORN,
    NUM_COLS
  };

  gboolean
  foreach_func (GtkTreeModel *model,
                GtkTreePath  *path,
                GtkTreeIter  *iter,
                gpointer      user_data)
  {
    gchar *first_name, *last_name, *tree_path_str;
    guint  year_of_birth;

    /* Note: here we use 'iter' and not '&amp;iter', because we did not allocate
     *  the iter on the stack and are already getting the pointer to a tree iter */

    gtk_tree_model_get (model, iter,
                        COL_FIRST_NAME, &amp;first_name,
                        COL_LAST_NAME, &amp;last_name,
                        COL_YEAR_BORN, &amp;year_of_birth,
                        -1);

    tree_path_str = gtk_tree_path_to_string(path);

    g_print ("Row %s: %s %s, born %u\n", tree_path_str,
             first_name, last_name, year_of_birth);

    g_free(tree_path_str);

    g_free(first_name); /* gtk_tree_model_get made copies of       */
    g_free(last_name);  /* the strings for us when retrieving them */

    return FALSE; /* do not stop walking the store, call us with next row */
  }

  void
  create_and_fill_and_dump_store (void)
  {
    GtkListStore *liststore;
    GtkTreeIter   iter;

    liststore = gtk_list_store_new(NUM_COLS, G_TYPE_STRING, G_TYPE_STRING, G_TYPE_UINT);

    /* Append an empty row to the list store. Iter will point to the new row */
    gtk_list_store_append(liststore, &amp;iter);

    /* Fill fields with some data */
    gtk_list_store_set (liststore, &amp;iter,
                        COL_FIRST_NAME, "Joe",
                        COL_LAST_NAME, "Average",
                        COL_YEAR_BORN, (guint) 1970,
                        -1);

    /* Append another row, and fill in some data */
    gtk_list_store_append(liststore, &amp;iter);

    gtk_list_store_set (liststore, &amp;iter,
                        COL_FIRST_NAME, "Jane",
                        COL_LAST_NAME, "Common",
                        COL_YEAR_BORN, (guint) 1967,
                        -1);

    /* Append yet another row, and fill it */
    gtk_list_store_append(liststore, &amp;iter);

    gtk_list_store_set (liststore, &amp;iter,
                        COL_FIRST_NAME, "Yo",
                        COL_LAST_NAME, "Da",
                        COL_YEAR_BORN, (guint) 1873,
                        -1);

    /* Now traverse the list */

    gtk_tree_model_foreach(GTK_TREE_MODEL(liststore), foreach_func, NULL);
  }

  int
  main (int argc, char **argv)
  {
    gtk_init(&amp;argc, &amp;argv);

    create_and_fill_and_dump_store();

    return 0;
  }

</programlisting>

      <para>Note that when a new row is created, all fields of a row are set
      to a default NIL value appropriate for the data type in question. A
      field of type <literal>G_TYPE_INT</literal> will automatically contain
      the value 0 until it is set to a different value, and strings and all
      kind of pointer types will be <literal>NULL</literal> until set to
      something else. Those are valid contents for the model, and if you are
      not sure that row contents have been set to something, you need to be
      prepared to handle <literal>NULL</literal> pointers and the like in your
      code.</para>

      <para>Run the above program with an additional empty row and look at the
      output to see this in effect.</para>

      <sect2 id="sec-treemodel-retrieved-data-disposal">
        <title>Freeing Retrieved Row Data</title>

        <para>Unless you are dealing with a model column of type
        <literal>G_TYPE_POINTER</literal>,
        <literal>gtk_tree_model_get</literal> will always make
        <emphasis>copies</emphasis> of the data retrieved.</para>

        <para>In the case of strings, this means that you need to
        <literal>g_free</literal> the string returned when you don't need it
        any longer, as in the example above.</para>

        <para>If you retrieve a <literal>GObject</literal> such as a
        <literal>GdkPixbuf</literal> from the store,
        <literal>gtk_tree_model_get</literal> will automatically add a
        reference to it, so you need to call <literal>g_object_unref</literal>
        on the retrieved object once you are done with it:</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
  ...

  GdkPixbuf *pixbuf;

  gtk_tree_model_get (model, &amp;iter, 
                      COL_PICTURE, &amp;pixbuf, 
                      NULL);

  if (pixbuf != NULL)
  {
    do_something_with_pixbuf (pixbuf);
    g_object_unref (pixbuf);
  }

  ...
</programlisting>

        <para>Similarly, <literal>GBoxed</literal>-derived types retrieved
        from a model need to be freed with <literal>g_boxed_free</literal>
        when done with them (don't worry if you have never heard of
        <literal>GBoxed</literal>).</para>

        <para>If the model column is of type
        <literal>G_TYPE_POINTER</literal>,
        <literal>gtk_tree_model_get</literal> will simply copy the pointer
        value, but not the data (even if if it wanted to, it couldn't copy the
        data, because it would not know how to copy it or what to copy
        exactly). If you store pointers to objects or strings in a pointer
        column (which you should not do unless you really know what you are
        doing and why you are doing it), you do not need to unref or free the
        returned values as described above, because
        <literal>gtk_tree_model_get</literal> would not know what kind of data
        they are and therefore won't ref or copy them on retrieval.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treemodel-remove-row">
      <title>Removing Rows</title>

      <para>Rows can easily be removed with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkListStore.html#gtk-list-store-remove">
      <literal>gtk_list_store_remove</literal></ulink> and <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeStore.html#gtk-tree-store-remove">
      <literal>gtk_tree_store_remove</literal></ulink>. The removed row will
      automatically be removed from the tree view as well, and all data stored
      will automatically be freed, with the exception of
      <literal>G_TYPE_POINTER</literal> columns (see above).</para>

      <para>Removing a single row is fairly straight forward: you need to get
      the iter that identifies the row you want to remove, and then use one of
      the above functions. Here is a simple example that removes a row when
      you double-click on it (bad from a user interface point of view, but
      then it is just an example):</para>

      <programlisting role="C">

  static void
  onRowActivated (GtkTreeView        *view,
                  GtkTreePath        *path,
                  GtkTreeViewColumn  *col,
                  gpointer            user_data)
  {
    GtkTreeModel *model;
    GtkTreeIter   iter;

    g_print ("Row has been double-clicked. Removing row.\n");

    model = gtk_tree_view_get_model(view);

    if (!gtk_tree_model_get_iter(model, &amp;iter, path))
      return; /* path describes a non-existing row - should not happen */

    gtk_list_store_remove(GTK_LIST_STORE(model), &amp;iter);
  }


  void
  create_treeview (void)
  {
    ...
    g_signal_connect(treeview, "row-activated", G_CALLBACK(onRowActivated), NULL);
    ...
  }

</programlisting>

      <para><emphasis>Note:</emphasis> <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkListStore.html#gtk-list-store-remove">
      <literal>gtk_list_store_remove</literal></ulink> and <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeStore.html#gtk-tree-store-remove">
      <literal>gtk_tree_store_remove</literal></ulink> both have slightly
      different semantics in Gtk+-2.0 and Gtk+-2.2 and later. In Gtk+-2.0,
      both functions do not return a value, while in later Gtk+ versions those
      functions return either <literal>TRUE</literal> or
      <literal>FALSE</literal> to indicate whether the iter given has been set
      to the next valid row (or invalidated if there is no next row). This is
      important to keep in mind when writing code that is supposed to work
      with all Gtk+-2.x versions. In that case you should just ignore the
      value returned (as in the call above) and check the iter with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkListStore.html#gtk-list-store-iter-is-valid">
      <literal>gtk_list_store_iter_is_valid</literal></ulink> if you need
      it.</para>

      <para>If you want to remove the n-th row from a list (or the n-th child
      of a tree node), you have two approaches: either you first create a
      <literal>GtkTreePath</literal> that describes that row and then turn it
      into an iter and remove it; or you take the iter of the parent node and
      use <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-iter-nth-child">
      <literal>gtk_tree_model_iter_nth_child</literal></ulink> (which will
      also work for list stores if you use <literal>NULL</literal> as the
      parent iter. Of course you could also start with the iter of the first
      top-level row, and then step-by-step move it to the row you want,
      although that seems a rather awkward way of doing it.</para>

      <para>The following code snippet will remove the n-th row of a list if
      it exists:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">

   /******************************************************************
    *
    *  list_store_remove_nth_row
    *
    *  Removes the nth row of a list store if it exists.
    *
    *  Returns TRUE on success or FALSE if the row does not exist.
    *
    ******************************************************************/

   gboolean
   list_store_remove_nth_row (GtkListStore *store, gint n)
   {
     GtkTreeIter  iter;

     g_return_val_if_fail (GTK_IS_LIST_STORE(store), FALSE);

     /* NULL means the parent is the virtual root node, so the
      *  n-th top-level element is returned in iter, which is
      *  the n-th row in a list store (as a list store only has
      *  top-level elements, and no children) */
     if (gtk_tree_model_iter_nth_child(GTK_TREE_MODEL(store), &amp;iter, NULL, n))
     {
       gtk_list_store_remove(store, &amp;iter);
       return TRUE;
     }

     return FALSE;
   }

</programlisting>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treemodel-remove-many-rows">
      <title>Removing Multiple Rows</title>

      <para>Removing multiple rows at once can be a bit tricky at times, and
      requires some thought on how to do this best. For example, it is not
      possible to traverse a store with
      <literal>gtk_tree_model_foreach</literal>, check in the callback
      function whether the given row should be removed and then just remove it
      by calling one of the stores' remove functions. This will not work,
      because the model is changed from within the foreach loop, which might
      suddenly invalidate formerly valid tree iters in the foreach function,
      and thus lead to unpredictable results.</para>

      <para>You could traverse the store in a <literal>while</literal> loop of
      course, and call <literal>gtk_list_store_remove</literal> or
      <literal>gtk_tree_store_remove</literal> whenever you want to remove a
      row, and then just continue if the remove functions returns
      <literal>TRUE</literal> (meaning that the iter is still valid and now
      points to the row after the row that was removed). However, this
      approach will only work with Gtk+-2.2 or later and will not work if you
      want your programs to compile and work with Gtk+-2.0 as well, for the
      reasons outlined above (in Gtk+-2.0 the remove functions did not set the
      passed iter to the next valid row). Also, while this approach might be
      feasable for a list store, it gets a bit awkward for a tree
      store.</para>

      <para>Here is an example for an alternative approach to removing
      multiple rows in one go (here we want to remove all rows from the store
      that contain persons that have been born after 1980, but it could just
      as well be all selected rows or some other criterion):</para>

      <programlisting role="C">

 /******************************************************************
  *
  *  Removing multiple rows in one go
  *
  ******************************************************************/

  ...

  gboolean
  foreach_func (GtkTreeModel *model,
                GtkTreePath  *path,
                GtkTreeIter  *iter,
                GList       **rowref_list)
  {
    guint  year_of_birth;

    g_assert ( rowref_list != NULL );

    gtk_tree_model_get (model, iter, COL_YEAR_BORN, &amp;year_of_birth, -1);

    if ( year_of_birth &gt; 1980 )
    {
      GtkTreeRowReference  *rowref;

      rowref = gtk_tree_row_reference_new(model, path);

      *rowref_list = g_list_append(*rowref_list, rowref);
    }

    return FALSE; /* do not stop walking the store, call us with next row */
  }

  void
  remove_people_born_after_1980 (void)
  {
     GList *rr_list = NULL;    /* list of GtkTreeRowReferences to remove */
     GList *node;

     gtk_tree_model_foreach(GTK_TREE_MODEL(store),
                            (GtkTreeModelForeachFunc) foreach_func,
                            &amp;rr_list);

     for ( node = rr_list;  node != NULL;  node = node-&gt;next )
     {
        GtkTreePath *path;

        path = gtk_tree_row_reference_get_path((GtkTreeRowReference*)node-&gt;data);

        if (path)
        {
           GtkTreeIter  iter;

           if (gtk_tree_model_get_iter(GTK_TREE_MODEL(store), &amp;iter, path))
           {
             gtk_list_store_remove(store, &amp;iter);
           }

           /* FIXME/CHECK: Do we need to free the path here? */
        }
     }

     g_list_foreach(rr_list, (GFunc) gtk_tree_row_reference_free, NULL);
     g_list_free(rr_list);
  }

  ...

</programlisting>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkListStore.html#gtk-list-store-clear">
      <literal>gtk_list_store_clear</literal></ulink> and <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeStore.html#gtk-tree-store-clear">
      <literal>gtk_tree_store_clear</literal></ulink> come in handy if you
      want to remove all rows.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treemodel-storing-gobjects">
      <title>Storing GObjects (Pixbufs etc.)</title>

      <para>A special case are <literal>GObject</literal> types, like
      <literal>GDK_TYPE_PIXBUF</literal>, that get stored in a list or tree
      store. The store will not make a copy of the object, rather it will
      increase the object's refcount. The store will then unref the object
      again if it is no longer needed (ie. a new object is stored in the old
      object's place, the current value is replaced by NULL, the row is
      removed, or the store is destroyed).</para>

      <para>From a developer perspective, this means that you need to
      <literal>g_object_unref</literal> an object that you have just added to
      the store if you want the store to automatically dispose of it when no
      longer needed. This is because on object creation, the object has an
      initial refcount of 1, which is "your" refcount, and the object will
      only be destroyed when it reaches a refcount of 0. Here is the life
      cycle of a pixbuf:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  GtkListStore *list_store;
  GtkTreeIter   iter;
  GdkPixbuf    *pixbuf;
  GError       *error = NULL;

  list_store = gtk_list_store_new (2, GDK_TYPE_PIXBUF, G_TYPE_STRING);

  pixbuf = gdk_pixbuf_new_from_file("icon.png", &amp;error);

  /* pixbuf has a refcount of 1 after creation */

  if (error)
  {
    g_critical ("Could not load pixbuf: %s\n", error-&gt;message);
    g_error_free(error);
    return;
  }

  gtk_list_store_append(list_store, &amp;iter);

  gtk_list_store_set(list_store, &amp;iter, 0, pixbuf, 1, "foo", -1);

  /* pixbuf has a refcount of 2 now, as the list store has added its own reference */

  g_object_unref(pixbuf);

  /* pixbuf has a refcount of 1 now that we have released our initial reference */

  /* we don't want an icon in that row any longer */
  gtk_list_store_set(list_store, &amp;iter, 0, NULL, -1);

  /* pixbuf has automatically been destroyed after its refcount has reached 0.
   *  The list store called g_object_unref() on the pixbuf when it replaced
   *  the object in the store with a new value (NULL). */
</programlisting>

      <para>Having learned how to add, manipulate, and retrieve data from a
      store, the next step is to get that data displayed in a
      <literal>GtkTreeView</literal> widget.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treemodel-storing-structs">
      <title>Storing Data Structures: of Pointers, GBoxed Types, and GObject
      (TODO)</title>

      <para>Unfinished chapter.</para>

      <!--
<para>
 <emphasis>
This section is for advanced users. You might want to skip it 
for now and come back to it later when you find yourself 
needing to store C-type custom data structures of your own 
in a tree model.
 </emphasis>
</para>

<para>
 <emphasis>
This section is also not really very refined and only a rough draft.
Its purpose is just to introduce some approaches that might not be 
immediately obvious for someone not familiar with the API.
 </emphasis>
</para>

<para>
If the data you want to display becomes more complex (or simply
just a lot), storing it into a list store or tree store using
a trizillion model columns is not always the most convenient 
way. It quickly leads to bulky code and unnecessary overhead.
</para>

<para>
Also, you often have an object or item of data where you
only want to display <emphasis>some</emphasis> of the data
in the tree view and have a fair bit of data you need to keep 
track of in addition. Storing all the data in the model is 
inconvenient, and keeping two copies of the data around and 
syncing the data in the model with the data in the structure
is also inconvenient, even more so if the data changes 
regularly.
</para>

<para>
Consider a tree view that displays the download status of 
various files, e.g. a web browser's download window. You 
might want to display the following data for each download:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para> 
   Destination File Name or Path 
  </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para> 
   Source URL
  </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>
   Size of Download
  </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>
   Download Status (Completed, Paused, Queued, Downloading, etc.) 
  </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>
   Download Speed (if applicable)
  </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>
   Estimated Time Left
  </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
An obvious solution is to keep track of a download in a structure, 
something along the lines of 
</para>

<programlisting role="C">
  typedef struct _MyDownload MyDownload;
  struct _MyDownload
  {
    gchar   *dest_fn;
    gchar   *src_url;
    guint    status;
    guint64  size;
    guint64  transfered;
    gfloat   speed;
    guint    seconds_left;
    
    ... more variables for the download action itself ..
  };
</programlisting>

<para>
Then you could have list store with a column of <literal>G_TYPE_POINTER</literal>
and just store a pointer to the structure there for each row. Instead of connecting
model columns to cell renderer properties via attributes (see below), you will have
to use cell data functions with this approach.
</para>

<para>
The main issue with storing struct pointers in a list store is that memory management 
becomes a bit awkward. You have to make sure that you remove the pointer data and/or 
whole row from the store when you free the structure. Equally, you need to free the
structure 'manually' when you remove the row and don't need it any longer. Nothing
that cannot be solved, yet still not exactly elegant either.
</para>

<para>
The advantage is of course that code that retrieves data from a row (e.g. a selected row)
becomes much cleaner, and that there is less overhead when retrieving data (like string
copies). Compare
</para>

<programlisting role="C">
void
treeview_on_row_activated (GtkTreeView       *treeview, 
                           GtkTreePath       *path, 
                           GtkTreeViewColumn *col,
                           gpointer           data)
{
  GtkTreeModel *model;
  GtkTreeIter   iter;
  
  model = gtk_tree_view_get_model (treeview);
  
  if (gtk_tree_model_get_iter (model, &amp;iter, path))
  {
    gchar   *fn, *url;
    guint    status;
    
    gtk_tree_model_get (model, &amp;iter,
                        COL_FILENAME, &amp;fn,
                        COL_URL, &amp;url,
                        COL_STATUS, &amp;status,
                        -1);
			
    ... do something with data on row double-click ....
    
    g_free (fn);
    g_free (url);
  }
}
</programlisting>

<para>
with
</para>

<programlisting role="C">
void
treeview_on_row_activated (GtkTreeView       *treeview, 
                           GtkTreePath       *path, 
                           GtkTreeViewColumn *col,
                           gpointer           data)
{
  GtkTreeModel *model;
  GtkTreeIter   iter;
  
  model = gtk_tree_view_get_model (treeview);
  
  if (gtk_tree_model_get_iter (model, &amp;iter, path))
  {
    MyDownload *dl;
    
    gtk_tree_model_get (model, &amp;iter, 0, &amp;dl, -1);
    
    ... do something with data on row double-click ....
  }
}
</programlisting>

<para>
Now, It would be nice if one could use memory management 
techniques like reference counting with one's custom 
structures, and have the tree models make use of them
automatically, just like the tree models take care of 
memory management for strings or for GObjects like GdkPixbuf.
</para>

<para>
The obvious way would be to derive MyDownload from GObject,
in which case it will be handled automatically by the models.
This requires a bit of a dive into the GObject system though 
and makes things more complicated than they have to be.
</para>

<para>
The alternative is to register your own type as a GBoxed-derived
type with the GType system, and implement some simple refcounting 
yourself. Some code snippets:
</para>


<programlisting role="C">
  #define MY_TYPE_DOWNLOAD   (my_download_get_type())
  
  typedef struct _MyDownload MyDownload;
  struct _MyDownload
  {
    gchar   *dest_fn;
    gchar   *src_url;
    guint    status;
    
    ... more ...
    
    gint     refcount;
  };
  
  void
  my_download_ref (MyDownload *dl)
  {
    g_return_if_fail (dl->refcount > 0);
    dl->refcount += 1;
  }
  
  void
  my_download_unref (MyDownload *dl)
  {
    g_return_if_fail (dl->refcount > 0);
    dl->refcount -= 1;
    
    if (dl->refcount == 0)
    {
      /* free structure content */
      g_free (dl->dest_fn);
      g_free (dl->src_url);
      
      /* poison memory */
      memset (dl, 0xFF, sizeof (MyDownload)); 
      
      /* free structure itself */
      g_free (dl);
    }
  }
  
  static gpointer
  my_download_copy_func (gpointer boxed)
  {
    my_download_ref ((MyDownload*) boxed);

    return boxed;
  }

  static void
  my_download_free_func (gpointer boxed)
  {
    /* for clarity */
    my_download_unref ((MyDownload*) boxed);
  }
  
  GType
  my_download_get_type (void)
  {
    static GType my_type = 0;
    if (my_type == 0) 
    {
      my_type = g_boxed_type_register_static ("MyDownload", 
                                              my_download_copy_func, 
                                              my_download_free_func);
    }
    return my_type;
  }
  
  MyDownload *
  make_new_download (const gchar *from, const gchar *to)
  {
    MyDownload *dl;
    
    dl = g_new0 (MyDownload, 1);
    
    dl->src_url = g_strdup (from);
    dl->dest_fn = g_strdup (to);
    
    dl->status = 0;
    dl->refcount = 1;

    return dl;
  }
</programlisting>

-->
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-treeview">
    <title>Creating a Tree View</title>

    <para>In order to display data in a tree view widget, we need to create
    one first, and we need to instruct it where to get the data to display
    from.</para>

    <para>A new tree view is created with:</para>

    <programlisting role="C">
  GtkWidget *view;

  view = gtk_tree_view_new();
</programlisting>

    <sect1 id="sec-treeview-connect-model">
      <title>Connecting Tree View and Model</title>

      <para>Before we proceed to the next section where we display data on the
      screen, we need connect our data store to the tree view, so it knows
      where to get the data to display from. This is achieved with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeView.html#gtk-tree-view-set-model">
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_set_model</literal></ulink>, which will by itself
      do very little. However, it is a prerequisite for what we do in the
      following sections. <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeView.html#gtk-tree-view-new-with-model">
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_new_with_model</literal></ulink> is a convenience
      function for the previous two.</para>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeView.html#gtk-tree-view-get-model">
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_get_model</literal></ulink> will return the model
      that is currently attached to a given tree view, which is particularly
      useful in callbacks where you only get passed the tree view widget
      (after all, we do not want to go down the road of global variables,
      which will inevitably lead to the Dark Side, do we?).</para>

      <sect2 id="sec-treeview-connect-model-refcounting">
        <title>Reference counting</title>

        <para>Tree models like <literal>GtkListStore</literal> and
        <literal>GtkTreeStore</literal> are <literal>GObjects</literal> and
        have a reference count of 1 after creation. The tree view will add its
        own reference to the model when you add the model with
        <literal>gtk_tree_view_set_model</literal>, and will unref it again
        when you replace the model with another model, unset the model by
        passing <literal>NULL</literal> as a model, or when the tree view is
        destroyed. <footnote>
            <para>'Reference counting' means that an object has a counter that
            can be increased or decreased (ref-ed and unref-ed). If the
            counter is unref-ed to 0, the object is automatically destroyed.
            This is useful, because other objects or application programmers
            only have to think about whether <emphasis>they
            themselves</emphasis> are still using that object or not, without
            knowing anything about others also using it. The object is simply
            automatically destroyed when no one is using it any more.</para>
          </footnote></para>

        <para>This means that you need to take care of "your" reference
        yourself, otherwise the model will not be destroyed properly when you
        disconnect it from the tree view, and its memory will not be freed
        (which does not matter much if the same model is connected to the tree
        view from application start to end). If you plan to use the same model
        for a tree view for the whole duration of the application, you can get
        rid of "your" reference right after you have connected the model to
        the view - then the model will be destroyed automatically when the
        tree view is destroyed (which will be automatically destroyed when the
        window it is in is destroyed):</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
  GtkListStore *liststore;
  GtkWidget    *view;

  view = gtk_tree_view_new();

  liststore = gtk_list_store_new(1, G_TYPE_STRING);

  gtk_tree_view_set_model(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view), GTK_TREE_MODEL(liststore));

  g_object_unref(liststore);

  /* Now the model will be destroyed when the tree view is destroyed */
</programlisting>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treeview-look">
      <title>Tree View Look and Feel</title>

      <para>There are a couple of ways to influence the look and feel of the
      tree view. You can hide or show column headers with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeView.html#gtk-tree-view-set-headers-visible">
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_set_headers_visible</literal></ulink>, and set
      them clickable or not with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeView.html#gtk-tree-view-set-headers-clickable">
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_set_headers_clickable</literal></ulink> (which
      will be done automatically for you if you enable sorting).</para>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeView.html#gtk-tree-view-set-rules-hint">
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_set_rules_hint</literal></ulink> will enable or
      disable rules in the tree view. <footnote>
          <para>'Rules' means that every second line of the tree view has a
          shaded background, which makes it easier to see which cell belongs
          to which row in tree views that have a lot of columns.</para>
        </footnote> As the function name implies, this setting is only a hint;
      in the end it depends on the active Gtk+ theme engine if the tree view
      shows ruled lines or not. Users seem to have strong feelings about rules
      in tree views, so it is probably a good idea to provide an option
      somewhere to disable rule hinting if you set it on tree views (but then,
      people also seem to have strong feelings about options abundance and
      'sensible' default options, so whatever you do will probably upset
      someone at some point).</para>

      <para>The expander column can be set with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeView.html#gtk-tree-view-set-expander-column">
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_set_expander_column</literal></ulink>. This is
      the column where child elements are indented with respect to their
      parents, and where rows with children have an 'expander' arrow with
      which a node's children can be collapsed (hidden) or expanded (shown).
      By default, this is the first column.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-treeviewcol-renderer">
    <title>Mapping Data to the Screen: GtkTreeViewColumn and
    GtkCellRenderer</title>

    <para>As outlined above, tree view columns represent the visible columns
    on the screen that have a column header with a column name and can be
    resized or sorted. A tree view is made up of tree view columns, and you
    need at least one tree view column in order to display something in the
    tree view. Tree view columns, however, do not display anything by
    themselves, this is done by specialised <literal>GtkCellRenderer</literal>
    objects. Cell renderers are packed into tree view columns much like
    widgets are packed into <literal>GtkHBoxes</literal>.</para>

    <para>Here is a diagram (courtesy of Owen Taylor) that pictures the
    relationship between tree view columns and cell renderers:</para>

    <figure id="sec-treeviewcol-renderer-diagram">
      <title>Cell Renderer Properties</title>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/tree-view-column.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/tree-view-column.eps" format="EPS"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>In the above diagram, both 'Country' and 'Representative' are tree
    view columns, where the 'Country' and 'Representative' labels are the
    column headers. The 'Country' column contains two cell renderers, one to
    display the flag icons, and one to display the country name. The
    'Representative' column only contains one cell renderer to display the
    representative's name.</para>

    <sect1 id="sec-renderer">
      <title>Cell Renderers</title>

      <para>Cell renderers are objects that are responsible for the actual
      rendering of data within a <literal>GtkTreeViewColumn</literal>. They
      are basically just GObjects (ie. not widgets) that have certain
      properties, and those properties determine how a single cell is
      drawn.</para>

      <para>In order to draw cells in different rows with different content, a
      cell renderer's properties need to be set accordingly for each single
      row/cell to render. This is done either via <link
      linkend="sec-treeview-col-attributes">attributes</link> or <link
      linkend="sec-treeview-col-celldatafunc">cell data functions</link> (see
      below). If you set up attributes, you tell Gtk which model column
      contains the data from which a property should be set before rendering a
      certain row. Then the properties of a cell renderer are set
      automatically according to the data in the model before each row is
      rendered. Alternatively, you can set up cell data functions, which are
      called for each row to be rendererd, so that you can manually set the
      properties of the cell renderer before it is rendered. Both approaches
      can be used at the same time as well. Lastly, you can set a cell
      renderer property when you create the cell renderer. That way it will be
      used for all rows/cells to be rendered (unless it is changed later of
      course).</para>

      <para>Different cell renderers exist for different purposes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara><ulink
          url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkCellRendererText.html">
          <literal>GtkCellRendererText</literal></ulink> renders strings or
          numbers or boolean values as text ("Joe", "99.32", "true")</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><ulink
          url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkCellRendererPixbuf.html">
          <literal>GtkCellRendererPixbuf</literal></ulink> is used to display
          images; either user-defined images, or one of the stock icons that
          come with Gtk+.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><ulink
          url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkCellRendererToggle.html">
          <literal>GtkCellRendererToggle</literal></ulink> displays a boolean
          value in form of a check box or as a radio button.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara><ulink
          url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkCellEditable.html">
          <literal>GtkCellEditable</literal></ulink> is a special cell that
          implements editable cells (ie. GtkEntry or GtkSpinbutton in a
          treeview). This is not a cell renderer! If you want to have editable
          text cells, use <literal>GtkCellRendererText</literal> and make sure
          the "editable" property is set. <literal>GtkCellEditable</literal>
          is only used by implementations of editable cells and widgets that
          can be inside of editable cells. You are unlikely to ever need
          it.</simpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Contrary to what one may think, a cell renderer does not render
      just one single cell, but is responsible for rendering part or whole of
      a tree view column for each single row. It basically starts in the first
      row and renders its part of the column there. Then it proceeds to the
      next row and renders its part of the column there again. And so
      on.</para>

      <para>How does a cell renderer know what to render? A cell renderer
      object has certain 'properties' that are documented in the <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/TreeWidgetObjects.html">
      API reference</ulink> (just like most other objects, and widgets). These
      properties determine what the cell renderer is going to render and how
      it is going to be rendered. Whenever the cell renderer is called upon to
      render a certain cell, it looks at its properties and renders the cell
      accordingly. This means that whenever you set a property or change a
      property of the cell renderer, this will affect all rows that are
      rendered after the change, until you change the property again.</para>

      <para>Here is a diagram (courtesy of Owen Taylor) that tries to show
      what is going on when rows are rendered:</para>

      <figure id="sec-treeviewcol-diagram">
        <title>GtkTreeViewColumns and GtkCellRenderers</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cell-renderer-properties.png"
                         format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cell-renderer-properties.eps"
                         format="EPS"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>

      <para>The above diagram shows the process when attributes are used. In
      the example, a text cell renderer's <literal>"text"</literal> property
      has been linked to the first model column. The <literal>"text"</literal>
      property contains the string to be rendered. The
      <literal>"foreground"</literal> property, which contains the colour of
      the text to be shown, has been linked to the second model column.
      Finally, the <literal>"strikethrough"</literal> property, which
      determines whether the text should be with a horizontal line that
      strikes through the text, has been connected to the third model column
      (of type <literal>G_TYPE_BOOLEAN</literal>).</para>

      <para>With this setup, the cell renderer's properties are 'loaded' from
      the model before each cell is rendered.</para>

      <para>Here is a silly and utterly useless little example that
      demonstrates this behaviour, and introduces some of the most commonly
      used properties of <literal>GtkCellRendererText</literal>:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
#include &lt;gtk/gtk.h&gt;

enum
{
  COL_FIRST_NAME = 0,
  COL_LAST_NAME,
  NUM_COLS
} ;

static GtkTreeModel *
create_and_fill_model (void)
{
  GtkTreeStore  *treestore;
  GtkTreeIter    toplevel, child;

  treestore = gtk_tree_store_new(NUM_COLS, G_TYPE_STRING, G_TYPE_STRING);

  /* Append a top level row and leave it empty */
  gtk_tree_store_append(treestore, &amp;toplevel, NULL);

  /* Append a second top level row, and fill it with some data */
  gtk_tree_store_append(treestore, &amp;toplevel, NULL);
  gtk_tree_store_set(treestore, &amp;toplevel,
                     COL_FIRST_NAME, "Joe",
                     COL_LAST_NAME, "Average",
                     -1);

  /* Append a child to the second top level row, and fill in some data */
  gtk_tree_store_append(treestore, &amp;child, &amp;toplevel);
  gtk_tree_store_set(treestore, &amp;child,
                     COL_FIRST_NAME, "Jane",
                     COL_LAST_NAME, "Average",
                     -1);

  return GTK_TREE_MODEL(treestore);
}

static GtkWidget *
create_view_and_model (void)
{
  GtkTreeViewColumn   *col;
  GtkCellRenderer     *renderer;
  GtkWidget           *view;
  GtkTreeModel        *model;

  view = gtk_tree_view_new();

  /* --- Column #1 --- */

  col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();

  gtk_tree_view_column_set_title(col, "First Name");

  /* pack tree view column into tree view */
  gtk_tree_view_append_column(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view), col);

  renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();

  /* pack cell renderer into tree view column */
  gtk_tree_view_column_pack_start(col, renderer, TRUE);

  /* set 'text' property of the cell renderer */
  g_object_set(renderer, "text", "Boooo!", NULL);


  /* --- Column #2 --- */

  col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();

  gtk_tree_view_column_set_title(col, "Last Name");

  /* pack tree view column into tree view */
  gtk_tree_view_append_column(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view), col);

  renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();

  /* pack cell renderer into tree view column */
  gtk_tree_view_column_pack_start(col, renderer, TRUE);

  /* set 'cell-background' property of the cell renderer */
  g_object_set(renderer,
               "cell-background", "Orange",
               "cell-background-set", TRUE,
               NULL);

  model = create_and_fill_model();

  gtk_tree_view_set_model(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view), model);

  g_object_unref(model); /* destroy model automatically with view */

  gtk_tree_selection_set_mode(gtk_tree_view_get_selection(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view)),
                              GTK_SELECTION_NONE);

  return view;
}


int
main (int argc, char **argv)
{
  GtkWidget *window;
  GtkWidget *view;

  gtk_init(&amp;argc, &amp;argv);

  window = gtk_window_new(GTK_WINDOW_TOPLEVEL);
  g_signal_connect(window, "delete_event", gtk_main_quit, NULL); /* dirty */

  view = create_view_and_model();

  gtk_container_add(GTK_CONTAINER(window), view);

  gtk_widget_show_all(window);

  gtk_main();

  return 0;
}


</programlisting>

      <para>The above code should produce something looking like this:</para>

      <figure id="sec-renderer-sshot">
        <title>Persistent Cell Renderer Properties</title>

        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/renderer.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/renderer.eps" format="EPS"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>

      <para>It looks like the tree view display is partly correct and partly
      incomplete. On the one hand the tree view renders the correct number of
      rows (note how there is no orange on the right after row 3), and it
      displays the hierarchy correctly (on the left), but it does not display
      any of the data that we have stored in the model. This is because we
      have made no connection between what the cell renderers should render
      and the data in the model. We have simply set some cell renderer
      properties on start-up, and the cell renderers adhere to those set
      properties meticulously.</para>

      <para>There are two different ways to connect cell renderers to data in
      the model: <link linkend="sec-treeview-col-attributes">attributes</link>
      and <link linkend="sec-treeview-col-celldatafunc">cell data
      functions</link>.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treeview-col-attributes">
      <title>Attributes</title>

      <para>An attribute is a connection between a cell renderer property and
      a field/column in the model. Whenever a cell is to be rendered, a cell
      renderer property will be set to the values of the specified model
      column of the row that is to be rendered. It is very important that the
      column's data type is the same type that a property takes according to
      the API reference manual. Here is some code to look at:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">

   ...

   col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();

   renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();

   gtk_tree_view_column_pack_start(col, renderer, TRUE);

   gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute(col, renderer, "text", COL_FIRST_NAME);

   ...

</programlisting>

      <para>This means that the text cell renderer property
      <literal>"text"</literal> will be set to the string in model column
      <literal>COL_FIRST_NAME</literal> of each row to be drawn. It is
      important to internalise the difference between <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeViewColumn.html#gtk-tree-view-column-add-attribute">
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute</literal></ulink> and
      <literal>g_object_set</literal>: <literal>g_object_set</literal> sets a
      property to a certain <emphasis>value</emphasis>, while
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute</literal> sets a property to
      whatever is in the specified _model column_ at the time of
      rendering.</para>

      <para>Again, when setting attributes it is very important that the data
      type stored in a model column is the same as the data type that a
      property requires as argument. Check the API reference manual to see the
      data type that is required for each property. When reading through the
      example a bit further above, you might have noticed that we set the
      <literal>"cell-background"</literal> property of a <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkCellRendererText.html">
      <literal>GtkCellRendererText</literal></ulink>, even though the API
      documentation does not list such a property. We can do this, because
      <literal>GtkCellRendererText</literal> is derived from <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkCellRenderer.html">
      <literal>GtkCellRenderer</literal></ulink>, which does in fact <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkCellRenderer.html#GtkCellRenderer--cell-background">
      have</ulink> such a property. Derived classes inherit the properties of
      their parents. This is the same as with widgets that you can cast into
      one of their ancestor classes. The API reference has an <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/ch01.html">object
      hierarchy</ulink> that shows you which classes a widget or some other
      object is derived from.</para>

      <para>There are two more noteworthy things about
      <literal>GtkCellRenderer</literal> properties: one is that sometimes
      there are different properties which do the same, but take different
      arguments, such as the <literal>"foreground"</literal> and
      <literal>"foreground-gdk"</literal> properties of
      <literal>GtkCellRendererText</literal> (which specify the text colour).
      The <literal>"foreground"</literal> property take a colour in string
      form, such as "Orange" or "CornflowerBlue", whereas
      <literal>"foreground-gdk"</literal> takes a <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gdk/gdk-Colormaps-and-Colors.html#GdkColor">GdkColor</ulink>
      argument. It is up to you to decide which one to use - the effect will
      be the same. The other thing worth mentioning is that most properties
      have a <literal>"foo-set"</literal> property taking a boolean value as
      argument, such as <literal>"foreground-set"</literal>. This is useful
      when you want to have a certain setting have an effect or not. If you
      set the <literal>"foreground"</literal> property, but set
      <literal>"foreground-set"</literal> to <literal>FALSE</literal>, then
      your foreground color setting will be disregarded. This is useful in
      cell data functions (see below), or, for example, if you want set the
      foreground colour to a certain value at start-up, but only want this to
      be in effect in some columns, but not in others (in which case you could
      just connect the <literal>"foreground-set"</literal> property to a model
      column of type <literal>G_TYPE_BOOLEAN</literal> with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeViewColumn.html#gtk-tree-view-column-add-attribute">
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute</literal></ulink>.</para>

      <para>Setting column attributes is the most straight-forward way to get
      your model data to be displayed. This is usually used whenever you want
      the data in the model to be displayed exactly as it is in the
      model.</para>

      <para>Another way to get your model data displayed on the screen is to
      set up cell data functions.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treeview-col-celldatafunc">
      <title>Cell Data Functions</title>

      <para>A cell data function is a function that is called for a specific
      cell renderer for each single row before that row is rendered. It gives
      you maximum control over what exactly is going to be rendered, as you
      can set the cell renderer's properties just like you want to have them.
      Remember not only to <emphasis>set</emphasis> a property if you want it
      to be active, but also to <emphasis>unset</emphasis> a property if it
      should not be active (and it might have been set in the previous
      row).</para>

      <para>Cell data functions are often used if you want more fine-grained
      control over what is to be displayed, or if the standard way to display
      something is not quite like you want it to be. A case in point are
      floating point numbers. If you want floating point numbers to be
      displayed in a certain way, say with only one digit after the
      colon/comma, then you need to use a cell data function. Use <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeViewColumn.html#gtk-tree-view-column-set-cell-data-func">
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_column_set_cell_data_func</literal></ulink> to
      set up a cell data function for a particular cell renderer. Here is an
      example:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">

   enum
   {
     COLUMN_NAME = 0,
     COLUMN_AGE_FLOAT,
     NUM_COLS
   };

   ...

   static void
   age_cell_data_function (GtkTreeViewColumn *col,
                           GtkCellRenderer   *renderer,
                           GtkTreeModel      *model,
                           GtkTreeIter       *iter,
                           gpointer           user_data)
   {
     gfloat  age;
     gchar   buf[20];

     gtk_tree_model_get(model, iter, COLUMN_AGE_FLOAT, &amp;age, -1);

     g_snprintf(buf, sizeof(buf), "%.1f", age);

     g_object_set(renderer, "text", buf, NULL);
   }

   ...

   liststore = gtk_list_store_new(NUM_COLS, G_TYPE_STRING, G_TYPE_FLOAT);

   col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();

   cell = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();

   gtk_tree_view_column_pack_start(col, cell, TRUE);

   gtk_tree_view_column_set_cell_data_func(col, cell, age_cell_data_func, NULL, NULL);

   ...

</programlisting>

      <para>for each row to be rendered by this particular cell renderer, the
      cell data function is going to be called, which then retrieves the float
      from the model, and turns it into a string where the float has only one
      digit after the colon/comma, and renders that with the text cell
      renderer.</para>

      <para>This is only a simple example, you can make cell data functions a
      lot more complicated if you want to. As always, there is a trade-off to
      keep in mind though. Your cell data function is going to be called every
      single time a cell in that (renderer) column is going to be rendered. Go
      and check how often this function is called in your program if you ever
      use one. If you do time-consuming operations within a cell data
      function, things are not going to be fast, especially if you have a lot
      of rows. The alternative in this case would have been to make an
      additional column COLUMN_AGE_FLOAT_STRING of type
      <literal>G_TYPE_STRING</literal>, and to set the float in string form
      whenever you set the float itself in a row, and then hook up the string
      column to a text cell renderer using attributes. This way the float to
      string conversion would only need to be done once. This is a cpu cycles
      / memory trade-off, and it depends on your particular case which one is
      more suitable. Things you should probably not do is to convert long
      strings into UTF8 format in a cell data function, for example.</para>

      <para>You might notice that your cell data function is called at times
      even for rows that are not visible at the moment. This is because the
      tree view needs to know its total height, and in order to calculate this
      it needs to know the height of each and every single row, and it can
      only know that by having it measured, which is going to be slow when you
      have a lot of rows with different heights (if your rows all have the
      same height, there should not be any visible delay though).</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treeview-celltext-types">
      <title>GtkCellRendererText and Integer, Boolean and Float Types</title>

      <para>It has been said before that, when using attributes to connect
      data from the model to a cell renderer property, the data in the model
      column specified in
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute</literal> must always be of
      the same type as the data type that the property requires.</para>

      <para>This is usually true, but there is an exception: if you use
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute</literal> to connect a text
      cell renderer's <literal>"text"</literal> property to a model column,
      the model column does not need to be of
      <literal>G_TYPE_STRING</literal>, it can also be one of most other
      fundamental GLib types, e.g. <literal>G_TYPE_BOOLEAN</literal>,
      <literal>G_TYPE_INT</literal>, <literal>G_TYPE_UINT</literal>,
      <literal>G_TYPE_LONG</literal>, <literal>G_TYPE_ULONG</literal>,
      <literal>G_TYPE_INT64</literal>, <literal>G_TYPE_UINT64</literal>,
      <literal>G_TYPE_FLOAT</literal>, or <literal>G_TYPE_DOUBLE</literal>.
      The text cell renderer will automatically display the values of these
      types correctly in the tree view. For example:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  enum
  {
    COL_NAME = 0,
    COL_YEAR_BORN,
    NUM_COLS
  };

  liststore = gtk_list_store_new(NUM_COLS, G_TYPE_STRING, G_TYPE_UINT);

  ...

  cell = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();
  col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();
  gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute(col, cell, "text", COL_YEAR_BORN);

  ...
</programlisting>

      <para>Even though the <literal>"text"</literal> property would require a
      string value, we use a model column of an integer type when setting
      attributes. The integer will then automatically be converted into a
      string before the cell renderer property is set <footnote>
          <para>For those interested, the conversion actually takes place
          within <literal>g_object_set_property</literal>. Before a certain
          cell is rendered, the tree view column will call
          <literal>gtk_tree_model_get_value</literal> to set the cell renderer
          properties according to values stored in the tree model (if any are
          mapped via <literal>gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute</literal> or
          one of the convenience functions that do the same thing), and then
          pass on the <literal>GValue</literal> retrieved to
          <literal>g_object_set_property</literal>.</para>
        </footnote>.</para>

      <para>If you are using a floating point type, ie.
      <literal>G_TYPE_FLOAT</literal> or <literal>G_TYPE_DOUBLE</literal>,
      there is no way to tell the text cell renderer how many digits after the
      floating point (or comma) should be rendered. If you only want a certain
      amount of digits after the point/comma, you will need to use a <link
      linkend="sec-treeview-col-celldatafunc">cell data
      function</link>.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treeview-col-utf8-pango">
      <title>GtkCellRendererText, UTF8, and pango markup</title>

      <para>All text used in Gtk+-2.0 widgets needs to be in UTF8 encoding,
      and <literal>GtkCellRendererText</literal> is no exception. Text in
      plain ASCII is automatically valid UTF8, but as soon as you have special
      characters that do not exist in plain ASCII (usually characters that are
      not used in the English language alphabet), they need to be in UTF8
      encoding. There are many different character encodings that all specify
      different ways to tell the computer which character is meant. Gtk+-2.0
      uses UTF8, and whenever you have text that is in a different encoding,
      you need to convert it to UTF8 encoding first, using one of the GLib
      <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/glib/glib-Character-Set-Conversion.html">
      <literal>g_convert</literal></ulink> family of functions. If you only
      use text input from other Gtk+ widgets, you are on the safe side, as
      they will return all text in UTF8 as well.</para>

      <para>However, if you use 'external' sources of text input, then you
      must convert that text from the text's encoding (or the user's locale)
      to UTF8, or it will not be rendered correctly (either not at all, or it
      will be cut off after the first invalid character). Filenames are
      especially hard, because there is no indication whatsoever what
      character encoding a filename is in (it might have been created when the
      user was using a different locale, so filename encoding is basically
      unreliable and broken). You may want to convert to UTF8 with fallback
      characters in that case. You can check whether a string is valid UTF8
      with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/glib/glib-Unicode-Manipulation.html#g-utf8-validate">
      <literal>g_utf8_validate</literal></ulink>. You should, in this author's
      opinion at least, put these checks into your code at crucial places
      wherever it is not affecting performance, especially if you are an
      English-speaking programmer that has little experience with non-English
      locales. It will make it easier for others and yourself to spot problems
      with non-English locales later on.</para>

      <para>In addition to the "text" property, GtkCellRendererText also has a
      "markup" property that takes text with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/pango/PangoMarkupFormat.html">
      pango markup</ulink> as input. Pango markup allows you to place special
      tags into a text string that affect the style the text is rendered (see
      the pango documentation). Basically you can achieve everything you can
      achieve with the other properties also with pango markup (only that
      using properties is more efficient and less messy). Pango markup has one
      distinct advantage though that you cannot achieve with text cell
      renderer properties: with pango markup, you can change the text style in
      the middle of the text, so you could, for example, render one part of a
      text string in bold print, and the rest of the text in normal. Here is
      an example of a string with pango markup:</para>

      <para><literal> "You can have text in &lt;b&gt;bold&lt;/b&gt; or in a
      &lt;span color='Orange'&gt;different color&lt;/span&gt;"
      </literal></para>

      <para>When using the <literal>"markup"</literal> property, you need to
      take into account that the <literal>"markup"</literal> and
      <literal>"text"</literal> properties do not seem to be mutually
      exclusive (I suppose this could be called a bug). In other words:
      whenever you set <literal>"markup"</literal> (and have used the
      <literal>"text"</literal> property before), set the
      <literal>"text"</literal> property to NULL, and vice versa.
      Example:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  ...

  void
  foo_cell_data_function ( ... )
  {
    ...
    if (foo-&gt;is_important)
      g_object_set(renderer, "markup", "&lt;b&gt;important&lt;/b&gt;", "text", NULL, NULL);
    else
      g_object_set(renderer, "markup", NULL, "text", "not important", NULL);
    ...
  }

  ...
</programlisting>

      <para>Another thing to keep in mind when using pango markup text is that
      you might need to escape text if you construct strings with pango markup
      on the fly using random input data. For example:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  ...

  void
  foo_cell_data_function ( ... )
  {
    gchar *markuptxt;

    ...
    /* This might be problematic if artist_string or title_string
     *   contain markup characters/entities: */
    markuptxt = g_strdup_printf("&lt;b&gt;%s&lt;/b&gt; - &lt;i&gt;%s&lt;/i&gt;",
                                artist_string, title_string);
    ...
    g_object_set(renderer, "markup", markuptxt, "text", NULL, NULL);
    ...
    g_free(markuptxt);
  }

  ...
</programlisting>

      <para>The above example will not work if artist_string is "Simon &amp;
      Garfunkel" for example, because the &amp; character is one of the
      characters that is special. They need to be escaped, so that pango knows
      that they do not refer to any pango markup, but are just characters. In
      this case the string would need to be "Simon &amp;amp; Garfunkel" in
      order to make sense in between the pango markup in which it is going to
      be pasted. You can escape a string with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/glib/glib-Simple-XML-Subset-Parser.html#g-markup-escape-text">
      <literal>g_markup_escape</literal></ulink> (and you will need to free
      the resulting newly-allocated string again with
      <literal>g_free</literal>).</para>

      <para>It is possible to combine both pango markup and text cell renderer
      properties. Both will be 'added' together to render the string in
      question, only that the text cell renderer properties will be applied to
      the whole string. If you set the <literal>"markup"</literal> property to
      normal text without any pango markup, it will render as normal text just
      as if you had used the <literal>"text"</literal> property. However, as
      opposed to the <literal>"text"</literal> property, special characters in
      the <literal>"markup"</literal> property text would still need to be
      escaped, even if you do not use pango markup in the text.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treeview-col-example">
      <title>A Working Example</title>

      <para>Here is our example from the very beginning again (with an
      additional column though), only that the contents of the model are
      rendered properly on the screen this time. Both attributes and a cell
      data function are used for demonstration purposes.</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
#include &lt;gtk/gtk.h&gt;

enum
{
  COL_FIRST_NAME = 0,
  COL_LAST_NAME,
  COL_YEAR_BORN,
  NUM_COLS
} ;

static GtkTreeModel *
create_and_fill_model (void)
{
  GtkTreeStore  *treestore;
  GtkTreeIter    toplevel, child;

  treestore = gtk_tree_store_new(NUM_COLS,
                                 G_TYPE_STRING,
                                 G_TYPE_STRING,
                                 G_TYPE_UINT);

  /* Append a top level row and leave it empty */
  gtk_tree_store_append(treestore, &amp;toplevel, NULL);
  gtk_tree_store_set(treestore, &amp;toplevel,
                     COL_FIRST_NAME, "Maria",
                     COL_LAST_NAME, "Incognito",
                     -1);

  /* Append a second top level row, and fill it with some data */
  gtk_tree_store_append(treestore, &amp;toplevel, NULL);
  gtk_tree_store_set(treestore, &amp;toplevel,
                     COL_FIRST_NAME, "Jane",
                     COL_LAST_NAME, "Average",
                     COL_YEAR_BORN, (guint) 1962,
                     -1);

  /* Append a child to the second top level row, and fill in some data */
  gtk_tree_store_append(treestore, &amp;child, &amp;toplevel);
  gtk_tree_store_set(treestore, &amp;child,
                     COL_FIRST_NAME, "Janinita",
                     COL_LAST_NAME, "Average",
                     COL_YEAR_BORN, (guint) 1985,
                     -1);

  return GTK_TREE_MODEL(treestore);
}

void
age_cell_data_func (GtkTreeViewColumn *col,
                    GtkCellRenderer   *renderer,
                    GtkTreeModel      *model,
                    GtkTreeIter       *iter,
                    gpointer           user_data)
{
  guint  year_born;
  guint  year_now = 2003; /* to save code not relevant for the example */
  gchar  buf[64];

  gtk_tree_model_get(model, iter, COL_YEAR_BORN, &amp;year_born, -1);

  if (year_born &lt;= year_now &amp;&amp; year_born &gt; 0)
  {
    guint age = year_now - year_born;

    g_snprintf(buf, sizeof(buf), "%u years old", age);

    g_object_set(renderer, "foreground-set", FALSE, NULL); /* print this normal */
  }
  else
  {
    g_snprintf(buf, sizeof(buf), "age unknown");

    /* make red */
    g_object_set(renderer, "foreground", "Red", "foreground-set", TRUE, NULL);
  }

  g_object_set(renderer, "text", buf, NULL);
}


static GtkWidget *
create_view_and_model (void)
{
  GtkTreeViewColumn   *col;
  GtkCellRenderer     *renderer;
  GtkWidget           *view;
  GtkTreeModel        *model;

  view = gtk_tree_view_new();

  /* --- Column #1 --- */

  col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();

  gtk_tree_view_column_set_title(col, "First Name");

  /* pack tree view column into tree view */
  gtk_tree_view_append_column(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view), col);

  renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();

  /* pack cell renderer into tree view column */
  gtk_tree_view_column_pack_start(col, renderer, TRUE);

  /* connect 'text' property of the cell renderer to
   *  model column that contains the first name */
  gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute(col, renderer, "text", COL_FIRST_NAME);


  /* --- Column #2 --- */

  col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();

  gtk_tree_view_column_set_title(col, "Last Name");

  /* pack tree view column into tree view */
  gtk_tree_view_append_column(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view), col);

  renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();

  /* pack cell renderer into tree view column */
  gtk_tree_view_column_pack_start(col, renderer, TRUE);

  /* connect 'text' property of the cell renderer to
   *  model column that contains the last name */
  gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute(col, renderer, "text", COL_LAST_NAME);

  /* set 'weight' property of the cell renderer to
   *  bold print (we want all last names in bold) */
  g_object_set(renderer,
               "weight", PANGO_WEIGHT_BOLD,
               "weight-set", TRUE,
               NULL);


  /* --- Column #3 --- */

  col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();

  gtk_tree_view_column_set_title(col, "Age");

  /* pack tree view column into tree view */
  gtk_tree_view_append_column(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view), col);

  renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();

  /* pack cell renderer into tree view column */
  gtk_tree_view_column_pack_start(col, renderer, TRUE);

  /* connect a cell data function */
  gtk_tree_view_column_set_cell_data_func(col, renderer, age_cell_data_func, NULL, NULL);


  model = create_and_fill_model();

  gtk_tree_view_set_model(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view), model);

  g_object_unref(model); /* destroy model automatically with view */

  gtk_tree_selection_set_mode(gtk_tree_view_get_selection(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view)),
                              GTK_SELECTION_NONE);

  return view;
}


int
main (int argc, char **argv)
{
  GtkWidget *window;
  GtkWidget *view;

  gtk_init(&amp;argc, &amp;argv);

  window = gtk_window_new(GTK_WINDOW_TOPLEVEL);
  g_signal_connect(window, "delete_event", gtk_main_quit, NULL); /* dirty */

  view = create_view_and_model();

  gtk_container_add(GTK_CONTAINER(window), view);

  gtk_widget_show_all(window);

  gtk_main();

  return 0;
}


</programlisting>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treeview-col-whole-row">
      <title>How to Make a Whole Row Bold or Coloured</title>

      <para>This seems to be a frequently asked question, so it is worth
      mentioning it here. You have the two approaches mentioned above: either
      you use cell data functions, and check in each whether a particular row
      should be highlighted in a particular way (bold, coloured, whatever),
      and then set the renderer properties accordingly (and unset them if you
      want that row to look normal), or you use attributes. Cell data
      functions are most likely not the right choice in this case
      though.</para>

      <para>If you only want every second line to have a gray background to
      make it easier for the user to see which data belongs to which line in
      wide tree views, then you do not have to bother with the stuff mentioned
      here. Instead just set the rules hint on the tree view as described in
      the <link linkend="sec-treeview-look"> here</link>, and everything will
      be done automatically, in colours that conform to the chosen theme even
      (unless the theme disables rule hints, that is).</para>

      <para>Otherwise, the most suitable approach for most cases is that you
      add two columns to your model, one for the property itself (e.g. a
      column COL_ROW_COLOR of type <literal>G_TYPE_STRING</literal>), and one
      for the boolean flag of the property (e.g. a column COL_ROW_COLOR_SET of
      type <literal>G_TYPE_BOOLEAN</literal>). You would then connect these
      columns with the <literal>"foreground"</literal> and
      <literal>"foreground-set"</literal> properties of each renderer. Now,
      whenever you set a row's COL_ROW_COLOR field to a colour, and set that
      row's COL_ROW_COLOR_SET field to <literal>TRUE</literal>, then this
      column will be rendered in the colour of your choice. If you only want
      either the default text colour or one special other colour, you could
      even achieve the same thing with just one extra model column: in this
      case you could just set all renderer's <literal>"foreground"</literal>
      property to whatever special color you want, and only connect the
      COL_ROW_COLOR_SET column to all renderer's
      <literal>"foreground-set"</literal> property using attributes. This
      works similar with any other attribute, only that you need to adjust the
      data type for the property of course (e.g. <literal>"weight"</literal>
      would take a <literal>G_TYPE_INT</literal>, in form of a
      <literal>PANGO_WEIGHT_FOO</literal> define in this case).</para>

      <para>As a general rule, you should not change the text colour or the
      background colour of a cell unless you have a really good reason for it.
      To <ulink url="http://ometer.com/gtk-colors.html">quote</ulink> Havoc
      Pennington: <quote>Because colors in GTK+ represent a theme the user has
      chosen, you should never set colors purely for aesthetic reasons. If
      users don't like GTK+ gray, they can change it themselves to their
      favorite shade of orange.</quote></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treeview-col-pixbufs">
      <title>How to Pack Icons into the Tree View</title>

      <para>So far we have only put text in the tree view. While everything
      you need to know to display icons (in the form of
      <literal>GdkPixbuf</literal>s) has been introduced in the previous
      sections, a short example might help to make things clearer. The
      following code will pack an icon and some text into the same tree view
      column:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">

  enum
  {
    COL_ICON = 0,
    COL_TEXT,
    NUM_COLS
  };

  GtkListStore *
  create_liststore(void)
  {
    GtkListStore  *store;
    GtkTreeIter    iter;
    GdkPixbuf     *icon;
    GError        *error = NULL;

    store = gtk_list_store_new(2, GDK_TYPE_PIXBUF, G_TYPE_STRING);

    icon = gdk_pixbuf_new_from_file("icon.png", &amp;error);
    if (error)
    {
      g_warning ("Could not load icon: %s\n", error-&gt;message);
      g_error_free(error);
      error = NULL;
    }

    gtk_list_store_append(store, &amp;iter);
    gtk_list_store_set(store, &amp;iter,
                       COL_ICON, icon,
                       COL_TEXT, "example",
                       -1);

    return store;
  }

  GtkWidget *
  create_treeview(void)
  {
    GtkTreeModel      *model;
    GtkTreeViewColumn *col;
    GtkCellRenderer   *renderer;
    GtkWidget         *view;

    model = GTK_TREE_MODEL(create_liststore());

    view = gtk_tree_view_new_with_model(model);

    col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();
    gtk_tree_view_column_set_title(col, "Title");

    renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_pixbuf_new();
    gtk_tree_view_column_pack_start(col, renderer, FALSE);
    gtk_tree_view_column_set_attributes(col, renderer,
                                        "pixbuf", COL_ICON,
                                        NULL);

    renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();
    gtk_tree_view_column_pack_start(col, renderer, TRUE);
    gtk_tree_view_column_set_attributes(col, renderer,
                                        "text", COL_TEXT,
                                        NULL);

    gtk_tree_view_append_column(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view), col);

    gtk_widget_show_all(view);

    return view;
  }

</programlisting>

      <para>Note that the tree view will not resize icons for you, but
      displays them in their original size. If you want to display <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/gtk-Stock-Items.html">
      stock icons</ulink> instead of <literal>GdkPixbuf</literal>s loaded from
      file, you should have a look at the <literal>"stock-id"</literal>
      property of <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkCellRendererPixbuf.html">
      <literal>GtkCellRendererPixbuf</literal></ulink> (and your model column
      should be of type <literal>G_TYPE_STRING</literal>, as all stock IDs are
      just strings by which to identify the stock icon).</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-sel-click-menus">
    <title>Selections, Double-Clicks and Context Menus</title>

    <sect1 id="sec-selections">
      <title>Handling Selections</title>

      <para>One of the most basic features of a list or tree view is that rows
      can be selected or unselected. Selections are handled using the <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSelection.html">
      <literal>GtkTreeSelection</literal></ulink> object of a tree view. Every
      tree view automatically has a <literal>GtkTreeSelection</literal>
      associated with it, and you can get it using <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeView.html#gtk-tree-view-get-selection">
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_get_selection</literal></ulink>. Selections are
      handled completely on the tree view side, which means that the model
      knows nothing about which rows are selected or not. There is no
      particular reason why selection handling could not have been implemented
      with functions that access the tree view widget directly, but for
      reasons of API cleanliness and code clarity the Gtk+ developers decided
      to create this special <literal>GtkTreeSelection</literal> object that
      then internally deals with the tree view widget. You will never need to
      create a tree selection object, it will be created for you automatically
      when you create a new tree view. You only need to use said
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_get_selection</literal> function to get a pointer
      to the selection object.</para>

      <para>There are three ways to deal with tree view selections: either you
      get a list of the currently selected rows whenever you need it, for
      example within a context menu function, or you keep track of all select
      and unselect actions and keep a list of the currently selected rows
      around for whenever you need them; as a last resort, you can also
      traverse your list or tree and check each single row for whether it is
      selected or not (which you need to do if you want all rows that are
      <emphasis>not</emphasis> selected for example).</para>

      <sect2 id="sec-selections-modes">
        <title>Selection Modes</title>

        <para>You can use <literal>gtk_tree_selection_set_mode</literal> to
        influence the way that selections are handled. There are four
        selection modes:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <simpara><literal>GTK_SELECTION_NONE</literal> - no items can be
            selected</simpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <simpara><literal>GTK_SELECTION_SINGLE</literal> - no more than
            one item can be selected</simpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <simpara><literal>GTK_SELECTION_BROWSE</literal> - exactly one
            item is always selected</simpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <simpara><literal>GTK_SELECTION_MULTIPLE</literal> - anything
            between no item and all items can be selected</simpara>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-selections-current">
        <title>Getting the Currently Selected Rows</title>

        <para>You can access the currently selected rows either by traversing
        all selected rows using <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSelection.html#gtk-tree-selection-selected-foreach">
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_selected_foreach</literal></ulink> or get
        a <literal>GList</literal> of tree paths of the selected rows using
        <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSelection.html#gtk-tree-selection-get-selected-rows">
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_get_selected_rows</literal></ulink>. Note
        that this function is only available in Gtk+-2.2 and newer, which
        means that you can't use it or need to reimplement it if you want your
        application to work with older installations.</para>

        <para>If the selection mode you are using is either
        <literal>GTK_SELECTION_SINGLE</literal> or
        <literal>GTK_SELECTION_BROWSE</literal>, the most convenient way to
        get the selected row is the function
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_get_selected</literal>, which will return
        <literal>TRUE</literal> and fill in the specified tree iter with the
        selected row (if a row is selected), and return
        <literal>FALSE</literal> otherwise. It is used like this:</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
  ...

  GtkTreeSelection *selection;
  GtkTreeModel     *model;
  GtkTreeIter       iter;

  /* This will only work in single or browse selection mode! */

  selection = gtk_tree_view_get_selection(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view));
  if (gtk_tree_selection_get_selected(selection, &amp;model, &amp;iter))
  {
    gchar *name;

    gtk_tree_model_get (model, &amp;iter, COL_NAME, &amp;name, -1);

    g_print ("selected row is: %s\n", name);

    g_free(name);
  }
  else
  {
    g_print ("no row selected.\n");
  }

  ...
</programlisting>

        <para>One thing you need to be aware of is that you need to take care
        when removing rows from the model in a
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_selected_foreach</literal> callback, or
        when looping through the list that
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_get_selected_rows</literal> returns
        (because it contains paths, and when you remove rows in the middle,
        then the old paths will point to either a non-existing row, or to
        another row than the one selected). You have two ways around this
        problem: one way is to use the solution to removing multiple rows that
        has been <link linkend="sec-treemodel-remove-row">described
        above</link>, ie. to get tree row references for all selected rows and
        then remove the rows one by one; the other solution is to sort the
        list of selected tree paths so that the last rows come first in the
        list, so that you remove rows from the end of the list or tree. You
        cannot remove rows from within a foreach callback in any case, that is
        simply not allowed.</para>

        <para>Here is an example of how to use
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_selected_foreach</literal>:</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
  ...

  gboolean
  view_selected_foreach_func (GtkTreeModel  *model,
                              GtkTreePath   *path,
                              GtkTreeIter   *iter,
                              gpointer       userdata)
  {
    gchar *name;

    gtk_tree_model_get (model, iter, COL_NAME, &amp;name, -1);

    g_print ("%s is selected\n", name);
  }


  void
  do_something_with_all_selected_rows (GtkWidget *treeview)
  {
    GtkTreeSelection  *selection = gtk_tree_view_get_selection(GTK_TREE_VIEW(treeview));

    gtk_tree_selection_selected_foreach(selection, view_selected_foreach_func, NULL);
  }


  void
  create_view (void)
  {
    GtkWidget         *view;
    GtkTreeSelection  *selection;

    ...

    view = gtk_tree_view_new();

    ...

    selection = gtk_tree_view_get_selection(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view));

    gtk_tree_selection_set_mode(selection, GTK_SELECTION_MULTIPLE);
    ...
  }

  ...
</programlisting>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-selections-function">
        <title>Using Selection Functions</title>

        <para>You can set up a custom selection function with <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSelection.html#gtk-tree-selection-set-select-function">
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_set_select_function</literal></ulink>.
        This function will then be called every time a row is going to be
        selected or unselected (meaning: it will be called before the
        selection status of that row is changed). Selection functions are
        commonly used for the following things:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>... to keep track of the currently selected items (then you
            maintain a list of selected items yourself). In this case, note
            again that your selection function is called
            <emphasis>before</emphasis> the row's selection status is changed.
            In other words: if the row is <emphasis>going to be</emphasis>
            selected, then the boolean path_currently_selected variable that
            is passed to the selection function is still
            <literal>FALSE</literal>. Also note that the selection function
            might not always be called when a row is removed, so you either
            have to unselect a row before you remove it to make sure your
            selection function is called and removes the row from your list,
            or check the validity of a row when you process the selection list
            you keep. You should not store tree paths in your self-maintained
            list of of selected rows, because whenever rows are added or
            removed or the model is resorted the paths might point to other
            rows. Use tree row references or other unique means of identifying
            a row instead.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>... to tell Gtk+ whether it is allowed to select or unselect
            that specific row (you should make sure though that it is
            otherwise obvious to a user whether a row can be selected or not,
            otherwise the user will be confused if she just cannot select or
            unselect a row). This is done by returning TRUE or FALSE in the
            selection function.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>... to take additional action whenever a row is selected or
            unselected.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>Yet another simple example:</para>

        <programlisting role="C">

  ...

  gboolean
  view_selection_func (GtkTreeSelection *selection,
                       GtkTreeModel     *model,
                       GtkTreePath      *path,
                       gboolean          path_currently_selected,
                       gpointer          userdata)
  {
    GtkTreeIter iter;

    if (gtk_tree_model_get_iter(model, &amp;iter, path))
    {
      gchar *name;

      gtk_tree_model_get(model, &amp;iter, COL_NAME, &amp;name, -1);

      if (!path_currently_selected)
      {
        g_print ("%s is going to be selected.\n", name);
      }
      else
      {
        g_print ("%s is going to be unselected.\n", name);
      }

      g_free(name);
    }

    return TRUE; /* allow selection state to change */
  }


  void
  create_view (void)
  {
    GtkWidget         *view;
    GtkTreeSelection  *selection;

    ...

    view = gtk_tree_view_new();

    ...

    selection = gtk_tree_view_get_selection(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view));

    gtk_tree_selection_set_select_function(selection, view_selection_func, NULL, NULL);
    ...
  }

  ...

</programlisting>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-selections-check-row">
        <title>Checking Whether a Row is Selected</title>

        <para>You can check whether a given row is selected or not using the
        functions <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSelection.html#gtk-tree-selection-iter-is-selected">
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_iter_is_selected</literal></ulink>. or
        <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSelection.html#gtk-tree-selection-path-is-selected">
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_path_is_selected</literal></ulink>. If you
        want to know all rows that are <emphasis>not</emphasis> selected, for
        example, you could just traverse the whole list or tree, and use the
        above functions to check for each row whether it is selected or
        not.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-selections-selecting-rows">
        <title>Selecting and Unselecting Rows</title>

        <para>You can select or unselect rows manually with <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSelection.html#gtk-tree-selection-select-iter">
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_select_iter</literal></ulink>, <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSelection.html#gtk-tree-selection-select-path">
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_select_path</literal></ulink>, <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSelection.html#gtk-tree-selection-unselect-iter">
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_unselect_iter</literal></ulink>, <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSelection.html#gtk-tree-selection-unselect-path">
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_unselect_path</literal></ulink>, <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSelection.html#gtk-tree-selection-select-all">
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_select_all</literal></ulink>, and <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSelection.html#gtk-tree-selection-unselect-all">
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_unselect_all</literal></ulink> should you
        ever need to do that.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-selections-row-count">
        <title>Getting the Number of Selected Rows</title>

        <para>Sometimes you want to know the number of rows that are currently
        selected (for example to set context menu entries active or inactive
        before you pop up a context menu). If you are using selection mode
        <literal>GTK_SELECTION_SINGLE</literal> or
        <literal>GTK_SELECTION_BROWSE</literal>, this is trivial to check with
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_get_selected</literal>, which will return
        either <literal>TRUE</literal> or <literal>FALSE</literal> (meaning
        one selected row or no selected row).</para>

        <para>If you are using <literal>GTK_SELECTION_MULTIPLE</literal> or
        want a more general approach that works for all selection modes,
        <literal>gtk_tree_selection_count_selected_rows</literal> will return
        the information you are looking for. The only caveat with this
        function is that it only exists in Gtk+-2.2 and newer, so you will
        have to reimplement it if you want users with old installations that
        still use Gtk+-2.0 to be able to use your program as well. Here is a
        way to reimplement this function:</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
  static void
  count_foreach_helper (GtkTreeModel *model,
                        GtkTreePath  *path,
                        GtkTreeIter  *iter,
                        gpointer      userdata)
  {
    gint *p_count = (gint*) userdata;

    g_assert (p_count != NULL);

    *p_count = *p_count + 1;
  }

  gint
  my_tree_selection_count_selected_rows (GtkTreeSelection *selection)
  {
    gint count = 0;

    gtk_tree_selection_selected_foreach(selection, count_foreach_helper, &amp;count);

    return count;
  }
</programlisting>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-selections-double-click">
      <title>Double-Clicks on a Row</title>

      <para>Catching double-clicks on a row is quite easy and is done by
      connecting to a tree view's <literal>"row-activated"</literal> signal,
      like this:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">

  void
  view_onRowActivated (GtkTreeView        *treeview,
                       GtkTreePath        *path,
                       GtkTreeViewColumn  *col,
                       gpointer            userdata)
  {
    GtkTreeModel *model;
    GtkTreeIter   iter;

    g_print ("A row has been double-clicked!\n");

    model = gtk_tree_view_get_model(treeview);

    if (gtk_tree_model_get_iter(model, &amp;iter, path))
    {
       gchar *name;

       gtk_tree_model_get(model, &amp;iter, COLUMN_NAME, &amp;name, -1);

       g_print ("Double-clicked row contains name %s\n", name);

       g_free(name);
    }
  }

  void
  create_view (void)
  {
    GtkWidget *view;

    view = gtk_tree_view_new();

    ...

    g_signal_connect(view, "row-activated", (GCallback) view_onRowActivated, NULL);

    ...
  }


</programlisting>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-selections-context-menus">
      <title>Context Menus on Right Click</title>

      <para>Context menus are context-dependent menus that pop up when a user
      right-clicks on a list or tree and usually let the user do something
      with the selected items or manipulate the list or tree in other
      ways.</para>

      <para>Right-clicks on a tree view are caught just like mouse button
      clicks are caught with any other widgets, namely by connecting to the
      tree view's "button_press_event" signal handler (which is a GtkWidget
      signal, and as GtkTreeView is derived from GtkWidget it has this signal
      as well). Additionally, you should also connect to the "popup-menu"
      signal, so users can access your context menu without a mouse. The
      "popup-menu" signal is emitted when the user presses Shift-F10. Also,
      you should make sure that all functions provided in your context menu
      can also be accessed by other means such as the application's main menu.
      See the <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gup/hig/">GNOME
      Human Interface Guidelines (HIG)</ulink> for more details. Straight from
      the a-snippet-of-code-says-more-than-a-thousand-words-department, some
      code to look at:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">

  void
  view_popup_menu_onDoSomething (GtkWidget *menuitem, gpointer userdata)
  {
    /* we passed the view as userdata when we connected the signal */
    GtkTreeView *treeview = GTK_TREE_VIEW(userdata);

    g_print ("Do something!\n");
  }


  void
  view_popup_menu (GtkWidget *treeview, GdkEventButton *event, gpointer userdata)
  {
    GtkWidget *menu, *menuitem;

    menu = gtk_menu_new();

    menuitem = gtk_menu_item_new_with_label("Do something");

    g_signal_connect(menuitem, "activate",
                     (GCallback) view_popup_menu_onDoSomething, treeview);

    gtk_menu_shell_append(GTK_MENU_SHELL(menu), menuitem);

    gtk_widget_show_all(menu);

    /* Note: event can be NULL here when called from view_onPopupMenu;
     *  gdk_event_get_time() accepts a NULL argument */
    gtk_menu_popup(GTK_MENU(menu), NULL, NULL, NULL, NULL,
                   (event != NULL) ? event-&gt;button : 0,
                   gdk_event_get_time((GdkEvent*)event));
  }


  gboolean
  view_onButtonPressed (GtkWidget *treeview, GdkEventButton *event, gpointer userdata)
  {
    /* single click with the right mouse button? */
    if (event-&gt;type == GDK_BUTTON_PRESS  &amp;&amp;  event-&gt;button == 3)
    {
      g_print ("Single right click on the tree view.\n");

      /* optional: select row if no row is selected or only
       *  one other row is selected (will only do something
       *  if you set a tree selection mode as described later
       *  in the tutorial) */
      if (1)
      {
        GtkTreeSelection *selection;

        selection = gtk_tree_view_get_selection(GTK_TREE_VIEW(treeview));

        /* Note: gtk_tree_selection_count_selected_rows() does not
         *   exist in gtk+-2.0, only in gtk+ &gt;= v2.2 ! */
        if (gtk_tree_selection_count_selected_rows(selection)  &lt;= 1)
        {
           GtkTreePath *path;

           /* Get tree path for row that was clicked */
           if (gtk_tree_view_get_path_at_pos(GTK_TREE_VIEW(treeview),
                                             (gint) event-&gt;x, 
                                             (gint) event-&gt;y,
                                             &amp;path, NULL, NULL, NULL))
           {
             gtk_tree_selection_unselect_all(selection);
             gtk_tree_selection_select_path(selection, path);
             gtk_tree_path_free(path);
           }
        }
      } /* end of optional bit */

      view_popup_menu(treeview, event, userdata);

      return TRUE; /* we handled this */
    }

    return FALSE; /* we did not handle this */
  }


  gboolean
  view_onPopupMenu (GtkWidget *treeview, gpointer userdata)
  {
    view_popup_menu(treeview, NULL, userdata);

    return TRUE; /* we handled this */
  }


  void
  create_view (void)
  {
    GtkWidget *view;

    view = gtk_tree_view_new();

    ...

    g_signal_connect(view, "button-press-event", (GCallback) view_onButtonPressed, NULL);
    g_signal_connect(view, "popup-menu", (GCallback) view_onPopupMenu, NULL);

    ...
  }

</programlisting>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-sorting">
    <title>Sorting</title>

    <para>Lists and trees are meant to be sorted. This is done using the
    <ulink
    url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSortable.html">
    <literal>GtkTreeSortable</literal></ulink> interface that can be
    implemented by tree models. 'Interface' means that you can just cast a
    <literal>GtkTreeModel</literal> into a <literal>GtkTreeSortable</literal>
    with <literal>GTK_TREE_SORTABLE(model)</literal> and use the documented
    tree sortable functions on it, just like we did before when we cast a list
    store to a tree model and used the <literal>gtk_tree_model_foo</literal>
    family of functions. Both <literal>GtkListStore</literal> and
    <literal>GtkTreeStore</literal> implement the tree sortable
    interface.</para>

    <para>The most straight forward way to sort a list store or tree store is
    to directly use the tree sortable interface on them. This will sort the
    store in place, meaning that rows will actually be reordered in the store
    if required. This has the advantage that the position of a row in the tree
    view will always be the same as the position of a row in the model, in
    other words: a tree path refering to a row in the view will always refer
    to the same row in the model, so you can get a row's iter easily with
    <literal>gtk_tree_model_get_iter</literal> using a tree path supplied by
    the tree view. This is not only convenient, but also sufficient for most
    scenarios.</para>

    <para>However, there are cases when sorting a model in place is not
    desirable, for example when several tree views display the same model with
    different sortings, or when the unsorted state of the model has some
    special meaning and needs to be restored at some point. This is where
    <ulink
    url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModelSort.html">
    <literal>GtkTreeModelSort</literal></ulink> comes in, which is a special
    model that maps the unsorted rows of a child model (e.g. a list store or
    tree store) into a sorted state without changing the child model.</para>

    <sect1 id="sec-sorting-tree-sortable">
      <title>GtkTreeSortable</title>

      <para>The tree sortable interface is fairly simple and should be easy to
      use. Basically you define a 'sort column ID' integer for every criterion
      you might want to sort by and tell the tree sortable which function
      should be called to compare two rows (represented by two tree iters) for
      every sort ID with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSortable.html#gtk-tree-sortable-set-sort-func">
      <literal>gtk_tree_sortable_set_sort_func</literal></ulink>. Then you
      sort the model by setting the sort column ID and sort order with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSortable.html#gtk-tree-sortable-set-column-id">
      <literal>gtk_tree_sortable_set_sort_column_id</literal></ulink>, and the
      model will be re-sorted using the compare function you have set up. Your
      sort column IDs can correspond to your model columns, but they do not
      have to (you might want to sort according to a criterion that is not
      directly represented by the data in one single model column, for
      example). Some code to illustrate this:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">

  enum
  {
    COL_NAME = 0,
    COL_YEAR_BORN
  };


  enum
  {
    SORTID_NAME = 0,
    SORTID_YEAR
  };


  GtkTreeModel  *liststore = NULL;


  void
  toolbar_onSortByYear (void)
  {
    GtkTreeSortable *sortable;
    GtkSortType      order;
    gint             sortid;

    sortable = GTK_TREE_SORTABLE(liststore);

    /* If we are already sorting by year, reverse sort order,
     *  otherwise set it to year in ascending order */

    if (gtk_tree_sortable_get_sort_column_id(sortable, &amp;sortid, &amp;order) == TRUE
          &amp;&amp;  sortid == SORTID_YEAR)
    {
      GtkSortType neworder;

      neworder = (order == GTK_SORT_ASCENDING) ? GTK_SORT_DESCENDING : GTK_SORT_ASCENDING;

      gtk_tree_sortable_set_sort_column_id(sortable, SORTID_YEAR, neworder);
    }
    else
    {
      gtk_tree_sortable_set_sort_column_id(sortable, SORTID_YEAR, GTK_SORT_ASCENDING);
    }
  }


  /* This is not pretty. Of course you can also use a
   *  separate compare function for each sort ID value */

  gint
  sort_iter_compare_func (GtkTreeModel *model,
                          GtkTreeIter  *a,
                          GtkTreeIter  *b,
                          gpointer      userdata)
  {
    gint sortcol = GPOINTER_TO_INT(userdata);
    gint ret = 0;

    switch (sortcol)
    {
      case SORTID_NAME:
      {
        gchar *name1, *name2;

        gtk_tree_model_get(model, a, COL_NAME, &amp;name1, -1);
        gtk_tree_model_get(model, b, COL_NAME, &amp;name2, -1);

        if (name1 == NULL || name2 == NULL)
        {
          if (name1 == NULL &amp;&amp; name2 == NULL)
            break; /* both equal =&gt; ret = 0 */

          ret = (name1 == NULL) ? -1 : 1;
        }
        else
        {
          ret = g_utf8_collate(name1,name2);
        }

        g_free(name1);
        g_free(name2);
      }
      break;

      case SORTID_YEAR:
      {
        guint year1, year2;

        gtk_tree_model_get(model, a, COL_YEAR_BORN, &amp;year1, -1);
        gtk_tree_model_get(model, b, COL_YEAR_BORN, &amp;year2, -1);

        if (year1 != year2)
        {
          ret = (year1 &gt; year2) ? 1 : -1;
        }
        /* else both equal =&gt; ret = 0 */
      }
      break;

      default:
        g_return_val_if_reached(0);
    }

    return ret;
  }


  void
  create_list_and_view (void)
  {
    GtkTreeSortable *sortable;

    ...

    liststore = gtk_list_store_new(2, G_TYPE_STRING, G_TYPE_UINT);

    sortable = GTK_TREE_SORTABLE(liststore);

    gtk_tree_sortable_set_sort_func(sortable, SORTID_NAME, sort_iter_compare_func,
                                    GINT_TO_POINTER(SORTID_NAME), NULL);

    gtk_tree_sortable_set_sort_func(sortable, SORTID_YEAR, sort_iter_compare_func,
                                    GINT_TO_POINTER(SORTID_YEAR), NULL);

    /* set initial sort order */
    gtk_tree_sortable_set_sort_column_id(sortable, SORTID_NAME, GTK_SORT_ASCENDING);

    ...

    view = gtk_tree_view_new_with_model(liststore);

    ...

  }

</programlisting>

      <para>Usually things are a bit easier if you make use of the tree view
      column headers for sorting, in which case you only need to assign sort
      column IDs and your compare functions, but do not need to set the
      current sort column ID or order yourself (see <link
      linkend="sec-sorting-view-cols">below</link>).</para>

      <para>Your tree iter compare function should return a negative value if
      the row specified by iter a comes before the row specified by iter b,
      and a positive value if row b comes before row a. It should return 0 if
      both rows are equal according to your sorting criterion (you might want
      to use a second sort criterion though to avoid 'jumping' of equal rows
      when the store gets resorted). Your tree iter compare function should
      not take the sort order into account, but assume an ascending sort order
      (otherwise bad things will happen).</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-sorting-model-sort">
      <title>GtkTreeModelSort</title>

      <para><ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModelSort.html">
      <literal>GtkTreeModelSort</literal></ulink> is a wrapper tree model. It
      takes another tree model such as a list store or a tree store as child
      model, and presents the child model to the 'outside' (ie. a tree view or
      whoever else is accessing it via the tree model interface) in a sorted
      state. It does that without changing the order of the rows in the child
      model. This is useful if you want to display the same model in different
      tree views with different sorting criteria for each tree view, for
      example, or if you need to restore the original unsorted state of your
      store again at some point.</para>

      <para><literal>GtkTreeModelSort</literal> implements the
      <literal>GtkTreeSortable</literal> interface, so you can treat it just
      as if it was your data store for sorting purposes. Here is the basic
      setup with a tree view:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">

  ...

  void
  create_list_and_view (void)
  {
    ...

    liststore = gtk_list_store_new(2, G_TYPE_STRING, G_TYPE_UINT);

    sortmodel = gtk_tree_model_sort_new_with_model(liststore);

    gtk_tree_sortable_set_sort_func(GTK_TREE_SORTABLE(sortmodel), SORTID_NAME,
                                    sort_func, GINT_TO_POINTER(SORTID_NAME), NULL);

    gtk_tree_sortable_set_sort_func(GTK_TREE_SORTABLE(sortmodel), SORTID_YEAR,
                                    sort_func, GINT_TO_POINTER(SORTID_YEAR), NULL);

    /* set initial sort order */
    gtk_tree_sortable_set_sort_column_id(GTK_TREE_SORTABLE(sortmodel),
                                         SORTID_NAME, GTK_SORT_ASCENDING);

    ...

    view = gtk_tree_view_new_with_model(sortmodel);

    ...

  }

  ...

</programlisting>

      <para>However, when using the sort tree model, you need to be careful
      when you use iters and paths with the model. This is because a path
      pointing to a row in the view (and the sort tree model here) does
      probably not point to the same row in the child model which is your
      original list store or tree store, because the row order in the child
      model is probably different from the sorted order. Similarly, an iter
      that is valid for the sort tree model is not valid for the child model,
      and vice versa. You can convert paths and iters from and to the child
      model using
      <literal>gtk_tree_model_sort_convert_child_path_to_path</literal>,
      <literal>gtk_tree_model_sort_convert_child_iter_to_iter</literal>,
      <literal>gtk_tree_model_sort_convert_path_to_child_path</literal>, and
      <literal>gtk_tree_model_sort_convert_iter_to_child_iter</literal>. You
      are unlikely to need these functions frequently though, as you can still
      directly use <literal>gtk_tree_model_get</literal> on the sort tree
      model with a path supplied by the tree view.</para>

      <para>For the tree view, the sort tree model is the 'real' model - it
      knows nothing about the sort tree model's child model at all, which
      means that any path or iter that you get passed from the tree view in a
      callback or otherwise will refer to the sort tree model, and that you
      need to pass a path or iter refering to the sort tree model as well if
      you call tree view functions.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-sorting-view-cols">
      <title>Sorting and Tree View Column Headers</title>

      <para>Unless you have hidden your tree view column headers or use custom
      tree view column header widgets, each tree view column's header can be
      made clickable. Clicking on a tree view column's header will then sort
      the list according to the data in that column. You need to do two things
      to make this happen: firstly, you need to tell your model which sort
      function to use for which sort column ID with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSortable.html#gtk-tree-sortable-set-sort-func">
      <literal>gtk_tree_sortable_set_sort_func</literal></ulink>. Once you
      have done this, you tell each tree view column which sort column ID
      should be active if this column's header is clicked. This is done with
      <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeViewColumn.html#gtk-tree-view-column-set-sort-column-id">
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_column_set_sort_column_id</literal></ulink>.</para>

      <para>And that is really all you need to do to get your list or tree
      sorted. The tree view columns will automatically set the active sort
      column ID and sort order for you if you click on a column header.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-sorting-string-nocase">
      <title>Case-insensitive String Comparing</title>

      <para>As described above in the <link
      linkend="sec-treeview-col-utf8-pango">"GtkCellRendererText, UTF8, and
      pango markup" section</link>, all strings that are to be displayed in
      the tree view need to be encoded in UTF8 encoding. All ASCII strings are
      valid UTF8, but as soon as non-ASCII characters are used, things get a
      bit tricky and the character encoding matters.</para>

      <para>Comparing two ASCII strings ignoring the case is trivial and can
      be done using <literal>g_ascii_strcasecmp</literal>, for example.
      <literal>strcasecmp</literal> will usually do the same, only that it is
      also locale-aware to some extent. The only problem is that a lot of
      users use locale character encodings that are not UTF8, so
      <literal>strcasecmp</literal> does not take us very far.</para>

      <para><literal>g_utf8_collate</literal> will compare two strings in UTF8
      encoding, but it does not ignore the case. In order to achieve at least
      half-way correct linguistic case-insensitive sorting, we need to take a
      two-step approach. For example, we could use
      <literal>g_utf8_casefold</literal> to convert the strings to compare
      into a form that is independent of case, and then use
      <literal>g_utf8_collate</literal> to compare those two strings (note
      that the strings returned by <literal>g_utf8_casefold</literal> will not
      resemble the original string in any recognisable way; they will work
      fine for comparisons though). Alternatively, one could use
      <literal>g_utf8_strdown</literal> on both strings and then compare the
      results again with <literal>g_utf8_collate</literal>.</para>

      <para>Obviously, all this is not going to be very fast, and adds up if
      you have a lot of rows. To speed things up, you can create a 'collation
      key' with <literal>g_utf8_collate_key</literal> and store that in your
      model as well. A collation key is just a string that does not mean
      anything to us, but can be used with <literal>strcmp</literal> for
      string comparison purposes (which is a lot faster than
      <literal>g_utf8_collate</literal>).</para>

      <para>It should be noted that the way <literal>g_utf8_collate</literal>
      sorts is dependent on the current locale. Make sure you are not working
      in the 'C' locale (=default, none specified) before you are wondering
      about weird sorting orders. Check with 'echo $LANG' on a command line
      what you current locale is set to.</para>

      <para>Check out the <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/glib/glib-Unicode-Manipulation.html#g-utf8-casefold">
      "Unicode Manipulation" section</ulink> in the GLib API Reference for
      more details.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-editable-cells">
    <title>Editable Cells</title>

    <sect1 id="sec-editable-cells-text">
      <title>Editable Text Cells</title>

      <para>With <literal>GtkCellRendererText</literal> you can not only
      display text, but you can also allow the user to edit a single cell's
      text right in the tree view by double-clicking on a cell.</para>

      <para>To make this work you need to tell the cell renderer that a cell
      is editable, which you can do by setting the
      <literal>"editable"</literal> property of the text cell renderer in
      question to <literal>TRUE</literal>. You can either do this on a per-row
      basis (which allows you to set each single cell either editable or not)
      by connecting the <literal>"editable"</literal> property to a boolean
      type column in your tree model using attributes; or you can just do a
      ...</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  g_object_set(renderer, "editable", TRUE, NULL);
</programlisting>

      <para>... when you create the renderer, which sets all rows in that
      particular renderer column to be editable.</para>

      <para>Now that our cells are editable, we also want to be notified when
      a cell has been edited. This can be achieved by connecting to the cell
      renderer's <literal>"edited"</literal> signal:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  g_signal_connect(renderer, "edited", (GCallback) cell_edited_callback, NULL);
</programlisting>

      <para>This callback is then called whenever a cell has been edited.
      Instead of <literal>NULL</literal> we could have passed a pointer to the
      model as user data for convenience, as we probably want to store the new
      value in the model.</para>

      <para>The callback for the <literal>"edited"</literal> signal looks like
      this (the API reference is a bit lacking in this particular
      case):</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
void        cell_edited_callback (GtkCellRendererText *cell,
                                  gchar               *path_string,
                                  gchar               *new_text,
                                  gpointer             user_data);
</programlisting>

      <para>The tree path is passed to the <literal>"edited"</literal> signal
      callback in string form. You can convert this into a
      <literal>GtkTreePath</literal> with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-path-new-from-string">
      <literal>gtk_tree_path_new_from_string</literal></ulink>, or convert it
      into an iter with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get-iter-from-string">
      <literal>gtk_tree_model_get_iter_from_string</literal></ulink>.</para>

      <para>Note that the cell renderer will not change the data for you in
      the store. After a cell has been edited, you will only receive an
      <literal>"edited"</literal> signal. If you do not change the data in the
      store, the old text will be rendered again as if nothing had
      happened.</para>

      <para>If you have multiple (renderer) columns with editable cells, it is
      not necessary to have a different callback for each renderer, you can
      use the same callback for all renderers, and attach some data to each
      renderer, which you can later retrieve again in the callback to know
      which renderer/column has been edited. This is done like this, for
      example:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();
  ...
  g_object_set_data(G_OBJECT(renderer), "my_column_num", GUINT_TO_POINTER(COLUMN_NAME));

  ...

  renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();
  ...
  g_object_set_data(G_OBJECT(renderer), "my_column_num", GUINT_TO_POINTER(COLUMN_YEAR_OF_BIRTH));

  ...
</programlisting>

      <para>where COLUMN_NAME and COLUMN_YEAR_OF_BIRTH are enum values. In
      your callback you can then get the column number with</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  guint column_number = GPOINTER_TO_UINT(g_object_get_data(G_OBJECT(renderer), "my_column_num"));
</programlisting>

      <para>You can use this mechanism to attach all kinds of custom data to
      any object or widget, with a string identifier to your liking.</para>

      <para>A good example for editable cells is in gtk-demo, which is part of
      the Gtk+ source code tree (in gtk+-2.x.y/demos/gtk-demo).</para>

      <sect2 id="sec-editable-cells-text-set">
        <title>Setting the cursor to a specific cell</title>

        <para>You can move the cursor to a specific cell in a tree view with
        <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeView.html#gtk-tree-view-set-cursor">
        <literal>gtk_tree_view_set_cursor</literal></ulink> (or <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeView.html#gtk-tree-view-set-cursor-on-cell">
        <literal>gtk_tree_view_set_cursor_on_cell</literal></ulink> if you
        have multiple editable cell renderers packed into one tree view
        column), and start editing the cell if you want to. Similarly, you can
        get the current row and focus column with <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeView.html#gtk-tree-view-get-cursor">
        <literal>gtk_tree_view_get_cursor</literal></ulink>. Use <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkWidget.html#gtk-widget-grab-focus">
        <literal>gtk_widget_grab_focus(treeview)</literal></ulink> will make
        sure that the tree view has the keyboard focus.</para>

        <para>As the API reference points out, the tree view needs to be
        realised for cell editing to happen. In other words: If you want to
        start editing a specific cell right at program startup, you need to
        set up an idle timeout with <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/glib/glib-The-Main-Event-Loop.html#g-idle-add">
        <literal>g_idle_add</literal></ulink> that does this for you as soon
        as the window and everything else has been realised (return
        <literal>FALSE</literal> in the timeout to make it run only once).
        Alternatively you could connect to the <literal>"realize"</literal>
        signal of the treeview with <literal>g_signal_connect_after</literal>
        to achieve the same thing.</para>

        <para>Connect to the tree view's <literal>"cursor-changed"</literal>
        and/or <literal>"move-cursor"</literal> signals to keep track of the
        current position of the cursor.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-editable-cells-toggle">
      <title>Editable Toggle and Radio Button Cells</title>

      <para>Just like you can set a <literal>GtkCellRendererText</literal>
      editable, you can specify whether a
      <literal>GtkCellRendererToggle</literal> should change its state when
      clicked by setting the <literal>"activatable"</literal> property -
      either when you create the renderer (in which case all cells in that
      column will be clickable) or by connecting the renderer property to a
      model column of boolean type via attributes.</para>

      <para>Connect to the <literal>"toggled"</literal> signal of the toggle
      cell renderer to be notified when the user clicks on a toggle button (or
      radio button). The user click will not change the value in the store, or
      the appearance of the value rendered. The toggle button will only change
      state when you update the value in the store. Until then it will be in
      an "inconsistent" state, which is also why you should read the current
      value of that cell from the model, and not from the cell
      renderer.</para>

      <para>The callback for the <literal>"toggled"</literal> signal looks
      like this (the API reference is a bit lacking in this particular
      case):</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
void        cell_toggled_callback (GtkCellRendererToggle *cell,
                                   gchar                 *path_string,
                                   gpointer               user_data);
</programlisting>

      <para>Just like with the <literal>"edited"</literal> signal of the text
      cell renderer, the tree path is passed to the
      <literal>"toggled"</literal> signal callback in string form. You can
      convert this into a <literal>GtkTreePath</literal> with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-path-new-from-string">
      <literal>gtk_tree_path_new_from_string</literal></ulink>, or convert it
      into an iter with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get-iter-from-string">
      <literal>gtk_tree_model_get_iter_from_string</literal></ulink>.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-editable-cells-spin">
      <title>Editable Spin Button Cells</title>

      <para>Even though <literal>GtkSpinButton</literal> implements the
      <literal>GtkCellEditable</literal> interface (as does
      <literal>GtkEntry</literal>), there is no easy way to get a cell
      renderer that uses a spin button instead of a normal entry when in
      editing mode.</para>

      <para>To get this functionality, you need to either write a new cell
      renderer that works very similar to
      <literal>GtkCellRendererText</literal>, or you need to write a new cell
      renderer class that derives from the text cell renderer and changes the
      behaviour in editing mode.</para>

      <para>The cleanest solution would probably be to write a
      'CellRendererNumeric' that does everything that the text cell renderer
      does, only that it has a float type property instead of the
      <literal>"text"</literal> property, and an additional digits property.
      However, no one seems to have done this yet, so you need to either write
      one, or find another solution to get spin buttons in editing
      mode.</para>

      <para>Among this tutorial's code examples there is a hackish
      CellRendererSpin implementation which is based on
      <literal>GtkCellRendererText</literal> and shows spin buttons in editing
      mode. The implementation is not very refined though, so you need to make
      sure it works in your particular context, and modify it as
      needed.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-misc">
    <title>Miscellaneous</title>

    <para>This section deals with issues and questions that did not seem to
    fit in anywhere else. If you can think of something else that should be
    dealt with here, do not hesitate to send a mail to <email>tim at
    centricular dot net</email>.</para>

    <sect1 id="sec-misc-column-index">
      <title>Getting the Column Number from a Tree View Column Widget</title>

      <para>Signal callbacks often only get passed a pointer to a
      <literal>GtkTreeViewColumn</literal> when the application programmer
      really just wants to know which column <emphasis>number</emphasis> was
      affected. There are two ways to find out the position of a column within
      the tree view. One way is to write a small helper function that looks up
      the column number from a given tree view column object, like this for
      example: <footnote>
          <para>This function has been inspired by <ulink
          url="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gtk-list/2003-July/msg00060.html">
          this</ulink> mailing list message (thanks to Ken Rastatter for the
          link and the topic suggestion).</para>
        </footnote>.</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  /* Returns column number or -1 if not found or on error */

  gint
  get_col_number_from_tree_view_column (GtkTreeViewColumn *col)
  {
    GList *cols;
    gint   num;

    g_return_val_if_fail ( col != NULL, -1 );
    g_return_val_if_fail ( col-&gt;tree_view != NULL, -1 );

    cols = gtk_tree_view_get_columns(GTK_TREE_VIEW(col-&gt;tree_view));

    num = g_list_index(cols, (gpointer) col);

    g_list_free(cols);

    return num;
  }
</programlisting>

      <para>Alternatively, it is possible to use
      <literal>g_object_set_data</literal> and
      <literal>g_object_get_data</literal> on the tree view column in order to
      identify which column it is. This also has the advantage that you can
      still keep track of your columns even if the columns get re-ordered
      within the tree view (a feature which is usually disabled though). Use
      like this:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  ...

  enum
  {
    COL_FIRSTNAME,
    COL_SURNAME,
  };

  ...

  void
  some_callback (GtkWidget *treeview, ..., GtkTreeViewColumn *col, ...)
  {
    guint colnum = GPOINTER_TO_UINT(g_object_get_data(G_OBJECT(col), "columnnum"));

    ...
  }

  void
  create_view(void)
  {
    ...
    col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();
    g_object_set_data(G_OBJECT(col), "columnnum", GUINT_TO_POINTER(COL_FIRSTNAME));
    ...
    col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();
    g_object_set_data(G_OBJECT(col), "columnnum", GUINT_TO_POINTER(COL_SURNAME));
    ...
  }
</programlisting>

      <para><literal>"columnnum"</literal> is a random string in the above
      example - you can use whatever string you want instead, or store
      multiple bits of data (with different string identifiers of course). Of
      course you can also combine both approaches, as they do slightly
      different things (the first tracks the 'physical' position of a column
      within the tree view, the second tracks the 'meaning' of a column to
      you, independent of its position within the view).</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-misc-expander-visibility">
      <title>Column Expander Visibility</title>

      <sect2 id="sec-misc-expander-visibility-hide">
        <title>Hiding the Column Expander</title>

        <para>Is it possible to hide the column expander completely? Yes and
        no. What follows, is probably a dirty hack at best and there is no
        guarantee that it will work with upcoming Gtk+ versions or even with
        all past versions (although the latter is easy enough to test of
        course).</para>

        <para>What you can do to hide the column expander is to create an
        empty tree view column (containing empty strings, for example) and
        make this the first column in the tree view. Then you can hide that
        column with <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeViewColumn.html#gtk-tree-view-column-set-visible">
        <literal>gtk_tree_view_column_set_visible</literal></ulink>. You will
        notice that the expander column will now automatically move to the
        formerly second, now first, visible column in the tree view. However,
        if you call <ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeView.html#gtk-tree-view-set-expander-column">
        <literal>gtk_tree_view_set_expander_column</literal></ulink> right
        after the call to <literal>_set_visible</literal>, then the expander
        will move back to the hidden column, and no expander is visible any
        longer.</para>

        <para>This means of course that you will have to take care of
        expanding and collapsing rows yourself and use the appropriate tree
        view functions. While it is at last thinkable that one could implement
        custom expanders using custom cell rendereres or pixbuf cell
        renderers, this is probably a task that will keep you busy for more
        than five minutes. Keep those head ache tablets nearby if you attempt
        it anyway...</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-misc-expander-visibility-force">
        <title>Forcing Column Expander Visibility</title>

        <para>There are situations where an expander should be visible even if
        the row in question does not have any children yet, for instance when
        part of a model should only be loaded on request when a node gets
        expanded (e.g. to show the contents of a directory). This is not
        possible. An expander is only shown if a node has children.</para>

        <para>A work-around for this problem exists however: simply attach an
        empty child row and set the node to collapsed state. Then listen for
        the tree view's <literal>"row-expanded"</literal> signal, and fill the
        contents of the already existing row with the first new row, then
        append new child rows. See <ulink
        url="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gtk-app-devel-list/2003-May/msg00241.html">
        this mailing list thread</ulink> for more details.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-misc-get-renderer-from-click">
      <title>Getting the Cell Renderer a Click Event Happened On</title>

      <para>It seems that in many cases when people want to know the cell
      renderer a click event happened on, they do not really need to know the
      cell renderer, but rather want to modify an individual cell in a
      particular column. For this you do not need to know the cell renderer.
      Use <literal> <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeView.html#gtk-tree-view-get-path-at-pos">
      gtk_tree_view_get_path_at_pos</ulink></literal> to get a tree path from
      the x and y coordinates of the button event that is passed to you in a
      <literal>"button-press-event"</literal> signal callback (if you use the
      <literal>"row-activated"</literal> signal to catch double-clicks you get
      the tree path passed directly into the callback function). Then convert
      that tree path into an iter using <literal><ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get-iter">
      gtk_tree_model_get_iter</ulink></literal> and modify the data in the
      cell you want to modify with <literal>gtk_list_store_set</literal> or
      <literal>gtk_tree_store_set</literal>.</para>

      <para>If you really do need to know the cell renderer where a button
      press event happened, that is a bit more tricky. Here is a suggestion on
      how to approach this issue (the function has not been well-tested and
      might not work correctly if the content rendered by one renderer in
      different columns varies in width; please send suggestions on how to fix
      or improve this function to the author):</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
static gboolean
tree_view_get_cell_from_pos(GtkTreeView *view, guint x, guint y, GtkCellRenderer **cell)
{
	GtkTreeViewColumn *col = NULL;
	GList             *node, *columns, *cells;
	guint              colx = 0;

	g_return_val_if_fail ( view != NULL, FALSE );
	g_return_val_if_fail ( cell != NULL, FALSE );

	/* (1) find column and column x relative to tree view coordinates */

	columns = gtk_tree_view_get_columns(view);

	for (node = columns;  node != NULL &amp;&amp; col == NULL;  node = node-&gt;next)
	{
		GtkTreeViewColumn *checkcol = (GtkTreeViewColumn*) node-&gt;data;

		if (x &gt;= colx  &amp;&amp;  x &lt; (colx + checkcol-&gt;width))
			col = checkcol;
		else
			colx += checkcol-&gt;width;
	}

	g_list_free(columns);

	if (col == NULL)
		return FALSE; /* not found */

	/* (2) find the cell renderer within the column */

	cells = gtk_tree_view_column_get_cell_renderers(col);

	for (node = cells;  node != NULL;  node = node-&gt;next)
	{
		GtkCellRenderer *checkcell = (GtkCellRenderer*) node-&gt;data;
		guint            width = 0, height = 0;

		/* Will this work for all packing modes? doesn't that
		 *  return a random width depending on the last content
		 * rendered? */
		gtk_cell_renderer_get_size(checkcell, GTK_WIDGET(view), NULL, NULL, NULL, &amp;width, NULL);

		if (x &gt;= colx &amp;&amp; x &lt; (colx + width))
		{
			*cell = checkcell;
			g_list_free(cells);
			return TRUE;
		}

		colx += width;
	}

	g_list_free(cells);
	return FALSE; /* not found */
}

static gboolean
onButtonPress (GtkWidget *view, GdkEventButton *bevent, gpointer data)
{
	GtkCellRenderer *renderer = NULL;

	if (tree_view_get_cell_from_pos(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view), bevent-&gt;x, bevent-&gt;y, &amp;renderer))
		g_print ("Renderer found\n");
	else
		g_print ("Renderer not found!\n");
}

</programlisting>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-misc-glade">
      <title>Glade and Tree Views</title>

      <para>A frequently asked question is how you can add columns to a
      <literal>GtkTreeView</literal> in <ulink
      url="http://glade.gnome.org">Glade</ulink>. <footnote>
          <para>Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> use Glade to generate code for
          you. Use Glade to create the interface. It will save the interface
          into a .glade file in XML format. You can then use libglade2 to
          construct your interface (windows etc.) from that .glade file. See
          <ulink
          url="http://lists.ximian.com/archives/public/glade-devel/2003-February/000015.html">
          this mailing list message for a short discussion about why you
          should avoid Glade code generation</ulink>.</para>
        </footnote> The answer is basically that you don't, and that you
      can't. The only thing glade/libglade can do for you is to create the
      <literal>GtkTreeView</literal> for you with nothing in it. You will need
      to look up the tree view widget at the start of your application (after
      the interface has been created of course), and connect your list store
      or tree store to it. Then you will need to add
      <literal>GtkTreeViewColumn</literal>s and cell renderers to display the
      information from the model as you want it to be displayed. You will need
      to do all that from within your application.</para>

      <para>An alternative approach is to derive your own special widget from
      <literal>GtkTreeView</literal> that sets up everything as you want it
      to, and then use the 'custom widget' function in glade. Of course this
      still means that you have to write all the code to fill in the columns
      and cell renderers and to create the model yourself.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-dnd">
    <title>Drag'n'Drop (DnD) **** needs revision ***</title>

    <para>****** NEEDS REVISION</para>

    <para>This section needs revision more than any other section. If you know
    anything about tree view drag'n'drop, you probably know more than the
    author of this text. Please give some feedback in that case.</para>

    <para>If you want to dive into treeview drag'n'drop, you might want to
    check out <ulink
    url="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gtk-devel-list/2001-November/msg00018.html">
    Owen Taylor's mail on that topic</ulink>. It might not be completely
    identical to what has actually been implemented, but it gives a great
    overview, and provides more information than the docs do.</para>

    <para>In addition to the standard Gtk+ Drag and Drop mechanisms that work
    with any widget, there are special Drag and Drop mechanisms just for the
    tree view widget. You usually want to use the tree-view specific
    Drag-and-Drop framework.</para>

    <sect1 id="sec-dnd-selected-item-info">
      <title>Drag'n'Dropping Row-Unrelated Data to and from a Tree View from
      other Windows or Widgets</title>

      <para>Drag'n'Dropping general information from or to a tree view widget
      works just like it works with any other widget and involves the standard
      <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/gtk-Drag-and-Drop.html">
      Gtk+ Drag and Drop</ulink> mechanisms. If you use this, you can receive
      drops to or initiate drags from anywhere in your tree view (including
      empty sections). This is not row- or column-specific and <emphasis>is
      most likely not want you want</emphasis>. Nevertheless, here is a small
      example of a tree view in which you can drag'n'drop URIs from other
      applications (browsers, for example), with the dropped URIs just being
      appended to the list (note that usually you would probably rather want
      to set up your whole window as a target then and not just the tree view
      widget):</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
#include &lt;gtk/gtk.h&gt;

enum
{
  COL_URI = 0,
  NUM_COLS
} ;


void
view_onDragDataReceived(GtkWidget *wgt, GdkDragContext *context, int x, int y,
                        GtkSelectionData *seldata, guint info, guint time,
                        gpointer userdata)
{
  GtkTreeModel *model;
  GtkTreeIter   iter;

  model = GTK_TREE_MODEL(userdata);

  gtk_list_store_append(GTK_LIST_STORE(model), &amp;iter);

  gtk_list_store_set(GTK_LIST_STORE(model), &amp;iter, COL_URI, (gchar*)seldata-&gt;data, -1);
}

static GtkWidget *
create_view_and_model (void)
{
  GtkTreeViewColumn   *col;
  GtkCellRenderer     *renderer;
  GtkListStore        *liststore;
  GtkWidget           *view;

  liststore = gtk_list_store_new(NUM_COLS, G_TYPE_STRING);

  view = gtk_tree_view_new_with_model(GTK_TREE_MODEL(liststore));

  g_object_unref(liststore); /* destroy model with view */

  col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();
  renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();

  gtk_tree_view_column_set_title(col, "URI");
  gtk_tree_view_append_column(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view), col);
  gtk_tree_view_column_pack_start(col, renderer, TRUE);
  gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute(col, renderer, "text", COL_URI);

  gtk_tree_selection_set_mode(gtk_tree_view_get_selection(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view)),
                              GTK_SELECTION_SINGLE);

  /* Make tree view a destination for Drag'n'Drop */
  if (1)
  {
    enum
    {
      TARGET_STRING,
      TARGET_URL
    };

    static GtkTargetEntry targetentries[] =
    {
      { "STRING",        0, TARGET_STRING },
      { "text/plain",    0, TARGET_STRING },
      { "text/uri-list", 0, TARGET_URL },
    };

    gtk_drag_dest_set(view, GTK_DEST_DEFAULT_ALL, targetentries, 3,
                      GDK_ACTION_COPY|GDK_ACTION_MOVE|GDK_ACTION_LINK);

    g_signal_connect(view, "drag_data_received",
                     G_CALLBACK(view_onDragDataReceived), liststore);
  }

  return view;
}

int
main (int argc, char **argv)
{
  GtkWidget *window, *vbox, *view, *label;

  gtk_init(&amp;argc, &amp;argv);

  window = gtk_window_new(GTK_WINDOW_TOPLEVEL);
  g_signal_connect(window, "delete_event", gtk_main_quit, NULL); /* dirty */
  gtk_window_set_default_size(GTK_WINDOW(window), 400, 200);

  vbox = gtk_vbox_new(FALSE, 0);
  gtk_container_add(GTK_CONTAINER(window), vbox);

  label = gtk_label_new("\nDrag and drop links from your browser into the tree view.\n");
  gtk_box_pack_start(GTK_BOX(vbox), label, FALSE, FALSE, 0);

  view = create_view_and_model();
  gtk_box_pack_start(GTK_BOX(vbox), view, TRUE, TRUE, 0);

  gtk_widget_show_all(window);

  gtk_main();

  return 0;
}
</programlisting>

      <para>If you are receiving drops into a tree view, you can connect to
      the view's <literal>"drag-motion"</literal> signal to track the mouse
      pointer while it is in a drag and drop operation over the tree view.
      This is useful for example if you want to expand a collapsed node in a
      tree when the mouse hovers above the node for a certain amount of time
      during a drag'n'drop operation. Here is an example of how to achieve
      this:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
/***************************************************************************
 *
 *   onDragMotion_expand_timeout
 *
 *   Timeout used to make sure that we expand rows only
 *    after hovering about them for a certain amount
 *    of time while doing Drag'n'Drop
 *
 ***************************************************************************/

gboolean
onDragMotion_expand_timeout (GtkTreePath **path)
{
        g_return_val_if_fail (  path != NULL, FALSE );
        g_return_val_if_fail ( *path != NULL, FALSE );

        gtk_tree_view_expand_row(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view), *path, FALSE);

        return FALSE; /* only call once */
}


/***************************************************************************
 *
 *   view_onDragMotion: we don't want to expand unexpanded nodes
 *                      immediately when the mouse pointer passes across
 *                      them during DnD. Instead, we only want to expand
 *                      the node if the pointer has been hovering above the
 *                      node for at least 1.5 seconds or so. To achieve this,
 *                      we use a timeout that is removed whenever the row
 *                      in focus changes.
 *
 ***************************************************************************/

static gboolean
view_onDragMotion (GtkWidget *widget, GdkDragContext *context, gint x,
                   gint y, guint time, gpointer data)
{
  static GtkTreePath  *lastpath;  /* NULL */
  GtkTreePath         *path = NULL;

  if (gtk_tree_view_get_path_at_pos(GTK_TREE_VIEW(widget), x, y, &amp;path, NULL, NULL, NULL))
  {
    if (!lastpath || ((lastpath) &amp;&amp; gtk_tree_path_compare(lastpath, path) != 0))
    {
      (void) g_source_remove_by_user_data(&amp;lastpath);

      if (!gtk_tree_view_row_expanded(GTK_TREE_VIEW(widget), path))
      {
        /* 1500 = 1.5 secs */
        g_timeout_add(1500, (GSourceFunc) onDragMotion_expand_timeout, &amp;lastpath);
      }
    }
  }
  else
  {
    g_source_remove_by_user_data(&amp;lastpath);
  }

  if (lastpath)
    gtk_tree_path_free(lastpath);

  lastpath = path;

  return TRUE;
}
</programlisting>

      <para>Connect to the view's <literal>"drag-drop"</literal> signal to be
      called when the drop happens. You can translate the coordinates provided
      into a tree path with <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeView.html#gtk-tree-view-get-path-at-pos">
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_get_path_at_pos</literal></ulink>.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-dnd-rows-within-tree">
      <title>Dragging Rows Around Within a Tree **** TODO ***</title>

      <para>****** TODO</para>

      <para>Both <literal>GtkListStore</literal> and
      <literal>GtkTreeStore</literal> implement the
      <literal>GtkTreeDragDest</literal> and
      <literal>GtkTreeDragSource</literal> interfaces, which means that they
      have in-built support for row reordering. You need to call
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_set_reorderable</literal> to activate this, and
      then connect to the tree model's signals to catch the reorderings that
      take place.</para>

      <para>*** SOMEONE NEEDS TO WRITE THIS SECTION (I have never gotten this
      to work in a way that does not suck, ie. where one does not have to
      place the row to move exact to the pixel on the target row).</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-dnd-rows-between-trees">
      <title>Dragging Rows from One Tree to Another **** TODO ***</title>

      <para>****** TODO (is this possible at all in Gtk+ &lt;= 2.2?)</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-custom-models">
    <title>Writing Custom Models</title>

    <sect1 id="sec-custom-models-when">
      <title>When is a Custom Model Useful?</title>

      <para>A custom tree model gives you complete control over your data and
      how it is represented to the outside (e.g. to the tree view widget). It
      has the advantage that you can store, access and modify your data
      exactly how you need it, and you can optimise the way your data is
      stored and retrieved, as you can write your own functions to access your
      data and need not rely solely on the
      <literal>gtk_tree_model_get</literal>. A model tailored to your needs
      will probably also be a lot faster than the generic list and tree stores
      that come with gtk and that have been designed with flexibility in
      mind.</para>

      <para>Another case where a custom model might come in handy is when you
      have all your data already stored in an external tree-like structure
      (for example a libxml2 XML tree) and only want to display that
      structure. Then you could write a custom model that maps that structure
      to a tree model (which is probably not quite as trivial as it sounds
      though).</para>

      <para>Using a custom model you could also implement a filter model that
      only displays certain rows according to some filter criterion instead of
      displaying all rows (Gtk+-2.4 has a filter model, <literal> <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModelFilter.html">
      GtkTreeModelFilter</ulink></literal>, that does exactly that and much
      more, but you might want to implement this yourself anyway. If you need
      to use GtkTreeModelFilter in Gtk-2.0 or Gtk-2.2, check out the code
      examples of this tutorial - there is GuiTreeModelFilter, which is
      basically just the original GtkTreeModelFilter but has been made to work
      with earlier Gtk-2.x versions and has a different name space, so that it
      does not clash with Gtk-2.4).</para>

      <para>However, all this comes at a cost: you are unlikely to write a
      useful custom model in less than a thousand lines, unless you strip all
      newline characters. Writing a custom model is not as difficult as it
      might sound though, and it may well be worth the effort, not least
      because it will result in much saner code if you have a lot of data to
      keep track of.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-custom-models-what">
      <title>What Does Writing a Custom Model Involve?</title>

      <para>Basically, all you need to do is to write a new GObject that
      implements the <literal>GtkTreeModel</literal> interface,
      <literal>GtkTreeModelIface</literal>. Intimate knowledge about the GLib
      GObject system is not a requirement - you just need to copy some
      boilerplate code and modify it a bit. The core of your custom tree model
      is your own implementation of a couple of
      <literal>gtk_tree_model_foo</literal> functions that reveal the
      structure of your data, ie. how many rows there are, how many children a
      row has, how many columns there are and what type of data they contain.
      Furthermore, you need to provide functions that convert a tree path to a
      tree iter and a tree iter to a tree path. Additionally, you should
      provide some functions to add and remove rows to your custom model, but
      those are only ever used by yourself anyway, so they do not fall within
      the scope of the tree model interface.</para>

      <para>The functions you <emphasis>need</emphasis> to implement
      are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><literal>get_flags</literal> - tells the outside that your
          model has certain special characterstics, like persistent
          iters.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>get_n_columns</literal> - how many data fields per
          row are visible to the outside that uses gtk_tree_model_get, e.g.
          cell renderer attributes</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>get_column_type</literal> - what type of data is
          stored in a data field (model column) that is visible to the
          outside</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>get_iter</literal> - take a tree path and fill an
          iter structure so that you know which row it refers to</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>get_path</literal> - take an iter and convert it into
          a tree path, ie. the 'physical' position within the model</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>get_value</literal> - retrieve data from a row</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>iter_next</literal> - take an iter structure and make
          it point to the next row</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>iter_children</literal> - tell whether the row
          represented by a given iter has any children or not</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>iter_n_children</literal> - tell how many children a
          row represented by a given iter has</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>iter_nth_child</literal> - set a given iter structure
          to the n-th child of a given parent iter</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>iter_parent</literal> - set a given iter structure to
          the parent of a given child iter</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>It is up to you to decide which of your data you make 'visible' to
      the outside in form of model columns and which not. You can always
      implement functions specific to your custom model that will return any
      data in any form you desire. You only <emphasis>need</emphasis> to make
      data 'visble' to the outside via the GType and GValue system if you want
      the tree view components to access it (e.g. when setting cell renderer
      attributes).</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-custom-model-list">
      <title>Example: A Simple Custom List Model</title>

      <para>What follows is the outline for a simple custom list model. You
      can find the complete source code for this model <link
      linkend="sec-custom-model-code">below</link>. The beginning of the code
      might look a bit scary, but you can just skip most of the GObject and
      GType stuff and proceed to the heart of the custom list, ie. the
      implementation of the tree model functions.</para>

      <para>Our list model is represented by a simple list of records, where
      each row corresponds to a <literal>CustomRecord</literal> structure
      which keeps track of the data we are interested in. For now, we only
      want to keep track of persons' names and years of birth (usually this
      would not really justify a custom model, but this is still just an
      example). It is trivial to extend the model to deal with additional
      fields in the <literal>CustomRecord</literal> structure.</para>

      <para>Within the model, more precisely: the
      <literal>CustomList</literal> structure, the list is stored as a pointer
      array, which not only provides fast access to the n-th record in the
      list, but also comes in handy later on when we add sorting. Apart from
      that, any other kind of list-specific data would go in this structure as
      well (the active sort column, for example, or hash tables to speed up
      searching for a specific row, etc.).</para>

      <para>Each row in our list is represented by a
      <literal>CustomRecord</literal> structure. You can store whatever other
      data you need in that structure. How you make row data available is up
      to you. Either you export it via the tree model interface using the
      <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gobject/gobject-Standard-Parameter-and-Value-Types.html">GValue
      system</ulink>, so that you can use
      <literal>gtk_tree_model_get</literal> to retrieve your data, or you
      provide custom model-specific functions to retrieve data, for example
      <literal>custom_list_get_name</literal>, taking a tree iter or a tree
      path as argument. Of course you can also do both.</para>

      <para>Furthermore, you will need to provide your own functions to add
      rows, remove rows, and set or modify row data, and you need to let the
      view and others know whenever something changes in your model by
      emitting the appropriate signals via the provided tree model
      functions.</para>

      <para>Some thought should go into how exactly you fill the <ulink
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#GtkTreeIter">
      <literal>GtkTreeIter</literal> fields</ulink> of the tree iters used by
      your model. You have three pointer fields at your disposal. These should
      be filled so that you can easily identify the row given the iter, and
      should also facilitate access to the next row and the parent row (if
      any). If your model advertises to have persistent iters, you need to
      make sure that the content of your iters is perfectly valid even if the
      user stores it somewhere for later use and the model gets changed or
      reordered. The 'stamp' field of a tree iter should be filled by a random
      model-instance-specific integer that was assigned to the model when it
      was created. This way you can catch iters that do not belong to your
      model. If your model does not have persistent iters, then you should
      change the model's stamp whenever the model changes, so that you can
      catch invalid iters that get passed to your functions (note: in the code
      below we do not check the stamp of the iters in order to save a couple
      of lines of code to print here).</para>

      <para>In our specific example, we simply store a pointer to a row's
      <literal>CustomRecord</literal> structure in our model's tree iters,
      which is valid as long as the row exists. Additionally we store the
      position of a row within the list in the <literal>CustomRecord</literal>
      as well, which is not only intuitive, but is also useful later on when
      we resort the list.</para>

      <para>If you want to store an integer value in an iter's fields, you
      should use GLib's <literal>GINT_TO_POINTER</literal> and
      <literal>GPOINTER_TO_INT</literal> macros for that.</para>

      <para>Let's look at the code sections in a bit more detail:</para>

      <sect2 id="sec-custom-model-list-header">
        <title>custom-list.h</title>

        <para>The <link linkend="sec-custom-model-code-header">header
        file</link> for our custom list model defines some standard type casts
        and type check macros, our <literal>CustomRecord</literal> structure,
        our <literal>CustomList</literal> structure, and some enums for the
        model columns we are exporting.</para>

        <para>The <literal>CustomRecord</literal> structure represents one
        row, while the <literal>CustomList</literal> structure contains all
        list-specific data. You can add additional fields to both structures
        without problems. For example, you might need a function that quickly
        looks up rows given the name or year of birth, for which additional
        hashtables or so might come in handy (which you would need to keep up
        to date as you insert, modify or remove rows of course).</para>

        <para>The only function you must export is
        <literal>custom_list_get_type</literal>, as it is used by the type
        check and type cast macros that are also defined in the header file.
        Additionally, we want to export a function to create one instance of
        our custom model, and a function that adds some rows. You will
        probably add more custom model-specific functions to modify the model
        as you extend it to suit your needs.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-custom-model-list-body">
        <title>custom-list.c</title>

        <para>Firstly, we need some boilerplate code to register our custom
        model with the GObject type system. You can skip this section and
        proceed to the tree model implementation.</para>

        <para>Functions of interested in this section are
        <literal>custom_list_init</literal> and
        <literal>custom_list_get_type</literal>. In
        <literal>custom_list_init</literal> we define what data type our
        exported model columns have, and how many columns we export. Towards
        the end of <literal>custom_list_get_type</literal> we register the
        <literal>GtkTreeModel</literal> interface with our custom model
        object. This is where we can also register additional interfaces (e.g.
        <literal>GtkTreeSortable</literal> or one of the Drag'n'Drop
        interfaces) that we want to implement.</para>

        <para>In <literal>custom_list_tree_model_init</literal> we override
        those tree model functions that we need to implement with our own
        functions. If it is beneficial for your model to know which rows are
        currently displayed in the tree view (for example for caching), you
        might want to override the <literal>ref_node</literal> and
        <literal>unref_node</literal> functions as well.</para>

        <para>Let's have a look at the heart of the object type
        registration:</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
GType
custom_list_get_type (void)
{
  static GType custom_list_type = 0;

  if (custom_list_type)
    return custom_list_type;

  /* Some boilerplate type registration stuff */
  if (1)
  {
    static const GTypeInfo custom_list_info =
    {
      sizeof (CustomListClass),
      NULL,                                         /* base_init */
      NULL,                                         /* base_finalize */
      (GClassInitFunc) custom_list_class_init,
      NULL,                                         /* class finalize */
      NULL,                                         /* class_data */
      sizeof (CustomList),
      0,                                           /* n_preallocs */
      (GInstanceInitFunc) custom_list_init
    };

    custom_list_type = g_type_register_static (G_TYPE_OBJECT, "CustomList",
                                               &amp;custom_list_info, (GTypeFlags)0);
  }

  /* Here we register our GtkTreeModel interface with the type system */
  if (1)
  {
    static const GInterfaceInfo tree_model_info =
    {
      (GInterfaceInitFunc) custom_list_tree_model_init,
      NULL,
      NULL
    };

    g_type_add_interface_static (custom_list_type, GTK_TYPE_TREE_MODEL, &amp;tree_model_info);
  }

  return custom_list_type;
}

</programlisting>

        <para>Here we just return the type assigned to our custom list by the
        type system if we have already registered it. If not, we register it
        and save the type. Of the three callbacks that we pass to the type
        system, only two are of immediate interest to us, namely
        <literal>custom_list_tree_model_init</literal> and
        <literal>custom_list_init</literal>.</para>

        <para>In <literal>custom_list_tree_model_init</literal> we fill the
        tree model interface structure with pointers to our own functions (at
        least the ones we implement):</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
static void
custom_list_tree_model_init (GtkTreeModelIface *iface)
{
  /* Here we override the GtkTreeModel
   *  interface functions that we implement */
  iface-&gt;get_flags       = custom_list_get_flags;
  iface-&gt;get_n_columns   = custom_list_get_n_columns;
  iface-&gt;get_column_type = custom_list_get_column_type;
  iface-&gt;get_iter        = custom_list_get_iter;
  iface-&gt;get_path        = custom_list_get_path;
  iface-&gt;get_value       = custom_list_get_value;
  iface-&gt;iter_next       = custom_list_iter_next;
  iface-&gt;iter_children   = custom_list_iter_children;
  iface-&gt;iter_has_child  = custom_list_iter_has_child;
  iface-&gt;iter_n_children = custom_list_iter_n_children;
  iface-&gt;iter_nth_child  = custom_list_iter_nth_child;
  iface-&gt;iter_parent     = custom_list_iter_parent;
}
</programlisting>

        <para>In <literal>custom_list_init</literal> we initialised the custom
        list structure to sensible default values. This function will be
        called whenever a new instance of our custom list is created, which we
        do in <literal>custom_list_new</literal>.</para>

        <para><literal>custom_list_finalize</literal> is called just before
        one of our lists is going to be destroyed. You should free all
        resources that you have dynamically allocated in there.</para>

        <para>Having taken care of all the type system stuff, we now come to
        the heart of our custom model, namely the tree model implementation.
        Our tree model functions need to behave exactly as the API reference
        requires them to behave, including all special cases, otherwise things
        will not work. Here is a list of links to the API reference
        descriptions of the functions we are implementing:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get-flags">gtk_tree_model_get_flags</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get-n-columns">gtk_tree_model_get_n_columns</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get-column-type">gtk_tree_model_get_column_type</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get-iter">gtk_tree_model_get_iter</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get-path">gtk_tree_model_get_path</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-get-value">gtk_tree_model_get_value</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-iter-next">gtk_tree_model_iter_next</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-iter-children">gtk_tree_model_iter_children</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-iter-has-child">gtk_tree_model_iter_has_child</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-iter-n-children">gtk_tree_model_iter_n_children</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-iter-nth-child">gtk_tree_model_iter_nth_child</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-iter-parent">gtk_tree_model_iter_parent</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Almost all functions are more or less straight-forward and
        self-explanatory in connection with the API reference descriptions, so
        you should be able to jump right into <link
        linkend="sec-custom-model-code-body">the code</link> and see how it
        works.</para>

        <para>After the tree model implementation we have those functions that
        are specific to our custom model. <literal>custom_list_new</literal>
        will create a new custom list for us, and
        <literal>custom_list_append_record</literal> will append a new record
        to the end of the list. Note the call to
        <literal>gtk_tree_model_row_inserted</literal> at the end of our
        append function, which emits a <literal>"row-inserted"</literal>
        signal on the model and informs all interested objects (tree views,
        tree row references) that a new row has been inserted, and where it
        has been inserted.</para>

        <para>You will need to emit tree model signals whenever something
        changes, e.g. rows are inserted, removed, or reordered, or when a row
        changes from a child-less row to a row which has children, or if a
        row's data changes. Here are the functions you need to use in those
        cases (we only implement row insertions here - other cases are left as
        an exercise for the reader):</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-row-inserted">gtk_tree_model_row_inserted</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-row-changed">gtk_tree_model_row_changed</ulink>
            (makes tree view redraw that row)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-row-has-child-toggled">gtk_tree_model_row_has_child_toggled</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-row-deleted">gtk_tree_model_row_deleted</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeModel.html#gtk-tree-model-rows-reordered">gtk_tree_model_rows_reordered</ulink>
            (note <ulink
            url="http://bugs.gnome.org/show_bug.cgi?id=124790">bug
            124790</ulink>)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>And that is all you have to do to write a custom model.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-custom-model-tree">
      <title>From a List to a Tree</title>

      <para>Writing a custom model for a tree is a bit trickier than a simple
      list model, but follows the same pattern. Basically you just need to
      extend the above model to cater for the case of children. You could do
      this by keeping track of the whole tree hierarchy in the
      <literal>CustomList</literal> structure, using GLib N-ary trees for
      example, or you could do this by keeping track of each row's children
      within the row's <literal>CustomRecord</literal> structure, keeping only
      a pointer to the (invisible) root record in the
      <literal>CustomList</literal> structure.</para>

      <para>TODO: do we need anything else here?</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-custom-model-sorting">
      <title>Additional interfaces, here: the GtkTreeSortable
      interface</title>

      <para>A custom model can implement additional interfaces to extend its
      functionality. Additional interfaces are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/GtkTreeSortable.html#GtkTreeSortableIface">GtkTreeSortableIface</ulink></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/gtk-GtkTreeView-drag-and-drop.html#GtkTreeDragDestIface">GtkTreeDragDestIface</ulink></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/gtk-GtkTreeView-drag-and-drop.html#GtkTreeDragSourceIface">GtkTreeDragSourceIface</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Here, we will show how to implement additional interfaces at the
      example of the <literal>GtkTreeSortable</literal> interface, which we
      will implement only partially (enough to make it functional and useful
      though).</para>

      <para>Three things are necessary to add another interface: we will need
      to register the interface with our model in
      <literal>custom_list_get_type</literal>, provide an interface init
      function where we set the interface to our own implementation of the
      interface functions, and then provide the implementation of those
      functions.</para>

      <para>Firstly, we need to provide the function prototypes for our
      functions at the beginning of the file:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">

  /* custom-list.c */

  ...

  /* -- GtkTreeSortable interface functions -- */

  static gboolean     custom_list_sortable_get_sort_column_id (GtkTreeSortable *sortable,
                                                               gint            *sort_col_id,
                                                               GtkSortType     *order);

  static void         custom_list_sortable_set_sort_column_id (GtkTreeSortable *sortable,
                                                               gint             sort_col_id,
                                                               GtkSortType      order);

  static void         custom_list_sortable_set_sort_func (GtkTreeSortable        *sortable,
                                                          gint                    sort_col_id,
                                                          GtkTreeIterCompareFunc  sort_func,
                                                          gpointer                user_data,
                                                          GtkDestroyNotify        destroy_func);

  static void         custom_list_sortable_set_default_sort_func (GtkTreeSortable        *sortable,
                                                                  GtkTreeIterCompareFunc  sort_func,
                                                                  gpointer                user_data,
                                                                  GtkDestroyNotify        destroy_func);

  static gboolean     custom_list_sortable_has_default_sort_func (GtkTreeSortable *sortable);

  static void         custom_list_resort (CustomList *custom_list);

  ...
</programlisting>

      <para>Next, let's extend our <literal>CustomList</literal> structure
      with a field for the currently active sort column ID and one for the
      sort order, and add an enum for the sort column IDs:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  /* custom-list.h */

  enum
  {
    SORT_ID_NONE = 0,
    SORT_ID_NAME,
    SORT_ID_YEAR_BORN,
  };

  ...

  struct _CustomList
  {
    GObject         parent;

    guint           num_rows;    /* number of rows that we have */
    CustomRecord  **rows;        /* a dynamically allocated array of pointers to the
                                  *  CustomRecord structure for each row */

    gint            n_columns;
    GType           column_types[CUSTOM_LIST_N_COLUMNS];

    gint            sort_id;
    GtkSortType     sort_order;

    gint            stamp;       /* Random integer to check whether an iter belongs to our model */
  };

  ...
</programlisting>

      <para>Now, we make sure we initialise the new fields in
      <literal>custom_list_new</literal>, and add our new interface:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  ...

  static void    custom_list_sortable_init (GtkTreeSortableIface *iface);

  ...

  void
  custom_list_init (CustomList *custom_list)
  {
    ...
    custom_list-&gt;sort_id    = SORT_ID_NONE;
    custom_list-&gt;sort_order = GTK_SORT_ASCENDING;
    ...
  }


  GType
  custom_list_get_type (void)
  {
    ...
    /* Add GtkTreeSortable interface */
    if (1)
    {
      static const GInterfaceInfo tree_sortable_info =
      {
        (GInterfaceInitFunc) custom_list_sortable_init,
        NULL,
        NULL
      };

      g_type_add_interface_static (custom_list_type, GTK_TYPE_TREE_SORTABLE, &amp;tree_sortable_info);
    }
    ...
  }


  static void
  custom_list_sortable_init (GtkTreeSortableIface *iface)
  {
    iface-&gt;get_sort_column_id    = custom_list_sortable_get_sort_column_id;
    iface-&gt;set_sort_column_id    = custom_list_sortable_set_sort_column_id;
    iface-&gt;set_sort_func         = custom_list_sortable_set_sort_func;          /* NOT SUPPORTED */
    iface-&gt;set_default_sort_func = custom_list_sortable_set_default_sort_func;  /* NOT SUPPORTED */
    iface-&gt;has_default_sort_func = custom_list_sortable_has_default_sort_func;  /* NOT SUPPORTED */
  }

</programlisting>

      <para>Now that we have finally taken care of the administrativa, we
      implement the tree sortable interface functions:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">

  static gboolean
  custom_list_sortable_get_sort_column_id (GtkTreeSortable *sortable,
                                           gint            *sort_col_id,
                                           GtkSortType     *order)
  {
    CustomList *custom_list;

    g_return_val_if_fail ( sortable != NULL        , FALSE );
    g_return_val_if_fail ( CUSTOM_IS_LIST(sortable), FALSE );

    custom_list = CUSTOM_LIST(sortable);

    if (sort_col_id)
      *sort_col_id = custom_list-&gt;sort_id;

    if (order)
      *order =  custom_list-&gt;sort_order;

    return TRUE;
  }


  static void
  custom_list_sortable_set_sort_column_id (GtkTreeSortable *sortable,
                                           gint             sort_col_id,
                                           GtkSortType      order)
  {
    CustomList *custom_list;

    g_return_if_fail ( sortable != NULL         );
    g_return_if_fail ( CUSTOM_IS_LIST(sortable) );

    custom_list = CUSTOM_LIST(sortable);

    if (custom_list-&gt;sort_id == sort_col_id &amp;&amp; custom_list-&gt;sort_order == order)
      return;

    custom_list-&gt;sort_id = sort_col_id;
    custom_list-&gt;sort_order  = order;

    custom_list_resort(custom_list);

    /* emit "sort-column-changed" signal to tell any tree views
     *  that the sort column has changed (so the little arrow
     *  in the column header of the sort column is drawn
     *  in the right column)                                     */

    gtk_tree_sortable_sort_column_changed(sortable);
  }


  static void
  custom_list_sortable_set_sort_func (GtkTreeSortable        *sortable,
                                      gint                    sort_col_id,
                                      GtkTreeIterCompareFunc  sort_func,
                                      gpointer                user_data,
                                      GtkDestroyNotify        destroy_func)
  {
    g_warning ("%s is not supported by the CustomList model.\n", __FUNCTION__);
  }


  static void
  custom_list_sortable_set_default_sort_func (GtkTreeSortable        *sortable,
                                              GtkTreeIterCompareFunc  sort_func,
                                              gpointer                user_data,
                                              GtkDestroyNotify        destroy_func)
  {
    g_warning ("%s is not supported by the CustomList model.\n", __FUNCTION__);
  }


  static gboolean
  custom_list_sortable_has_default_sort_func (GtkTreeSortable *sortable)
  {
    return FALSE;
  }

</programlisting>

      <para>Now, last but not least, the only thing missing is the function
      that does the actual sorting. We do not implement
      <literal>set_sort_func</literal>,
      <literal>set_default_sort_func</literal> and
      <literal>set_has_default_sort_func</literal> because we use our own
      internal sort function here.</para>

      <para>The actual sorting is done using GLib's
      <literal>g_qsort_with_data</literal> function, which sorts an array
      using the QuickSort algorithm. Note how we notify the tree view and
      other objects of the new row order by emitting the "rows-reordered"
      signal on the tree model.</para>

      <programlisting role="C">

  static gint
  custom_list_compare_records (gint sort_id, CustomRecord *a, CustomRecord *b)
  {
    switch(sort_id)
    {
      case SORT_ID_NONE:
        return 0;

      case SORT_ID_NAME:
      {
        if ((a-&gt;name) &amp;&amp; (b-&gt;name))
          return g_utf8_collate(a-&gt;name, b-&gt;name);

        if (a-&gt;name == b-&gt;name)
          return 0; /* both are NULL */
        else
          return (a-&gt;name == NULL) ? -1 : 1;
      }

      case SORT_ID_YEAR_BORN:
      {
        if (a-&gt;year_born == b-&gt;year_born)
          return 0;

        return (a-&gt;year_born &gt; b-&gt;year_born) ? 1 : -1;
      }
    }

    g_return_val_if_reached(0);
  }


  static gint
  custom_list_qsort_compare_func (CustomRecord **a, CustomRecord **b, CustomList *custom_list)
  {
    gint ret;

    g_assert ((a) &amp;&amp; (b) &amp;&amp; (custom_list));

    ret = custom_list_compare_records(custom_list-&gt;sort_id, *a, *b);

    /* Swap -1 and 1 if sort order is reverse */
    if (ret != 0  &amp;&amp;  custom_list-&gt;sort_order == GTK_SORT_DESCENDING)
      ret = (ret &lt; 0) ? 1 : -1;

    return ret;
  }


  static void
  custom_list_resort (CustomList *custom_list)
  {
    GtkTreePath *path;
    gint        *neworder, i;

    g_return_if_fail ( custom_list != NULL );
    g_return_if_fail ( CUSTOM_IS_LIST(custom_list) );

    if (custom_list-&gt;sort_id == SORT_ID_NONE)
      return;

    if (custom_list-&gt;num_rows == 0)
      return;

    /* resort */
    g_qsort_with_data(custom_list-&gt;rows,
                      custom_list-&gt;num_rows,
                      sizeof(CustomRecord*),
                      (GCompareDataFunc) custom_list_qsort_compare_func,
                      custom_list);

    /* let other objects know about the new order */
    neworder = g_new0(gint, custom_list-&gt;num_rows);

    for (i = 0; i &lt; custom_list-&gt;num_rows; ++i)
    {
      /* Note that the API reference might be wrong about
       * this, see bug number 124790 on bugs.gnome.org.
       * Both will work, but one will give you 'jumpy'
       * selections after row reordering. */
      /* neworder[(custom_list-&gt;rows[i])-&gt;pos] = i; */
      neworder[i] = (custom_list-&gt;rows[i])-&gt;pos;
      (custom_list-&gt;rows[i])-&gt;pos = i;
    }

    path = gtk_tree_path_new();

    gtk_tree_model_rows_reordered(GTK_TREE_MODEL(custom_list), path, NULL, neworder);

    gtk_tree_path_free(path);
    g_free(neworder);
  }

</programlisting>

      <para>Finally, we should make sure that the model is resorted after we
      have inserted a new row by adding a call to
      <literal>custom_list_resort</literal> to the end of
      <literal>custom_list_append</literal>:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  ...
  void
  custom_list_append_record (CustomList *custom_list, const gchar *name, guint year_born)
  {
    ...

    custom_list_resort(custom_list);
  }

</programlisting>

      <para>And that is it. Adding two calls to
      <literal>gtk_tree_view_column_set_sort_column_id</literal> in main.c is
      left as yet another exercise for the reader.</para>

      <para>If you are interested in seeing string sorting speed issues in
      action, you should modify main.c like this:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  GtkWidget *
  create_view_and_model (void)
  {
    gint i;
    ...
    for (i=0; i &lt; 1000; ++i)
    {
      fill_model(customlist);
    }
    ...
  }
</programlisting>

      <para>Most likely, sorting 24000 rows by name will take up to several
      seconds now. Now, if you go back to
      <literal>custom_list_compare_records</literal> and replace the call to
      <literal>g_utf8_collate</literal> with:</para>

      <programlisting role="C">
  static gint
  custom_list_compare_records (gint sort_id, CustomRecord *a, CustomRecord *b)
  {
    ...

    if ((a-&gt;name) &amp;&amp; (b-&gt;name))
      return strcmp(a-&gt;name_collate_key,b-&gt;name_collate_key);

    ...
  }
</programlisting>

      <para>... then you should hopefully register a dramatic speed increase
      when sorting by name.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-custom-model-code">
      <title>Working Example: Custom List Model Source Code</title>

      <para>Here is the complete source code for the custom list model
      presented <link linkend="sec-custom-model-list">above</link>. Compile
      with:</para>

      <programlisting>
  gcc -o customlist custom-list.c main.c `pkg-config --cflags --libs gtk+-2.0`
</programlisting>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><link
          linkend="sec-custom-model-code-header">custom-list.h</link></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><link
          linkend="sec-custom-model-code-body">custom-list.c</link></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><link
          linkend="sec-custom-model-code-example">main.c</link></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <sect2 id="sec-custom-model-code-header">
        <title>custom-list.h</title>

        <programlisting role="C">
#ifndef _custom_list_h_included_
#define _custom_list_h_included_

#include &lt;gtk/gtk.h&gt;

/* Some boilerplate GObject defines. 'klass' is used
 *   instead of 'class', because 'class' is a C++ keyword */

#define CUSTOM_TYPE_LIST            (custom_list_get_type ())
#define CUSTOM_LIST(obj)            (G_TYPE_CHECK_INSTANCE_CAST ((obj), CUSTOM_TYPE_LIST, CustomList))
#define CUSTOM_LIST_CLASS(klass)    (G_TYPE_CHECK_CLASS_CAST ((klass),  CUSTOM_TYPE_LIST, CustomListClass))
#define CUSTOM_IS_LIST(obj)         (G_TYPE_CHECK_INSTANCE_TYPE ((obj), CUSTOM_TYPE_LIST))
#define CUSTOM_IS_LIST_CLASS(klass) (G_TYPE_CHECK_CLASS_TYPE ((klass),  CUSTOM_TYPE_LIST))
#define CUSTOM_LIST_GET_CLASS(obj)  (G_TYPE_INSTANCE_GET_CLASS ((obj),  CUSTOM_TYPE_LIST, CustomListClass))

/* The data columns that we export via the tree model interface */

enum
{
  CUSTOM_LIST_COL_RECORD = 0,
  CUSTOM_LIST_COL_NAME,
  CUSTOM_LIST_COL_YEAR_BORN,
  CUSTOM_LIST_N_COLUMNS,
} ;


typedef struct _CustomRecord     CustomRecord;
typedef struct _CustomList       CustomList;
typedef struct _CustomListClass  CustomListClass;



/* CustomRecord: this structure represents a row */

struct _CustomRecord
{
  /* data - you can extend this */
  gchar    *name;
  gchar    *name_collate_key;
  guint     year_born;

  /* admin stuff used by the custom list model */
  guint     pos;   /* pos within the array */
};



/* CustomList: this structure contains everything we need for our
 *             model implementation. You can add extra fields to
 *             this structure, e.g. hashtables to quickly lookup
 *             rows or whatever else you might need, but it is
 *             crucial that 'parent' is the first member of the
 *             structure.                                          */

struct _CustomList
{
  GObject         parent;      /* this MUST be the first member */

  guint           num_rows;    /* number of rows that we have   */
  CustomRecord  **rows;        /* a dynamically allocated array of pointers to
                                *   the CustomRecord structure for each row    */

  /* These two fields are not absolutely necessary, but they    */
  /*   speed things up a bit in our get_value implementation    */
  gint            n_columns;
  GType           column_types[CUSTOM_LIST_N_COLUMNS];

  gint            stamp;       /* Random integer to check whether an iter belongs to our model */
};



/* CustomListClass: more boilerplate GObject stuff */

struct _CustomListClass
{
  GObjectClass parent_class;
};


GType             custom_list_get_type (void);

CustomList       *custom_list_new (void);

void              custom_list_append_record (CustomList   *custom_list,
                                             const gchar  *name,
                                             guint         year_born);

#endif /* _custom_list_h_included_ */

</programlisting>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><link
            linkend="sec-custom-model-code-header">custom-list.h</link></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><link
            linkend="sec-custom-model-code-body">custom-list.c</link></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><link
            linkend="sec-custom-model-code-example">main.c</link></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-custom-model-code-body">
        <title>custom-list.c</title>

        <programlisting role="C">

#include "custom-list.h"


/* boring declarations of local functions */

static void         custom_list_init            (CustomList      *pkg_tree);

static void         custom_list_class_init      (CustomListClass *klass);

static void         custom_list_tree_model_init (GtkTreeModelIface *iface);

static void         custom_list_finalize        (GObject           *object);

static GtkTreeModelFlags custom_list_get_flags  (GtkTreeModel      *tree_model);

static gint         custom_list_get_n_columns   (GtkTreeModel      *tree_model);

static GType        custom_list_get_column_type (GtkTreeModel      *tree_model,
                                                 gint               index);

static gboolean     custom_list_get_iter        (GtkTreeModel      *tree_model,
                                                 GtkTreeIter       *iter,
                                                 GtkTreePath       *path);

static GtkTreePath *custom_list_get_path        (GtkTreeModel      *tree_model,
                                                 GtkTreeIter       *iter);

static void         custom_list_get_value       (GtkTreeModel      *tree_model,
                                                 GtkTreeIter       *iter,
                                                 gint               column,
                                                 GValue            *value);

static gboolean     custom_list_iter_next       (GtkTreeModel      *tree_model,
                                                 GtkTreeIter       *iter);

static gboolean     custom_list_iter_children   (GtkTreeModel      *tree_model,
                                                 GtkTreeIter       *iter,
                                                 GtkTreeIter       *parent);

static gboolean     custom_list_iter_has_child  (GtkTreeModel      *tree_model,
                                                 GtkTreeIter       *iter);

static gint         custom_list_iter_n_children (GtkTreeModel      *tree_model,
                                                 GtkTreeIter       *iter);

static gboolean     custom_list_iter_nth_child  (GtkTreeModel      *tree_model,
                                                 GtkTreeIter       *iter,
                                                 GtkTreeIter       *parent,
                                                 gint               n);

static gboolean     custom_list_iter_parent     (GtkTreeModel      *tree_model,
                                                 GtkTreeIter       *iter,
                                                 GtkTreeIter       *child);



static GObjectClass *parent_class = NULL;  /* GObject stuff - nothing to worry about */


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_get_type: here we register our new type and its interfaces
 *                        with the type system. If you want to implement
 *                        additional interfaces like GtkTreeSortable, you
 *                        will need to do it here.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

GType
custom_list_get_type (void)
{
  static GType custom_list_type = 0;

  if (custom_list_type)
    return custom_list_type;

  /* Some boilerplate type registration stuff */
  if (1)
  {
    static const GTypeInfo custom_list_info =
    {
      sizeof (CustomListClass),
      NULL,                                         /* base_init */
      NULL,                                         /* base_finalize */
      (GClassInitFunc) custom_list_class_init,
      NULL,                                         /* class finalize */
      NULL,                                         /* class_data */
      sizeof (CustomList),
      0,                                           /* n_preallocs */
      (GInstanceInitFunc) custom_list_init
    };

    custom_list_type = g_type_register_static (G_TYPE_OBJECT, "CustomList",
                                               &amp;custom_list_info, (GTypeFlags)0);
  }

  /* Here we register our GtkTreeModel interface with the type system */
  if (1)
  {
    static const GInterfaceInfo tree_model_info =
    {
      (GInterfaceInitFunc) custom_list_tree_model_init,
      NULL,
      NULL
    };

    g_type_add_interface_static (custom_list_type, GTK_TYPE_TREE_MODEL, &amp;tree_model_info);
  }

  return custom_list_type;
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_class_init: more boilerplate GObject/GType stuff.
 *                          Init callback for the type system,
 *                          called once when our new class is created.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static void
custom_list_class_init (CustomListClass *klass)
{
  GObjectClass *object_class;

  parent_class = (GObjectClass*) g_type_class_peek_parent (klass);
  object_class = (GObjectClass*) klass;

  object_class-&gt;finalize = custom_list_finalize;
}

/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_tree_model_init: init callback for the interface registration
 *                               in custom_list_get_type. Here we override
 *                               the GtkTreeModel interface functions that
 *                               we implement.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static void
custom_list_tree_model_init (GtkTreeModelIface *iface)
{
  iface-&gt;get_flags       = custom_list_get_flags;
  iface-&gt;get_n_columns   = custom_list_get_n_columns;
  iface-&gt;get_column_type = custom_list_get_column_type;
  iface-&gt;get_iter        = custom_list_get_iter;
  iface-&gt;get_path        = custom_list_get_path;
  iface-&gt;get_value       = custom_list_get_value;
  iface-&gt;iter_next       = custom_list_iter_next;
  iface-&gt;iter_children   = custom_list_iter_children;
  iface-&gt;iter_has_child  = custom_list_iter_has_child;
  iface-&gt;iter_n_children = custom_list_iter_n_children;
  iface-&gt;iter_nth_child  = custom_list_iter_nth_child;
  iface-&gt;iter_parent     = custom_list_iter_parent;
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_init: this is called everytime a new custom list object
 *                    instance is created (we do that in custom_list_new).
 *                    Initialise the list structure's fields here.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static void
custom_list_init (CustomList *custom_list)
{
  custom_list-&gt;n_columns       = CUSTOM_LIST_N_COLUMNS;

  custom_list-&gt;column_types[0] = G_TYPE_POINTER;  /* CUSTOM_LIST_COL_RECORD    */
  custom_list-&gt;column_types[1] = G_TYPE_STRING;   /* CUSTOM_LIST_COL_NAME      */
  custom_list-&gt;column_types[2] = G_TYPE_UINT;     /* CUSTOM_LIST_COL_YEAR_BORN */

  g_assert (CUSTOM_LIST_N_COLUMNS == 3);

  custom_list-&gt;num_rows = 0;
  custom_list-&gt;rows     = NULL;

  custom_list-&gt;stamp = g_random_int();  /* Random int to check whether an iter belongs to our model */

}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_finalize: this is called just before a custom list is
 *                        destroyed. Free dynamically allocated memory here.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static void
custom_list_finalize (GObject *object)
{
/*  CustomList *custom_list = CUSTOM_LIST(object); */

  /* free all records and free all memory used by the list */
  #warning IMPLEMENT

  /* must chain up - finalize parent */
  (* parent_class-&gt;finalize) (object);
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_get_flags: tells the rest of the world whether our tree model
 *                         has any special characteristics. In our case,
 *                         we have a list model (instead of a tree), and each
 *                         tree iter is valid as long as the row in question
 *                         exists, as it only contains a pointer to our struct.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static GtkTreeModelFlags
custom_list_get_flags (GtkTreeModel *tree_model)
{
  g_return_val_if_fail (CUSTOM_IS_LIST(tree_model), (GtkTreeModelFlags)0);

  return (GTK_TREE_MODEL_LIST_ONLY | GTK_TREE_MODEL_ITERS_PERSIST);
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_get_n_columns: tells the rest of the world how many data
 *                             columns we export via the tree model interface
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static gint
custom_list_get_n_columns (GtkTreeModel *tree_model)
{
  g_return_val_if_fail (CUSTOM_IS_LIST(tree_model), 0);

  return CUSTOM_LIST(tree_model)-&gt;n_columns;
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_get_column_type: tells the rest of the world which type of
 *                               data an exported model column contains
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static GType
custom_list_get_column_type (GtkTreeModel *tree_model,
                             gint          index)
{
  g_return_val_if_fail (CUSTOM_IS_LIST(tree_model), G_TYPE_INVALID);
  g_return_val_if_fail (index &lt; CUSTOM_LIST(tree_model)-&gt;n_columns &amp;&amp; index &gt;= 0, G_TYPE_INVALID);

  return CUSTOM_LIST(tree_model)-&gt;column_types[index];
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_get_iter: converts a tree path (physical position) into a
 *                        tree iter structure (the content of the iter
 *                        fields will only be used internally by our model).
 *                        We simply store a pointer to our CustomRecord
 *                        structure that represents that row in the tree iter.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static gboolean
custom_list_get_iter (GtkTreeModel *tree_model,
                      GtkTreeIter  *iter,
                      GtkTreePath  *path)
{
  CustomList    *custom_list;
  CustomRecord  *record;
  gint          *indices, n, depth;

  g_assert(CUSTOM_IS_LIST(tree_model));
  g_assert(path!=NULL);

  custom_list = CUSTOM_LIST(tree_model);

  indices = gtk_tree_path_get_indices(path);
  depth   = gtk_tree_path_get_depth(path);

  /* we do not allow children */
  g_assert(depth == 1); /* depth 1 = top level; a list only has top level nodes and no children */

  n = indices[0]; /* the n-th top level row */

  if ( n &gt;= custom_list-&gt;num_rows || n &lt; 0 )
    return FALSE;

  record = custom_list-&gt;rows[n];

  g_assert(record != NULL);
  g_assert(record-&gt;pos == n);

  /* We simply store a pointer to our custom record in the iter */
  iter-&gt;stamp      = custom_list-&gt;stamp;
  iter-&gt;user_data  = record;
  iter-&gt;user_data2 = NULL;   /* unused */
  iter-&gt;user_data3 = NULL;   /* unused */

  return TRUE;
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_get_path: converts a tree iter into a tree path (ie. the
 *                        physical position of that row in the list).
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static GtkTreePath *
custom_list_get_path (GtkTreeModel *tree_model,
                      GtkTreeIter  *iter)
{
  GtkTreePath  *path;
  CustomRecord *record;
  CustomList   *custom_list;

  g_return_val_if_fail (CUSTOM_IS_LIST(tree_model), NULL);
  g_return_val_if_fail (iter != NULL,               NULL);
  g_return_val_if_fail (iter-&gt;user_data != NULL,    NULL);

  custom_list = CUSTOM_LIST(tree_model);

  record = (CustomRecord*) iter-&gt;user_data;

  path = gtk_tree_path_new();
  gtk_tree_path_append_index(path, record-&gt;pos);

  return path;
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_get_value: Returns a row's exported data columns
 *                         (_get_value is what gtk_tree_model_get uses)
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static void
custom_list_get_value (GtkTreeModel *tree_model,
                       GtkTreeIter  *iter,
                       gint          column,
                       GValue       *value)
{
  CustomRecord  *record;
  CustomList    *custom_list;

  g_return_if_fail (CUSTOM_IS_LIST (tree_model));
  g_return_if_fail (iter != NULL);
  g_return_if_fail (column &lt; CUSTOM_LIST(tree_model)-&gt;n_columns);

  g_value_init (value, CUSTOM_LIST(tree_model)-&gt;column_types[column]);

  custom_list = CUSTOM_LIST(tree_model);

  record = (CustomRecord*) iter-&gt;user_data;

  g_return_if_fail ( record != NULL );

  if(record-&gt;pos &gt;= custom_list-&gt;num_rows)
   g_return_if_reached();

  switch(column)
  {
    case CUSTOM_LIST_COL_RECORD:
      g_value_set_pointer(value, record);
      break;

    case CUSTOM_LIST_COL_NAME:
      g_value_set_string(value, record-&gt;name);
      break;

    case CUSTOM_LIST_COL_YEAR_BORN:
      g_value_set_uint(value, record-&gt;year_born);
      break;
  }
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_iter_next: Takes an iter structure and sets it to point
 *                         to the next row.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static gboolean
custom_list_iter_next (GtkTreeModel  *tree_model,
                       GtkTreeIter   *iter)
{
  CustomRecord  *record, *nextrecord;
  CustomList    *custom_list;

  g_return_val_if_fail (CUSTOM_IS_LIST (tree_model), FALSE);

  if (iter == NULL || iter-&gt;user_data == NULL)
    return FALSE;

  custom_list = CUSTOM_LIST(tree_model);

  record = (CustomRecord *) iter-&gt;user_data;

  /* Is this the last record in the list? */
  if ((record-&gt;pos + 1) &gt;= custom_list-&gt;num_rows)
    return FALSE;

  nextrecord = custom_list-&gt;rows[(record-&gt;pos + 1)];

  g_assert ( nextrecord != NULL );
  g_assert ( nextrecord-&gt;pos == (record-&gt;pos + 1) );

  iter-&gt;stamp     = custom_list-&gt;stamp;
  iter-&gt;user_data = nextrecord;

  return TRUE;
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_iter_children: Returns TRUE or FALSE depending on whether
 *                             the row specified by 'parent' has any children.
 *                             If it has children, then 'iter' is set to
 *                             point to the first child. Special case: if
 *                             'parent' is NULL, then the first top-level
 *                             row should be returned if it exists.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static gboolean
custom_list_iter_children (GtkTreeModel *tree_model,
                           GtkTreeIter  *iter,
                           GtkTreeIter  *parent)
{
  CustomList  *custom_list;

  g_return_val_if_fail (parent == NULL || parent-&gt;user_data != NULL, FALSE);

  /* this is a list, nodes have no children */
  if (parent)
    return FALSE;

  /* parent == NULL is a special case; we need to return the first top-level row */

  g_return_val_if_fail (CUSTOM_IS_LIST (tree_model), FALSE);

  custom_list = CUSTOM_LIST(tree_model);

  /* No rows =&gt; no first row */
  if (custom_list-&gt;num_rows == 0)
    return FALSE;

  /* Set iter to first item in list */
  iter-&gt;stamp     = custom_list-&gt;stamp;
  iter-&gt;user_data = custom_list-&gt;rows[0];

  return TRUE;
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_iter_has_child: Returns TRUE or FALSE depending on whether
 *                              the row specified by 'iter' has any children.
 *                              We only have a list and thus no children.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static gboolean
custom_list_iter_has_child (GtkTreeModel *tree_model,
                            GtkTreeIter  *iter)
{
  return FALSE;
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_iter_n_children: Returns the number of children the row
 *                               specified by 'iter' has. This is usually 0,
 *                               as we only have a list and thus do not have
 *                               any children to any rows. A special case is
 *                               when 'iter' is NULL, in which case we need
 *                               to return the number of top-level nodes,
 *                               ie. the number of rows in our list.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static gint
custom_list_iter_n_children (GtkTreeModel *tree_model,
                             GtkTreeIter  *iter)
{
  CustomList  *custom_list;

  g_return_val_if_fail (CUSTOM_IS_LIST (tree_model), -1);
  g_return_val_if_fail (iter == NULL || iter-&gt;user_data != NULL, FALSE);

  custom_list = CUSTOM_LIST(tree_model);

  /* special case: if iter == NULL, return number of top-level rows */
  if (!iter)
    return custom_list-&gt;num_rows;

  return 0; /* otherwise, this is easy again for a list */
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_iter_nth_child: If the row specified by 'parent' has any
 *                              children, set 'iter' to the n-th child and
 *                              return TRUE if it exists, otherwise FALSE.
 *                              A special case is when 'parent' is NULL, in
 *                              which case we need to set 'iter' to the n-th
 *                              row if it exists.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static gboolean
custom_list_iter_nth_child (GtkTreeModel *tree_model,
                            GtkTreeIter  *iter,
                            GtkTreeIter  *parent,
                            gint          n)
{
  CustomRecord  *record;
  CustomList    *custom_list;

  g_return_val_if_fail (CUSTOM_IS_LIST (tree_model), FALSE);

  custom_list = CUSTOM_LIST(tree_model);

  /* a list has only top-level rows */
  if(parent)
    return FALSE;

  /* special case: if parent == NULL, set iter to n-th top-level row */

  if( n &gt;= custom_list-&gt;num_rows )
    return FALSE;

  record = custom_list-&gt;rows[n];

  g_assert( record != NULL );
  g_assert( record-&gt;pos == n );

  iter-&gt;stamp = custom_list-&gt;stamp;
  iter-&gt;user_data = record;

  return TRUE;
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_iter_parent: Point 'iter' to the parent node of 'child'. As
 *                           we have a list and thus no children and no
 *                           parents of children, we can just return FALSE.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

static gboolean
custom_list_iter_parent (GtkTreeModel *tree_model,
                         GtkTreeIter  *iter,
                         GtkTreeIter  *child)
{
  return FALSE;
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_new:  This is what you use in your own code to create a
 *                    new custom list tree model for you to use.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

CustomList *
custom_list_new (void)
{
  CustomList *newcustomlist;

  newcustomlist = (CustomList*) g_object_new (CUSTOM_TYPE_LIST, NULL);

  g_assert( newcustomlist != NULL );

  return newcustomlist;
}


/*****************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_list_append_record:  Empty lists are boring. This function can
 *                              be used in your own code to add rows to the
 *                              list. Note how we emit the "row-inserted"
 *                              signal after we have appended the row
 *                              internally, so the tree view and other
 *                              interested objects know about the new row.
 *
 *****************************************************************************/

void
custom_list_append_record (CustomList   *custom_list,
                           const gchar  *name,
                           guint         year_born)
{
  GtkTreeIter   iter;
  GtkTreePath  *path;
  CustomRecord *newrecord;
  gulong        newsize;
  guint         pos;

  g_return_if_fail (CUSTOM_IS_LIST(custom_list));
  g_return_if_fail (name != NULL);

  pos = custom_list-&gt;num_rows;

  custom_list-&gt;num_rows++;

  newsize = custom_list-&gt;num_rows * sizeof(CustomRecord*);

  custom_list-&gt;rows = g_realloc(custom_list-&gt;rows, newsize);

  newrecord = g_new0(CustomRecord, 1);

  newrecord-&gt;name = g_strdup(name);
  newrecord-&gt;name_collate_key = g_utf8_collate_key(name,-1); /* for fast sorting, used later */
  newrecord-&gt;year_born = year_born;

  custom_list-&gt;rows[pos] = newrecord;
  newrecord-&gt;pos = pos;

  /* inform the tree view and other interested objects
   *  (e.g. tree row references) that we have inserted
   *  a new row, and where it was inserted */

  path = gtk_tree_path_new();
  gtk_tree_path_append_index(path, newrecord-&gt;pos);

  custom_list_get_iter(GTK_TREE_MODEL(custom_list), &amp;iter, path);

  gtk_tree_model_row_inserted(GTK_TREE_MODEL(custom_list), path, &amp;iter);

  gtk_tree_path_free(path);
}

</programlisting>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><link
            linkend="sec-custom-model-code-header">custom-list.h</link></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><link
            linkend="sec-custom-model-code-body">custom-list.c</link></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><link
            linkend="sec-custom-model-code-example">main.c</link></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-custom-model-code-example">
        <title>main.c</title>

        <para>The following couple of lines provide a working test case that
        makes use of our custom list. It creates one of our custom lists, adds
        some records, and displays it in a tree view.</para>

        <programlisting role="C">

#include "custom-list.h"
#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;

void
fill_model (CustomList *customlist)
{
  const gchar  *firstnames[] = { "Joe", "Jane", "William", "Hannibal", "Timothy", "Gargamel", NULL } ;
  const gchar  *surnames[]   = { "Grokowich", "Twitch", "Borheimer", "Bork", NULL } ;
  const gchar **fname, **sname;

  for (sname = surnames;  *sname != NULL;  sname++)
  {
    for (fname = firstnames;  *fname != NULL;  fname++)
    {
      gchar *name = g_strdup_printf ("%s %s", *fname, *sname);

      custom_list_append_record (customlist, name, 1900 + (guint) (103.0*rand()/(RAND_MAX+1900.0)));

      g_free(name);
    }
  }
}

GtkWidget *
create_view_and_model (void)
{
  GtkTreeViewColumn   *col;
  GtkCellRenderer     *renderer;
  CustomList          *customlist;
  GtkWidget           *view;

  customlist = custom_list_new();
  fill_model(customlist);

  view = gtk_tree_view_new_with_model(GTK_TREE_MODEL(customlist));

  g_object_unref(customlist); /* destroy store automatically with view */

  renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();
  col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();

  gtk_tree_view_column_pack_start (col, renderer, TRUE);
  gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute (col, renderer, "text", CUSTOM_LIST_COL_NAME);
  gtk_tree_view_column_set_title (col, "Name");
  gtk_tree_view_append_column(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view),col);

  renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();
  col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();
  gtk_tree_view_column_pack_start (col, renderer, TRUE);
  gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute (col, renderer, "text", CUSTOM_LIST_COL_YEAR_BORN);
  gtk_tree_view_column_set_title (col, "Year Born");
  gtk_tree_view_append_column(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view),col);

  return view;
}

int
main (int argc, char **argv)
{
  GtkWidget *window, *view, *scrollwin;

  gtk_init(&amp;argc,&amp;argv);

  window = gtk_window_new(GTK_WINDOW_TOPLEVEL);
  gtk_window_set_default_size (GTK_WINDOW(window), 200, 400);
  g_signal_connect(window, "delete_event", gtk_main_quit, NULL);

  scrollwin = gtk_scrolled_window_new(NULL,NULL);

  view = create_view_and_model();

  gtk_container_add(GTK_CONTAINER(scrollwin), view);
  gtk_container_add(GTK_CONTAINER(window), scrollwin);

  gtk_widget_show_all(window);

  gtk_main();

  return 0;
}

</programlisting>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-custom-cell-renderers">
    <title>Writing Custom Cell Renderers</title>

    <para>The cell renderers that come with Gtk+ should be sufficient for most
    purposes, but there might be occasions where you want to display something
    in a tree view that you cannot display with the provided cell renderers,
    or where you want to derive from one of the provided cell renderers to
    extend its functionality.</para>

    <para>You can do this by writing a new object that derives from
    <literal>GtkCellRenderer</literal> (or even one of the other cell
    renderers if you just want to extend an existing one).</para>

    <para>Three things you need to do in the course of that:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Register some new properties that your renderer needs with the
        type system and write your own <literal>set_property</literal> and
        <literal>get_property</literal> functions to set and get your new
        renderer's properties.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Write your own <literal>cell_renderer_get_size</literal>
        function and override the parent object's function (usually the parent
        is of type <literal>GtkCellRenderer</literal>. Note that you should
        honour the standard properties for padding and cell alignment of the
        parent object here.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Write your own <literal>cell_renderer_render</literal> function
        and override the parent object's function. This function does the
        actual rendering.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The GObject type system stuff of writing a new cell renderer is
    similar to what we have done above when writing a custom tree model, and
    is relatively straight forward in this case. Copy and paste and modify
    according to your own needs.</para>

    <para>Good examples of cell renderer code to look at or even modify are
    <literal>GtkCellRendererPixbuf</literal> and
    <literal>GtkCellRendererToggle</literal> in the Gtk+ source code tree.
    Both cases are less than five hundred lines of code to look at and thus
    should be fairly easy to digest.</para>

    <sect1 id="sec-custom-cell-renderer-example">
      <title>Working Example: a Progress Bar Cell Renderer</title>

      <para>In the following we will write a custom cell renderer to render
      progress bars into a tree view (the code was "heavily inspired" by Sean
      Egan's progress bar cell renderer implementation in GAIM):</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><link
          linkend="sec-custom-cell-renderer-example-header">custom-cell-renderer-progressbar.h</link></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><link
          linkend="sec-custom-cell-renderer-example-body">custom-cell-renderer-progressbar.c</link></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><link
          linkend="sec-custom-cell-renderer-example-test">main.c</link></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <sect2 id="sec-custom-cell-renderer-example-header">
        <title>custom-cell-renderer-progressbar.h</title>

        <para>The header file consists of the usual GObject type cast and type
        check defines and our <literal>CustomCellRendererProgress</literal>
        structure. As the type of the parent indicates, we derive from
        <literal>GtkCellRenderer</literal>. The parent object must always be
        the first item in the structure (note also that it is not a pointer to
        an object, but the parent object structure itself embedded in our
        structure).</para>

        <para>Our <literal>CustomCellRendererProgress</literal> structure is
        fairly uneventful and contains only a double precision float variable
        in which we store our new <literal>"percentage"</literal> property
        (which will determine how long the progressbar is going to be).</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
  #ifndef _custom_cell_renderer_progressbar_included_
  #define _custom_cell_renderer_progressbar_included_

  #include &lt;gtk/gtk.h&gt;

  /* Some boilerplate GObject type check and type cast macros.
   *  'klass' is used here instead of 'class', because 'class'
   *  is a c++ keyword */

  #define CUSTOM_TYPE_CELL_RENDERER_PROGRESS             (custom_cell_renderer_progress_get_type())
  #define CUSTOM_CELL_RENDERER_PROGRESS(obj)             (G_TYPE_CHECK_INSTANCE_CAST((obj),  CUSTOM_TYPE_CELL_RENDERER_PROGRESS, CustomCellRendererProgress))
  #define CUSTOM_CELL_RENDERER_PROGRESS_CLASS(klass)     (G_TYPE_CHECK_CLASS_CAST ((klass),  CUSTOM_TYPE_CELL_RENDERER_PROGRESS, CustomCellRendererProgressClass))
  #define CUSTOM_IS_CELL_PROGRESS_PROGRESS(obj)          (G_TYPE_CHECK_INSTANCE_TYPE ((obj), CUSTOM_TYPE_CELL_RENDERER_PROGRESS))
  #define CUSTOM_IS_CELL_PROGRESS_PROGRESS_CLASS(klass)  (G_TYPE_CHECK_CLASS_TYPE ((klass),  CUSTOM_TYPE_CELL_RENDERER_PROGRESS))
  #define CUSTOM_CELL_RENDERER_PROGRESS_GET_CLASS(obj)   (G_TYPE_INSTANCE_GET_CLASS ((obj),  CUSTOM_TYPE_CELL_RENDERER_PROGRESS, CustomCellRendererProgressClass))

  typedef struct _CustomCellRendererProgress CustomCellRendererProgress;
  typedef struct _CustomCellRendererProgressClass CustomCellRendererProgressClass;

  /* CustomCellRendererProgress: Our custom cell renderer
   *   structure. Extend according to need */

  struct _CustomCellRendererProgress
  {
    GtkCellRenderer   parent;

    gdouble           progress;
  };


  struct _CustomCellRendererProgressClass
  {
    GtkCellRendererClass  parent_class;
  };


  GType                custom_cell_renderer_progress_get_type (void);

  GtkCellRenderer     *custom_cell_renderer_progress_new (void);


  #endif /* _custom_cell_renderer_progressbar_included_ */
</programlisting>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-custom-cell-renderer-example-body">
        <title>custom-cell-renderer-progressbar.c</title>

        <para>The code contains everything as described above, so let's jump
        right into it:</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
#include "custom-cell-renderer-progressbar.h"

/* This is based mainly on GtkCellRendererProgress
 *  in GAIM, written and (c) 2002 by Sean Egan
 *  (Licensed under the GPL), which in turn is
 *  based on Gtk's GtkCellRenderer[Text|Toggle|Pixbuf]
 *  implementation by Jonathan Blandford */

/* Some boring function declarations: GObject type system stuff */

static void     custom_cell_renderer_progress_init       (CustomCellRendererProgress      *cellprogress);

static void     custom_cell_renderer_progress_class_init (CustomCellRendererProgressClass *klass);

static void     custom_cell_renderer_progress_get_property  (GObject                    *object,
                                                             guint                       param_id,
                                                             GValue                     *value,
                                                             GParamSpec                 *pspec);

static void     custom_cell_renderer_progress_set_property  (GObject                    *object,
                                                             guint                       param_id,
                                                             const GValue               *value,
                                                             GParamSpec                 *pspec);

static void     custom_cell_renderer_progress_finalize (GObject *gobject);


/* These functions are the heart of our custom cell renderer: */

static void     custom_cell_renderer_progress_get_size   (GtkCellRenderer            *cell,
                                                          GtkWidget                  *widget,
                                                          GdkRectangle               *cell_area,
                                                          gint                       *x_offset,
                                                          gint                       *y_offset,
                                                          gint                       *width,
                                                          gint                       *height);

static void     custom_cell_renderer_progress_render     (GtkCellRenderer            *cell,
                                                          GdkWindow                  *window,
                                                          GtkWidget                  *widget,
                                                          GdkRectangle               *background_area,
                                                          GdkRectangle               *cell_area,
                                                          GdkRectangle               *expose_area,
                                                          guint                       flags);


enum
{
  PROP_PERCENTAGE = 1,
};

static   gpointer parent_class;


/***************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_cell_renderer_progress_get_type: here we register our type with
 *                                          the GObject type system if we
 *                                          haven't done so yet. Everything
 *                                          else is done in the callbacks.
 *
 ***************************************************************************/

GType
custom_cell_renderer_progress_get_type (void)
{
  static GType cell_progress_type = 0;

  if (cell_progress_type)
    return cell_progress_type;

  if (1)
  {
    static const GTypeInfo cell_progress_info =
    {
      sizeof (CustomCellRendererProgressClass),
      NULL,                                                     /* base_init */
      NULL,                                                     /* base_finalize */
      (GClassInitFunc) custom_cell_renderer_progress_class_init,
      NULL,                                                     /* class_finalize */
      NULL,                                                     /* class_data */
      sizeof (CustomCellRendererProgress),
      0,                                                        /* n_preallocs */
      (GInstanceInitFunc) custom_cell_renderer_progress_init,
    };

    /* Derive from GtkCellRenderer */
    cell_progress_type = g_type_register_static (GTK_TYPE_CELL_RENDERER,
                                                 "CustomCellRendererProgress",
                                                  &amp;cell_progress_info,
                                                  0);
  }

  return cell_progress_type;
}


/***************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_cell_renderer_progress_init: set some default properties of the
 *                                      parent (GtkCellRenderer).
 *
 ***************************************************************************/

static void
custom_cell_renderer_progress_init (CustomCellRendererProgress *cellrendererprogress)
{
  GTK_CELL_RENDERER(cellrendererprogress)-&gt;mode = GTK_CELL_RENDERER_MODE_INERT;
  GTK_CELL_RENDERER(cellrendererprogress)-&gt;xpad = 2;
  GTK_CELL_RENDERER(cellrendererprogress)-&gt;ypad = 2;
}


/***************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_cell_renderer_progress_class_init:
 *
 *  set up our own get_property and set_property functions, and
 *  override the parent's functions that we need to implement.
 *  And make our new "percentage" property known to the type system.
 *  If you want cells that can be activated on their own (ie. not
 *  just the whole row selected) or cells that are editable, you
 *  will need to override 'activate' and 'start_editing' as well.
 *
 ***************************************************************************/

static void
custom_cell_renderer_progress_class_init (CustomCellRendererProgressClass *klass)
{
  GtkCellRendererClass *cell_class   = GTK_CELL_RENDERER_CLASS(klass);
  GObjectClass         *object_class = G_OBJECT_CLASS(klass);

  parent_class           = g_type_class_peek_parent (klass);
  object_class-&gt;finalize = custom_cell_renderer_progress_finalize;

  /* Hook up functions to set and get our
   *   custom cell renderer properties */
  object_class-&gt;get_property = custom_cell_renderer_progress_get_property;
  object_class-&gt;set_property = custom_cell_renderer_progress_set_property;

  /* Override the two crucial functions that are the heart
   *   of a cell renderer in the parent class */
  cell_class-&gt;get_size = custom_cell_renderer_progress_get_size;
  cell_class-&gt;render   = custom_cell_renderer_progress_render;

  /* Install our very own properties */
  g_object_class_install_property (object_class,
                                   PROP_PERCENTAGE,
                                   g_param_spec_double ("percentage",
                                                        "Percentage",
                                                         "The fractional progress to display",
                                                         0, 1, 0,
                                                         G_PARAM_READWRITE));
}


/***************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_cell_renderer_progress_finalize: free any resources here
 *
 ***************************************************************************/

static void
custom_cell_renderer_progress_finalize (GObject *object)
{
/*
  CustomCellRendererProgress *cellrendererprogress = CUSTOM_CELL_RENDERER_PROGRESS(object);
*/

  /* Free any dynamically allocated resources here */

  (* G_OBJECT_CLASS (parent_class)-&gt;finalize) (object);
}


/***************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_cell_renderer_progress_get_property: as it says
 *
 ***************************************************************************/

static void
custom_cell_renderer_progress_get_property (GObject    *object,
                                            guint       param_id,
                                            GValue     *value,
                                            GParamSpec *psec)
{
  CustomCellRendererProgress  *cellprogress = CUSTOM_CELL_RENDERER_PROGRESS(object);

  switch (param_id)
  {
    case PROP_PERCENTAGE:
      g_value_set_double(value, cellprogress-&gt;progress);
      break;

    default:
      G_OBJECT_WARN_INVALID_PROPERTY_ID (object, param_id, psec);
      break;
  }
}


/***************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_cell_renderer_progress_set_property: as it says
 *
 ***************************************************************************/

static void
custom_cell_renderer_progress_set_property (GObject      *object,
                                            guint         param_id,
                                            const GValue *value,
                                            GParamSpec   *pspec)
{
  CustomCellRendererProgress *cellprogress = CUSTOM_CELL_RENDERER_PROGRESS (object);

  switch (param_id)
  {
    case PROP_PERCENTAGE:
      cellprogress-&gt;progress = g_value_get_double(value);
      break;

    default:
      G_OBJECT_WARN_INVALID_PROPERTY_ID(object, param_id, pspec);
      break;
  }
}

/***************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_cell_renderer_progress_new: return a new cell renderer instance
 *
 ***************************************************************************/

GtkCellRenderer *
custom_cell_renderer_progress_new (void)
{
  return g_object_new(CUSTOM_TYPE_CELL_RENDERER_PROGRESS, NULL);
}


/***************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_cell_renderer_progress_get_size: crucial - calculate the size
 *                                          of our cell, taking into account
 *                                          padding and alignment properties
 *                                          of parent.
 *
 ***************************************************************************/

#define FIXED_WIDTH   100
#define FIXED_HEIGHT  10

static void
custom_cell_renderer_progress_get_size (GtkCellRenderer *cell,
                                        GtkWidget       *widget,
                                        GdkRectangle    *cell_area,
                                        gint            *x_offset,
                                        gint            *y_offset,
                                        gint            *width,
                                        gint            *height)
{
  gint calc_width;
  gint calc_height;

  calc_width  = (gint) cell-&gt;xpad * 2 + FIXED_WIDTH;
  calc_height = (gint) cell-&gt;ypad * 2 + FIXED_HEIGHT;

  if (width)
    *width = calc_width;

  if (height)
    *height = calc_height;

  if (cell_area)
  {
    if (x_offset)
    {
      *x_offset = cell-&gt;xalign * (cell_area-&gt;width - calc_width);
      *x_offset = MAX (*x_offset, 0);
    }

    if (y_offset)
    {
      *y_offset = cell-&gt;yalign * (cell_area-&gt;height - calc_height);
      *y_offset = MAX (*y_offset, 0);
    }
  }
}99


/***************************************************************************
 *
 *  custom_cell_renderer_progress_render: crucial - do the rendering.
 *
 ***************************************************************************/

static void
custom_cell_renderer_progress_render (GtkCellRenderer *cell,
                                      GdkWindow       *window,
                                      GtkWidget       *widget,
                                      GdkRectangle    *background_area,
                                      GdkRectangle    *cell_area,
                                      GdkRectangle    *expose_area,
                                      guint            flags)
{
  CustomCellRendererProgress *cellprogress = CUSTOM_CELL_RENDERER_PROGRESS (cell);
  GtkStateType                state;
  gint                        width, height;
  gint                        x_offset, y_offset;

  custom_cell_renderer_progress_get_size (cell, widget, cell_area,
                                          &amp;x_offset, &amp;y_offset,
                                          &amp;width, &amp;height);

  if (GTK_WIDGET_HAS_FOCUS (widget))
    state = GTK_STATE_ACTIVE;
  else
    state = GTK_STATE_NORMAL;

  width  -= cell-&gt;xpad*2;
  height -= cell-&gt;ypad*2;

  gtk_paint_box (widget-&gt;style,
                 window,
                 GTK_STATE_NORMAL, GTK_SHADOW_IN,
                 NULL, widget, "trough",
                 cell_area-&gt;x + x_offset + cell-&gt;xpad,
                 cell_area-&gt;y + y_offset + cell-&gt;ypad,
                 width - 1, height - 1);

  gtk_paint_box (widget-&gt;style,
                 window,
                 state, GTK_SHADOW_OUT,
                 NULL, widget, "bar",
                 cell_area-&gt;x + x_offset + cell-&gt;xpad,
                 cell_area-&gt;y + y_offset + cell-&gt;ypad,
                 width * cellprogress-&gt;progress,
                 height - 1);
}

</programlisting>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec-custom-cell-renderer-example-test">
        <title>main.c</title>

        <para>And here is a little test that makes use of our new
        <literal>CustomCellRendererProgress</literal>:</para>

        <programlisting role="C">
#include "custom-cell-renderer-progressbar.h"

static GtkListStore        *liststore;

static gboolean             increasing = TRUE;   /* direction of progress bar change */

enum
{
  COL_PERCENTAGE = 0,
  COL_TEXT,
  NUM_COLS
};

#define STEP  0.01

gboolean
increase_progress_timeout (GtkCellRenderer *renderer)
{
  GtkTreeIter  iter;
  gfloat       perc = 0.0;
  gchar        buf[20];

  gtk_tree_model_get_iter_first(GTK_TREE_MODEL(liststore), &amp;iter); /* first and only row */

  gtk_tree_model_get (GTK_TREE_MODEL(liststore), &amp;iter, COL_PERCENTAGE, &amp;perc, -1);

  if ( perc &gt; (1.0-STEP)  ||  (perc &lt; STEP &amp;&amp; perc &gt; 0.0) )
  {
    increasing = (!increasing);
  }

  if (increasing)
    perc = perc + STEP;
  else
    perc = perc - STEP;

  g_snprintf(buf, sizeof(buf), "%u %%", (guint)(perc*100));

  gtk_list_store_set (liststore, &amp;iter, COL_PERCENTAGE, perc, COL_TEXT, buf, -1);

  return TRUE; /* Call again */
}


GtkWidget *
create_view_and_model (void)
{
  GtkTreeViewColumn   *col;
  GtkCellRenderer     *renderer;
  GtkTreeIter          iter;
  GtkWidget           *view;

  liststore = gtk_list_store_new(NUM_COLS, G_TYPE_FLOAT, G_TYPE_STRING);
  gtk_list_store_append(liststore, &amp;iter);
  gtk_list_store_set (liststore, &amp;iter, COL_PERCENTAGE, 0.5, -1); /* start at 50% */

  view = gtk_tree_view_new_with_model(GTK_TREE_MODEL(liststore));

  g_object_unref(liststore); /* destroy store automatically with view */

  renderer = gtk_cell_renderer_text_new();
  col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();
  gtk_tree_view_column_pack_start (col, renderer, TRUE);
  gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute (col, renderer, "text", COL_TEXT);
  gtk_tree_view_column_set_title (col, "Progress");
  gtk_tree_view_append_column(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view),col);

  renderer = custom_cell_renderer_progress_new();
  col = gtk_tree_view_column_new();
  gtk_tree_view_column_pack_start (col, renderer, TRUE);
  gtk_tree_view_column_add_attribute (col, renderer, "percentage", COL_PERCENTAGE);
  gtk_tree_view_column_set_title (col, "Progress");
  gtk_tree_view_append_column(GTK_TREE_VIEW(view),col);

  g_timeout_add(50, (GSourceFunc) increase_progress_timeout, NULL);

  return view;
}


int
main (int argc, char **argv)
{
  GtkWidget *window, *view;

  gtk_init(&amp;argc,&amp;argv);

  window = gtk_window_new(GTK_WINDOW_TOPLEVEL);
  gtk_window_set_default_size (GTK_WINDOW(window), 150, 100);
  g_signal_connect(window, "delete_event", gtk_main_quit, NULL);

  view = create_view_and_model();

  gtk_container_add(GTK_CONTAINER(window), view);

  gtk_widget_show_all(window);

  gtk_main();

  return 0;
}

</programlisting>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-custom-cell-renderers-external">
      <title>Cell Renderers Others Have Written</title>

      <para>Just in case you are one of those people who do not like to
      re-invent the wheel, here is a list of custom cell renderers other
      people have written:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/gaim/gaim/src/gtkcellrendererprogress.c">Progress
          bar cell renderer</ulink> (gaim)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://cvs.gnome.org/bonsai/cvsblame.cgi?file=mrproject%2Fsrc%2Fcell-renderers/mg-cell-renderer-date.c&amp;rev=&amp;root=/cvs/gnome">Date
          cell renderer</ulink> (mrproject) (is this one easy to
          re-use?)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://cvs.gnome.org/bonsai/cvsblame.cgi?file=mrproject%2Fsrc%2Fcell-renderers/mg-cell-renderer-list.c&amp;rev=&amp;root=/cvs/gnome">List/combo
          cell renderer</ulink> (mrproject) (is this one easy to
          re-use?)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://cvs.gnome.org/bonsai/cvsblame.cgi?file=mrproject%2Fsrc%2Fcell-renderers/mg-cell-renderer-popup.c&amp;rev=&amp;root=/cvs/gnome">Pop-up
          cell renderer</ulink> (mrproject) (what does this do?)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Your custom cell renderer here?!</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-other-info">
    <title>Other Resources</title>

    <para>A short tutorial like this cannot possibly cover everything.
    Luckily, there is a lot more information out there. Here is a list of
    links that you might find useful (if you have any links that should appear
    here as well, please send them to <literal>tim at centricular dot
    net</literal>).</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gtk/index.html">Gtk+ API
        Reference Manual</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/gdk/index.html">Gdk API
        Reference Manual</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/pango/index.html">Pango
        API Reference Manual</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/2.0/glib/index.html">GLib API
        Reference Manual</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gtk-app-devel-list/index.html">gtk-app-devel
        mailing list archives</ulink> - search them!</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://cvs.gnome.org/bonsai/rview.cgi?cvsroot=/cvs/gnome&amp;dir=gtk%2b/demos/gtk-demo">gtk-demo</ulink>
        - part of the Gtk+ source code (look in gtk+-2.x.y/demos/gtk-demo),
        especially <ulink
        url="http://cvs.gnome.org/bonsai/cvsblame.cgi?file=gtk%2B%2Fdemos%2Fgtk-demo/list_store.c&amp;rev=&amp;root=/cvs/gnome">list_store.c</ulink>,
        <ulink
        url="http://cvs.gnome.org/bonsai/cvsblame.cgi?file=gtk%2B%2Fdemos%2Fgtk-demo/tree_store.c&amp;rev=&amp;root=/cvs/gnome">tree_store.c</ulink>,
        and <ulink
        url="http://cvs.gnome.org/bonsai/cvsblame.cgi?file=gtk%2B%2Fdemos%2Fgtk-demo/stock_browser.c&amp;rev=&amp;root=/cvs/gnome">stock_browser.c</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.gtkmm.org/gtkmm2/docs/tutorial/html/ch08.html">TreeView
        tutorial using Gtk's C++ interface (gtkmm)</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://liw.iki.fi/liw/texts/gtktreeview-tutorial.html">TreeView
        tutorial using Gtk's python interface</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Some slides from Owen Taylor's GUADEC 2003 <ulink
        url="http://people.redhat.com/otaylor/tutorial/guadec2003/">tutorial</ulink>
        (<ulink
        url="http://people.redhat.com/otaylor/tutorial/guadec2003/gtk-tut.ps">postscript</ulink>,
        <ulink
        url="http://people.redhat.com/otaylor/tutorial/guadec2003/gtk-tut.pdf">pdf</ulink>,
        see pages 13-15)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.gnome.org/softwaremap/">Existing
        applications</ulink> - yes, they exist, and <emphasis>you</emphasis>
        can look at their source code. <ulink
        url="http://sourceforge.net/">SourceForge's</ulink> WebCVS browse
        feature is quite useful, and the same goes for <ulink
        url="http://cvs.gnome.org/bonsai/rview.cgi?cvsroot=/cvs/gnome">GNOME</ulink>
        as well.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If your intention is to display external data (from a database,
        or in XML form) as a list or tree or table, you might also be
        interested <ulink url="http://www.gnome-db.org/">GnomeDB</ulink>,
        especially libgda and libgnomedb (e.g. the GnomeDBGrid widget). See
        also <ulink url="ftp://kalamazoolinux.org/pub/pdf/dbaccess.pdf">this
        PDF presentation</ulink> (page 24ff).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>your link here!</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="sec-treeviewtut-license">
    <title>Copyright, License, Credits, and Revision History</title>

    <sect1 id="sec-treeviewtut-copyright-license">
      <title>Copyright and License</title>

      <para>Copyright (c) 2003-2004 Tim-Philipp Müller <email>tim at
      centricular dot net</email></para>

      <para>This tutorial may be redistributed and modified freely in any
      form, as long as all authors are given due credit for their work and all
      non-trivial changes by third parties are clearly marked as such either
      within the document (e.g. in a revision history), or at an external and
      publicly accessible place that is refered to in the document (e.g. a CVS
      repository).</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treeviewtut-credits">
      <title>Credits</title>

      <para>Thanks to Axel C. for proof-reading the first drafts, for many
      suggestions, and for introducing me to the tree view widget in the first
      place (back then when I was still convinced that porting to Gtk+-2.x was
      unnecessary, Gtk+-1.2 applications looked nice, and Aristotle had
      already said everything about politics that needs to be said).</para>

      <para>Harring Figueiredo <ulink
      url="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gtk-app-devel-list/2003-September/msg00240.html">shed</ulink>
      some light on how GtkListStore and GtkTreeStore deal with
      pixbufs.</para>

      <para>Ken Rastatter <ulink
      url="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gtk-app-devel-list/2003-September/msg00250.html">suggested</ulink>
      some additional topics (with complete references even).</para>

      <para>Both Andrej Prsa and Alan B. Canon sent me a couple of
      suggestions, and 'taf2', Massimo Mangoni and others spotted some
      typos.</para>

      <para>Many thanks to all of them, and of course also to kris and
      everyone else in #gtk+.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec-treeviewtut-history">
      <title>Revision History</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>5th June 2005</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>Remove unnecessary col = gtk_tree_view_column_new() im hello
          world code (leftover from migration to convenience
          functions).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>3rd February 2005</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>Point out that GObjects such as GdkPixbufs retrieved with
          gtk_tree_model_get() need to be g_object_unref()'ed after use, as
          gtk_tree_model_get() adds a reference.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added explicit (gint) event-&gt;x double to int conversion to
          code snippet using gtk_tree_view_get_path_at_pos() to avoid compiler
          warnings.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>9th September 2004</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed another mistake in tree path explanation: text did not
          correspond picture (s/movie clips/movie trailers/); (thanks to
          Benjamin Brandt for spotting it).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>6th August 2004</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed mistake in tree path explanation (s/4th/5th/) (thanks to
          both Andrew Kirillov and Benjamin Brandt for spotting it).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>30th April 2004</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added Hello World</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>31st March 2004</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed fatal typo in custom list code: g_assert() in
          custom_list_init() should be ==, not != (spotted by mmc).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added link to Owen Taylor's mail on the GtkTreeView
          Drag'n'Drop API.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>24th January 2004</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed typo in code example (remove n-th row example) (Thanks
          to roel for spotting it).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Changed 'Context menus' section title</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>19th January 2004</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>Expanded section on GtkTreeRowReferences, and on removing
          multiple rows.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>8th January 2004</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added tiny section on Glade and treeviews</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added more detail to the section describing GtkTreePath,
          GtkTreeIter et.al.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Reformatted document structure: instead of one single chapter
          with lots of sections, have multiple chapters (this tutorial is way
          to big to become part of the Gtk+ tutorial anyway); enumerate
          chapters and sections.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Expanded the section on tree view columns and cell renderers,
          with help of two diagrams by Owen Taylor (from the GUADEC 2003 Gtk+
          tutorial slides).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>10th December 2003</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added more information about how to remove a single row, or
          more specifically, the n-th row of a list store</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added a short example about how to pack icons into the tree
          view.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>28th October 2003</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>Editable cells will work fine even if selection is set to
          GTK_SELECTION_NONE. Removed sentences that say otherwise.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>23rd October 2003</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>fix 'jumpy' selections in custom model GtkTreeSortable
          interface implementation. gtk_tree_model_rows_reordered() does not
          seem to work like the API reference implies (see <ulink
          url="http://bugs.gnome.org/show_bug.cgi?id=124790">bug
          #124790</ulink>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>added section about how to get the cell renderer a button
          click happened on</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>added section about editable cells with spin buttons (and a
          CellRendererSpin implementation to the examples)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>10th October 2003</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>make custom model GtkTreeSortable implementation emit
          "sort-column-changed" signal when sortid is changed</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>fixed code typo in selection function section; added a
          paragraph about rule hint to 'make whole row coloured or bold'
          section</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>7th October 2003</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>Reformatted source code to make it fit on pages when
          generating ps/pdf output</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added link to PDF and docbook XML versions.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
</book>
